<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[35% Campaign]]></title>
  <link href="http://35percent.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://35percent.org/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-21T14:17:30+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://35percent.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[EAN]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build to Rent - Public Funds for Private Homes]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/06/19/housing-minister-visits-new-heygate/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-19T20:04:16+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/06/19/housing-minister-visits-new-heygate</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Was great to welcome <a href="https://twitter.com/BrandonLewis">@brandonlewis</a> from <a href="https://twitter.com/CommunitiesUK">@CommunitiesUK</a> today at <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/TrafalgarPlace?src=hash">#TrafalgarPlace</a>. We hope you enjoyed your visit <a href="http://t.co/R2Ld2SL8PZ">pic.twitter.com/R2Ld2SL8PZ</a></p>&mdash; Elephant Park (@ElephantParkLDN) <a href="https://twitter.com/ElephantParkLDN/status/606461178991255552">June 4, 2015</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/28/manifesto-for-destruction-of-council-estates/">blogged in February</a> about Labour Lord Adonis&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/8192">visit to the Elephant &amp; Castle</a> and his <a href="http://www.ippr.org/publications/city-villages-more-homes-better-communities">manifesto</a> for the destruction of the council estates. Now Tory Housing Minister Brandon Lewis has <a href="https://twitter.com/ElephantParkLDN/status/606512000261345280">visited the redeveloped Heygate</a> and made a <a href="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/e764af1c-0f6a-11e5-897e-00144feabdc0.html">similar call</a>, in what appears to be a race to the bottom in UK housing policy.</p>

<p>In his <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/brandon-lewis-speaks-at-the-london-real-estate-forum">speech</a> at the <a href="http://www.lref.co.uk/">London Real Estate Forum</a>, Lewis vowed to <em>&ldquo;regenerate those inner city estates that are dominated by the high-rise blocks of the 1960s and 70s&rdquo;</em> and claimed that <em>&ldquo;completely rebuilding these estates will provide more homes and commercial space using the same amount of land.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>He referred to a report he <a href="http://www.savills.co.uk/_news/article/72418/175241-0/04/2014/savills-research--london-regeneration-research-proposal">commissioned</a> last year from Savills, which claims that <em>&ldquo;rediscovering just half of this former housing capacity would supply London’s expected housing needs for the next 17 years.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/revitalising.png" width="350" height="350">We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/08/southwark-fails-to-deliver/">blogged</a> last year about Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/download/3934/the_new_southwark_plan">draft new planning policy</a>, which praises the Heygate regeneration and proposes to roll out similar schemes across the borough.
We also <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">wrote</a> about the assessment Southwark had <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SNhat.pdf">commissioned</a> from Savills, to establish which of its council estates were no longer &lsquo;viable&rsquo;. Rumour has it that this assessment is now complete but the results have not been published. As soon as this &lsquo;disposals list&rsquo; is made public, we&rsquo;ll be looking to explain to tenants &amp; residents groups affected exactly what regeneration means.<br/>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>Build to Rent (but don&rsquo;t ask what the rents are)</h2>

<p>Brandon Lewis has also <a href="http://www.egi.co.uk/news/lewis-announces-252m-prs-boost/">announced</a> the third round of successful bidders in the government&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/1000-new-homes-for-private-rent-in-london">Build to Rent fund</a>.</p>

<p>&lsquo;Build to rent&rsquo; or PRS is the Conservative government&rsquo;s answer to the housing crisis, with which it subsidises the building of homes for rent, but without imposing constraints on how much those rents will be. Last year we <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/07/19/community-infrastructure-levy/">reported</a> that Delancey had let slip that its new PRS homes at the Elephant are expected to fetch £375pw for 1-bed and £500pw for a 2-bed.</p>

<p>Most housing associations have snubbed the PRS funding on the grounds that it doesn&rsquo;t create housing affordable for those in need. As usual Notting Hill Housing saw pound signs and was one of the first to apply. So far it has been <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/build-to-rent-round-1-allocations/build-to-rent-round-1-signed-contracts">allocated</a> £17m in the first round of the funding to build 181 PRS homes in London. We don&rsquo;t know how many of these will be on the new Aylesbury, but we do now know that despite its insistence that there would be no &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; homes on the Aylesbury, the Mayor has now <a href="http://questions.london.gov.uk/QuestionSearch/searchclient/questions/question_282124">confirmed</a> that he has allocated funding for at least 450 new homes on the Aylesbury at - guess what? affordable rent.</p>

<p>Also receiving PRS funding was Richard Rogers&#8217; <a href="http://35percent.org/london-360-tower">London 360 Tower</a> on the site of the former London Park Hotel. Note that £18m of public money was spent acquiring this site with the purpose of building affordable housing, and it is now about to receive <a href="http://www.london.gov.uk/moderngov/documents/s45702/06%20Programmes%20delegated%20to%20HCA.rtf">another £45m</a>, in order to build a development in which there won&rsquo;t be a single social rented home.</p>

<p>In summary, £63m in public funds is being spent to acquire and develop a 44-storey tower comprising what is rightly <a href="http://residential.jll.co.uk/en-gb/property-search/property-details.aspx?t=c&amp;id=JLLATC41432">described</a> by the scheme&rsquo;s advisors as <strong>&ldquo;274 private homes&rdquo;</strong>.</p>

<h2>Carrots for the masses</h2>

<p>Meanwhile council leader Peter John was also led on a tour of <a href="http://trafalgarplace.com/">&lsquo;Trafalgar Place&rsquo;</a> (phase one of the redeveloped Heygate which is nearing completion). Cllr John was particularly excited about the new &lsquo;community garden&rsquo;, which comes with a ready-grown vegetable patch.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Carrots growing well at Trafalgar Place SE17 <a href="http://t.co/IYOq4iqqrq">pic.twitter.com/IYOq4iqqrq</a></p>&mdash; Peter John (@peterjohn6) <a href="https://twitter.com/peterjohn6/status/610408022645587968">June 15, 2015</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr"><a href="https://twitter.com/35percent_EAN">@35percent_EAN</a> This is what Joe Public gets to see of the &#39;community garden&#39;. That&#39;s &#39;community&#39; as in &#39;affordable&#39;. <a href="http://t.co/H7Ft2ASyIq">pic.twitter.com/H7Ft2ASyIq</a></p>&mdash; 35% Campaign (@35percent_EAN) <a href="https://twitter.com/35percent_EAN/status/611120243033931776">June 17, 2015</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>It was left to us to point out that the &lsquo;community garden&rsquo; is situated in a raised courtyard above the parking lobby with zero public access, and that just 8 of the 235 new homes in this phase are social rented. There will be a handful affordable rented homes and shared ownership flats (<a href="http://35percent.org/images/LQPriceList.pdf">if you earn an income of £57k</a>). All in all, not much to celebrate on a site that was once home to an <a href="http://heygatewashome.org">established community</a> that has now been <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2013/06/08/the-heygate-diaspora/">scattered to the wind</a>.</p>

<h2>Urban Practitioners</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="http://action.labour.org.uk/page/-/site/img/people/headshots/helen%20hayes.jpg">One of our new Southwark MPs Helen Hayes appeared in an <a href="http://www.private-eye.co.uk/hp-sauce">article</a> in Private Eye last week. Helen took over from Tessa Jowell as MP for Dulwich and West Norwood earlier this year, but has been a Southwark councillor since 2010. The Eye took issue with her simultaneous role as boss of an architecture firm, which has not only been writing up council planning policy, but was also <a href="http://m.building.co.uk/lend-lease-wins-%C2%A315bn-regeneration-of-elephant-and-castle/3092038.article">part of the Lend Lease consortium</a> that had won the bid for the Elephant &amp; Castle regeneration and has <a href="http://www.architectsjournal.co.uk/news/allies-and-morrison-wins-go-ahead-for-first-private-homes-on-olympic-park/8656074.article">contracts</a> with Lend Lease elsewhere. Her firm has also been involved in a number of controversial developments in the borough, including the Ministry of Sound (<a href="http://35percent.org/eileen-house">Eileen House</a>) development and the <a href="http://www.alliesandmorrison.com/project/aylesbury-academy/">Aylesbury estate regeneration</a>.</p>

<h2>Urban Campaigners</h2>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='https://i-d-images.vice.com/images/articles/meta/2015/06/19/untitled-article-1434727223.jpg?crop=1xw:0.8450292397660819xh;0xw,0.005847953216374269xh&resize=1200:*&output-format=image/jpeg&output-quality=90' width='' height='' title='Marching for homes - former investment banker and Southwark regeneration boss Fiona Colley - bottom right'><span class='caption-text'>Marching for homes - former investment banker and Southwark regeneration boss Fiona Colley - bottom right</span></span>
Our very own <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=116">Cllr Fiona Colley</a> was spotted campaigning for more affordable homes and against austerity in <a href="https://i-d.vice.com/en_gb/article/why-did-the-daily-mail-paint-this-anti-austerity-campaigner-as-a-violent-extremist">this vice article</a> last week. After selling off the Heygate and Aylesbury, former investment banker Cllr Colley stepped down from her role as <strong>Cabinet member for Regeneration</strong> last year, to take up her new role as <strong>Cabinet member for Finance, Modernisation and Performance</strong>. We wonder whether she has had a change of heart, or - having snapped up two new-build flats in the Canada Water regeneration - the homes she is marching for are of a different tenure to those her fellow marchers have in mind..</p>

<h2>Aylesbury CPO Public Inquiry</h2>

<p>A date has been set for the Aylesbury CPO Inquiry to resume. The Inquiry will reconvene on Tuesday October 13th back at the Den. It is scheduled to last for two days and will hear further arguments relating to Human Rights, which the council was unable to respond to during the last hearing. This time the objectors have instructed counsel and will be represented at the hearing by a barrister from <a href="http://landmarkchambers.co.uk">Landmark Chambers</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury CPO Inquiry - Extra Time]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/16/aylesbury-cpo-inquiry-extra-time/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-16T13:54:39+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/16/aylesbury-cpo-inquiry-extra-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://www.eastlondonlines.co.uk/ell_wp/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/alanfootballclub.jpg" width="300" height="200">The Aylesury CPO Inquiry resumed back at the Den on Tuesday, but by the end of day the Inspector had decided extra time was needed. She accepted the objectors&#8217; argument that there were still legal questions to be answered, among others about the absence of a successful ballot result in favour of demolition. She also agreed that objectors needed more time to get legal assistance and that it will probably be autumn before the the inquiry resumes.  We understand that the leaseholders have since instructed Landmark Chambers to act on their behalf.</p>

<p>Tuesday&rsquo;s hearing returned to the issue of the Bermondsey Spa regeneration and the switch of tenures from social rent to affordable rent. Objectors had raised questions about this at the first hearing and in their <a href="http://35percent.org/images/Objectors_OpeningSubmissions_andAppendices.pdf">opening submission</a>, but were told that Southwark and Notting Hill Housing needed time to look into the details before answering questions.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/theexchange.jpg' width='' height='' title='Notting Hill's Bermondsey Spa regeneration'><span class='caption-text'>Notting Hill&rsquo;s Bermondsey Spa regeneration</span></span></p>

<p>On being questioned again, this time representatives from the council and Notting Hill both said they could not comment because the matter was in the hands of their respective legal departments.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, Southwark did table two &lsquo;explanatory notes&rsquo; agreed with Notting Hill about the Bermondsey Spa regeneration and four other developments, which did shed some further light on the matter. The <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/CPO_ExplanatoryNote27April2015.pdf">first</a> of these shows that wholesale changes to the tenure mix had been made post approval on all four developments and that while there was an overall increase in affordable housing of 260 units, there was a net loss in <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/ObjectorsReplyToExplantoryNote1.pdf">social rented housing of 15 homes</a>. Also in each case a broadly policy-compliant scheme was changed after planning approval to become wildly non-compliant.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/ExplanatoryNote1.png' width='' height='' title='The Council's first 'explanatory note' tabled on day 4 of the Inquiry'><span class='caption-text'>The Council&rsquo;s first &lsquo;explanatory note&rsquo; tabled on day 4 of the Inquiry</span></span></p>

<p>The <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/CPO_ExplanatoryNote12May2015.pdf">second note</a> was a strictly legal description of how in each case these changes could be justified. It does not address any of the issues about policy compliance, the correct mix of social and intermediate housing, or why the planning committee is left entirely in ignorance of the significant tenure changes being made post approval.</p>

<p>In the second note Southwark also confirmed that the definition of affordable rent used in the legal agreements <em>&ldquo;can be interpreted flexibly enough to allow them to be delivered as social rented units&rdquo;</em>. However, Notting Hill doesn&rsquo;t agree - as the note says: <em>&ldquo;It is not yet clear whether the parties agree on the correct interpretation.&rdquo;</em> Southwark has therefore <em>&ldquo;sought advice from the council&rsquo;s legal department&rdquo;</em> and Notting Hill is also <em>&ldquo;seeking advice in relation to the wording of the agreement&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/ExplanatoryNote2.png' width='' height='' title='The Council's second 'explanatory note' tabled on day 5 of the Inquiry'><span class='caption-text'>The Council&rsquo;s second &lsquo;explanatory note&rsquo; tabled on day 5 of the Inquiry</span></span></p>

<p>The problem for Notting Hill and Southwark Council is that they have been found out. By using the same legal definition for both affordable rent and social rent, they can claim to be delivering social rented housing when in actual fact they are delivering affordable rent. The question now is who is going to shoulder the blame and whether or not the affordable rented units at Bermondsey Spa (and maybe elsewhere?) will be converted to social rent.</p>

<p>If these differences cannot be resolved amicably Southwark has the option of enforcing its own interpretation, in which case Notting Hill could respond via the courts. Notting Hill Housing is Southwark&rsquo;s development partner on the Aylesbury and its largest development partner in the borough. So the Council needs to lay down the law and make sure that Notting Hill delivers the social rented homes that the borough so desperately needs, not some bogus &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; or &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; by the back door.</p>

<p><strong>Postscript Update 22/5/15</strong>
Southwark News has picked up on our tenure switch story and published an <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/southwark-council-probes-44-missing-social-homes/">article</a> with quotes from Cllr Williams, claiming that the council is <em>&ldquo;looking into the rent levels proposed at Bermondsey Spa&rdquo;</em> and that <em>&ldquo;appropriate action&rdquo;</em> will be taken. The article also confirms that Notting Hill has built a total of 1,442 homes in Southwark and that it has another 5,489 in the pipeline.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury CPO Inquiry - Into the Lion's Den]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/02/aylesbury-estate-compulsory-purchase-order-public-inquiry/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-02T09:10:32+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/02/aylesbury-estate-compulsory-purchase-order-public-inquiry</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/CDsUkrnW0AEP5X-.jpg" width="400" height="300">The Public Inquiry into the Aylesbury Compulsory Purchase Order was adjourned on Friday (until 12th May), after four days of sharp argument between Southwark Council and objectors to the order. This is the third CPO Southwark has sought in relation to the Aylesbury regeneration and we can expect many more as it seeks to get rid of leaseholders who do not accept its derisory compensation offers.</p>

<p>The Inquiry was conducted by government Inspector Leslie Coffey and was held in Arry&rsquo;s Bar at Millwall Football ground. The Inquiry had been moved to the Den to be better able to control feared protests from angry estate residents.</p>

<h2>Them and Us</h2>

<p>Southwark Council&rsquo;s large team of officers were led by barrister <a href="http://www.chambersandpartners.com/uk-bar/person/224510/melissa-murphy">Melissa Murphy</a>, whose recent work includes acting for Basildon council in the eviction of the Dale Farm gypsy and traveller site.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.peoplesrepublicofsouthwark.co.uk/images/stories/news/2804201502.jpg" width="410" height="300">Objectors included representatives from the <a href="https://halag.wordpress.com/">Aylesbury Leaseholders Action Group</a>, the 35% Campaign and former local Tory Councillor Toby Eckersley.
Over the first two days council regeneration officers detailed the background and benefits of new development with much reference to the key planning document, the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200211/area_action_plans/1327/aylesbury_area_action_plan">Aylesbury Area Action Plan</a> (AAAP) of 2009, according to which the regeneration will provide a <em>&lsquo;mixed community&rsquo;</em> comprising about 3,500 homes of great design standards with new green spaces.</p>

<h2>Social rent or not social rent?</h2>

<p>Also present was Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s Head of Regeneration, Rosemary Houseman. Ms Houseman was closely questioned by Objectors about the funding arrangements for the scheme. Under cross examination Ms Housman reluctantly admitted that the 1670 &lsquo;target rented&rsquo; Aylesbury homes that Notting Hill had received funding for under the <a href="https://www.london.gov.uk/priorities/housing-land/increasing-housing-supply/mayor-housing-covenant-2015-2018">Mayor&rsquo;s 2015-18 MHC programme</a>, were referred to in the funding allocation as affordable rent - not social rent.</p>

<h2>Non answers</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/manorplace_sr.png" width="300" height="500">Notting Hill Housing and Southwark Council were also cross examined by objectors about the <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing/">Bermondsey Spa S106 fiasco</a>, where Notting Hill had promised social rented housing but delivered affordable rent instead. Objectors raised further concerns about tenure switching at other Notting Hill developments including <a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk">Manor Place depot</a>, where <a href="http://www.manorplacedepot.co.uk/Manor-Place-Exhibition-Banners.pdf">pre-planning consultation documents</a> described <em>&ldquo;9 Social Rent Family Homes&rdquo;</em>, which subsequently disappeared into <em>&ldquo;Affordable Rent&rdquo;</em> homes when the planning application was submitted.</p>

<p>No clear answers to these questions were forthcoming - council and Notting Hill witnesses repeatedly argued that they didn&rsquo;t have the details of the schemes before them and thus couldn&rsquo;t comment. Eventually an explanatory note was promised and this arrived at 2pm of what was to be the final day of the Inquiry. These points will be taken up when the Inquiry resumes next week and we will be addressing this in our next blog.</p>

<h2>The cost</h2>

<p>Southwark Council did <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Email14April2015_KReed.pdf">confirm</a> that it had spent a staggering £46.8m on the Aylesbury regeneration scheme to date. This comprised total capital account costs of £32.1m (demolition &amp; acquisiton) and revenue account costs amounting to £14.7m (Management &amp; Administration, Master-planning, Communications, PFI, Development Partner Procurement, Feasibility Studies etc).</p>

<p>Southwark Council also <a href="http://35percent.org/images/PMcGreal_Email28April2015.pdf">confirmed</a> that some of its officers valuing leaseholders&#8217; homes were not fully qualified or RICS registered. Leaseholders had <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/ALAG_RICS.pdf">complained to RICS</a> about officers conducting the valuations, but because neither the officers in question or Southwark Council were RICS registered, they were unable to pursue the matter.</p>

<h2>&lsquo;Sham&rsquo; consultations and legal queries</h2>

<p>On the objectors&#8217; side Toby Eckersley called the consultation for the AAAP a &lsquo;sham&rsquo;. He supported his claim by reference to the evidence base supporting the council&rsquo;s decision making process. He took the Inquiry to paragraph 3.1.4 of the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/2938/consultation_report_main_report-appendix_6"><em>&ldquo;Consultation report for the Aylesbury Area Action Plan&rdquo;</em></a>, which shows that Southwark received just 33 written representations in response to its consultation on the question of demolition or refurbishment, of which only 5 supported demolition while 9 supported refurbishment (the estate is home to over 7,500 people).</p>

<p>Toby also raised several interesting legal points around whether Southwark had actually fulfilled all the procedural conditions needed to go ahead with the regeneration. He argued that several provisions of the Housing Act 1985 could be open to the interpretation that a ballot is required for a scheme to demolish an estate, especially when the scheme provides for secure tenants to be moved to a new tenancy on the site with a registered provider (i.e. stock transfer). He referred the Inquiry to the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/8289/1293538.pdf">Statutory Guidance on schedule 3A</a> and also to section 105 of the Act, which expressly mentions demolition as a housing management matter which, in principle, should be consulted on. The council responded that a ballot with <strong>YES</strong> vote wasn&rsquo;t necessary because its deal with Notting Hill wasn&rsquo;t a stock transfer; i.e. they were booting residents out before handing the buildings over to Notting Hill to demolish. The Inspector granted an adjournment that would allow objectors time to consider and reply to Southwark&rsquo;s response.</p>

<h2>Ms Murphy&rsquo;s law</h2>

<p>Objectors had several expert witnesses to support their case; <a href="https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=BJCAM61">Dr Ben Campkin</a> of the UCL Bartlett School of Architecture argued that the unjustified negative image of the estate is the thread which underlies ideas about its demolition and regeneration. He gave a presentation based on his book <a href="https://www.bartlett.ucl.ac.uk/architecture/events/remaking-london-event">&lsquo;Remaking London&rsquo;</a> and was subsequently subjected to a fierce cross-examination by Ms Murphy. She took Dr Campkin to task for not being familiar with the Aylesbury Area Action Plan, one of the many large documents within the Inquiry&rsquo;s four-volume core bundle. Amongst other points she also referred to a previous Inspector&rsquo;s <em>&lsquo;educated judgement&rsquo;</em> that the Aylesbury estate was <em>&ldquo;visually unattractive&rdquo;</em>, which drew laughter from the (largely uneducated) public present .</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Conisbee_Nov2004Figures.png"><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/Conisbee_Nov2004Figures.png" width="400" height="300"></a>Dr <a href="http://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=CACRA07">Kate Crawford</a> from the UCL Faculty for Engineering Science gave evidence <em>&lsquo;as an expert citizen&rsquo;</em> on the pros and cons of demoliton vs refurbishment, for which she had authored a <a href="http://www.engineering.ucl.ac.uk/engineering-exchange/files/2014/10/Report-Refurbishment-Demolition-Social-Housing.pdf">report</a> by the <a href="http://www.engineering.ucl.ac.uk/">UCL Engineering Exchange</a>.</p>

<p>Dr Crawford pointed out that there was no legible version of the cost benefit analysis comparing the benefits of demolition against refurbishment, which had been keenly sought by objectiors. She also pointed out that the issue of embodied energy had not been addressed. Ms Murphy had little time for any of this and again referred her to all the documents that Dr Crawford might not have read.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.peoplesrepublicofsouthwark.co.uk/images/stories/0205201502.jpg" width="400" height="300">Also appearing in support of the objectors were <a href="https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=JREND85">Professor Jane Rendell</a> from UCL Bartlett, who in her <a href="http://35percent.org/images/SummaryProfRendell.pdf">expert witness statement</a> pointed to seven reasons why the CPO was not in the public benefit and <a href="http://www2.le.ac.uk/departments/geography/people/professor-loretta-lees-1">Professor Loretta Lees</a>, an <em>&lsquo;international expert on gentrification and the policies and practices associated with it&rsquo;</em>. Professor Lees presented her research to the Inquiry which included extracts from interviews conducted on the estate and an analysis of the extent to which residents were being displaced from the area. Her displacement maps projected during the presentation, were a sobering reminder of the <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2013/06/08/the-heygate-diaspora/">Heygate diaspora</a> and provided a clear indication as to who this regeneration is (or isn&rsquo;t) benefitting.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/lorettalees_aylesburydisplacement.png"></p>

<h2>The residents speak</h2>

<p>On the fourth day a dose of reality was introduced into proceedings when residents gave personal testimony about the human impact and cost of the regeneration.</p>

<p>Les Kerrigan was a leaseholder and resident of 27 years standing and he spoke up for the refurbishment option. His family and friends were all in the area and he complained of the treatment he had received from Southwark&rsquo;s surveyors (a recurring theme) and their &lsquo;derisory&rsquo; offers of compensation.</p>

<p>Mrs Agnes Kabuto had been leaseholder for 25 years and spoke of Southwark&rsquo;s broken promises, including the promise that residents could return to the rebuilt Aylesbury.  Her grandchild attended the local school and her wheelchair-bound mother was becoming ill with anxiety about what would happen to them.  She could not afford any of the rehousing options Notting Hill had offered her and would have a problem getting a mortgage because of her age. She said she felt like <em>&lsquo;a small fish in a sea of sharks&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Ms Judi Boss complained of the confusion Southwark had caused leaseholders and spoke of the support leaseholders had given each other.  She said <em>&lsquo;I feel like I signed my human rights away when I signed my lease&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<p>A statement was read out on behalf of Mr Mehmet Suzman, aged 80, and his wife, Mrs Suzman, aged 76, because they were only able to attend the first day of the hearing. It said that they had no idea they could be bought-out without comparable compensation. They had had shop on the Walworth Rd and had lived in the area 40 years; their family and friends lived all around them; they asked where were they to go if Southwark took their home away from them? Who would give them a mortgage?</p>

<p>The Inquiry resumes back at the Den on 12th May.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury Applications Approved]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/26/aylesbury-applications-approved/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-26T20:25:05+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/26/aylesbury-applications-approved</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/CDTZqH_WYAAUca2.jpg" width="300" height="200">Southwark council battoned down the hatches at their Tooley Street headquarters last Thursday, in preparation for the controversial Aylesbury planning application committee hearing.
In the event, Aylesbury tenants and leaseholders were bitterly disappointed when the six hour meeting approved the <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">applications</a>.
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://peoplesrepublicofsouthwark.co.uk/images/2304201504.jpg" width="300" height="200">Unsurprisingly there was much emotion and some anger at the packed Committee meeting. Objectors were led by tenants group &lsquo;Aylesbury Tenants &amp; Leaseholders First&rsquo; <a href="http://aylesburytenantsfirst.org.uk/">ATLF</a>, accompanied by a representative from the 35% campaign.</p>

<p>ATLF spoke forcefully against the applications. They objected to the loss of social rented housing, the failure to respect the estate ballot that overwhelmingly voted against stock transfer and redevelopment by a housing association and the pitiful compensation and displacement of leaseholders.</p>

<p>35% campaigners took up the issue of the slippery social rented housing definitions and cited the <a href="http://35percent.org/images/AylesburyPlanningApplications_ref15AP3843-44.pdf">sleight of hand</a> used by Notting Hill Housing in their <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing/">Bermondsey Spa regeneration</a> and <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/18/aylesbury-planning-application-hearing/">Elmington estate regeneration</a>, switching social rent for affordable rent.</p>

<p>When Councillors challenged John Hughes - NHHT&rsquo;s Development Director about why NHHT had switched rent tenures at these schemes he replied: <strong> <em>&ldquo;The rents that we are charging at Grange Walk (Bermondsey Spa) and Edmund Street (Elmington estate) are wholly compliant with the planning permissions we received.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<iframe width="350" height="197" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Xqme8oXrCp0?rel=0" align="center" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>This is technically correct (affordable rent is ultimately what ended up in the planning legal agreements) but avoids the question of why the schemes were submitted and approved by committee as social rent. This question Hughes deferred to officers, suggesting they would be better placed to answer it, but thanks to the tight chairing of the meeting this was never followed up.</p>

<p>The only people who stepped forward to speak in support of the application were the Labour ward councillors for the estate.</p>

<p>While the decision to approve the application means that leaseholders now face the loss of their homes and at least 778 social rented homes are lost, a small victory was achieved: Southwark and Notting Hill agreed during the Committee to a tighter definition of social rented housing in the legal S106 agreement. So while this may provide some safeguard, true social rents are not yet guaranteed.</p>

<p>The 35% Campaign challenged Notting Hill&rsquo;s use of the term &lsquo;target rent&rsquo;. In response Notting Hill Housing <a href="http://35percent.org/images/MasterplanClarificationLetter7April.pdf">said</a> <em>&ldquo;social rent means target rent&rdquo;</em>. To which we can only ask <em>&ldquo;why not say social rent then?&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/votinginfavour.png" width="400" height="300">Notting Hill&rsquo;s funding for the Aylesbury development is <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/InsideHousingBoris.pdf">linked to providing affordable rent</a> not social rent. On the other hand Southwark has pledged that social rent is exactly what local people will get out of the Aylesbury redevelopment. Cooking up this new term <em>&lsquo;target rent&rsquo;</em> squares the circle, but at the expense of higher rents for local people.</p>

<p>The 35% campaign will be giving evidence at this week&rsquo;s Public Inquiry into the Aylesbury redevelopment, where we will be giving witness evidence and seeking a fuller explanation of Notting Hill&rsquo;s slippery definitions. The four-day Inquiry is open to the public and will be held at the <a href="http://www.millwallfc.co.uk/tickets/how0-to-get-here/">Millwall Football Club Conference Centre</a> from Tues 28th to Fri 1st (10am-5pm). For an idea of what will be debated at the Inquiry, <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Objectors_OpeningSubmissions_andAppendices.pdf">this copy</a> of the Objectors&#8217; Opening Submission sets out their arguments very clearly.</p>

<h2>Spineless Southwark</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11135/north-south_southwark_spine_cycle_route"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SouthwarkSpine.png" width="300" height="480"></a>While the 35% campaign learnt a wonderful bit of planning jargon on Thursday evening - &ldquo;bikeability&rdquo; - a great opportunity to strengthen the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1812/southwark_council_launches_new_cycling_strategy">&lsquo;Southwark Spine&rsquo;</a> cycling strategy was lost. This recently announced cycle route from the north to the south of the borough runs directly through the middle of the Aylesbury. The aspiration is that <em>&ldquo;the route will be segregated in areas of heavy traffic or large vehicles&rdquo;</em>. But this is now not going to happen on the Aylesbury, despite the fact that an additional bus route will be added to the three already which run down Thurlow street. Instead we will be getting <em>&ldquo;traffic calming measures&rdquo;</em> because Notting Hill doesn&rsquo;t want to encourage <em>&ldquo;fast commuter cycling&rdquo;</em> through its quiet residential development.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury Redevelopment - Decision Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/18/aylesbury-planning-application-hearing/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/18/aylesbury-planning-application-hearing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Aylesburyoutline2.jpg" width="400" height="300"> The planning applications for the redevelopment of the Aylesbury estate are to be considered by Southwark council&rsquo;s planning commitee on <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/ieListDocuments.aspx?CId=119&amp;MId=4808&amp;Ver=4">Thursday evening</a>. Officers recommend that approval be granted - their report on the outline masterplan application can be found <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!Vbu5QpckfYCnJrulzlWyuQ%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">here</a>.</p>

<p>We blogged <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing/">previously</a> about Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s development at the Bermondsey Spa regeneration, where social rented housing agreed at planning committee became affordable rent when - by sleight of hand - social rent was defined in the legal agreement as affordable rent.</p>

<p>In an email response to an enquiry about its Bermondsey Spa development from a local ward councillor, a Notting Hill spokesperson confirmed <strong> <em>&ldquo;we don&rsquo;t have any social rented properties here&rdquo;</em> </strong> and explained that the 44 &lsquo;social rented&rsquo; units are currently let at affordable rents, ranging from 42% of market rent for 3 beds to 63% of market rent for 1 beds (average across all unit types = 58% of market rents).</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!J5kImYW5llmj0BA4PEvWpw%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/elmingtons106.png" width="430" height="310"></a>We have now discovered that the Bermondsey Spa tenure definition switch was no isolated incident: another Notting Hill Housing redevelopment - the Elmington estate regeneration (now rebranded <a href="http://www.camberwellfields.com/">&lsquo;Camberwell Fields&rsquo;</a>) has a definition of social rented housing in its <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!J5kImYW5llmj0BA4PEvWpw%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">S106 agreement</a> enabling the very same tenure switch.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/camberwell-fields-logo.png" width="300" height="200">&lsquo;Camberwell Fields&rsquo; is not due to be completed until later in the year, so we don&rsquo;t know exactly the percentage of market rent the supposed &lsquo;social rented&rsquo; units will be let at yet.<br/>
</br></p>

<p>Concern about the same thing happening on the Aylesbury has been amplified by Notting Hill&rsquo;s use of the term &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; in its planning application; this has raised great suspicion amongst local people. On the very eve of the planning hearing, Notting Hill were obliged to send <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/MasterplanClarificationLetter7April.pdf">letters</a> to all objectors &lsquo;clarifying&rsquo; amongst other things that the term &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; means social rent. Southwark&rsquo;s planning officers agree with this:<br/>
<img class="center" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/CCoxHXoWYAAyHtv.png"></p>

<p>However, Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s <a href="http://35percent.org/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.pdf">Development Partnership Agreement</a> for the Aylesbury has no such definiton; &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; is defined with a vague reference to a &lsquo;target&rsquo; and &lsquo;formula&rsquo; set by government, without any reference to the term social rent or the National Rent Regime regulatory framework which governs it.<br/>
<a href="http://35percent.org/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Aylesbury_targetrent.png"></a></p>

<p>Past planning committees have had the wool pulled over their eyes by Notting Hill Housing. If the same thing happens again on Thursday then we can add the loss of roughly 1300 social rented units promised by Notting Hill on the Aylesbury, to the 44 units lost at Bermondsey Spa and the 41 units set to be lost on its Elmington estate regeneration.</p>

<p>The Aylesbury applications are due to be heard on Thursday evening. In the meantime, we have written a <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyPlanningApplications_ref15AP3843-44.pdf">letter</a> to Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="https://twitter.com/interpolitan_1">Head of Planning</a> and the following planning committee councillors who will be deciding the application, urging them to reject the application until the precise legal definition of the social housing tenure proposed has been published for public consultation. If they stand for social housing which really is social housing or believe in a fair and transparent planning process then they will support and act upon our request.</p>

<ul>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=899">Nick Dolezal</a> -    Chair (Labour)</li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=50000619">Maisie Anderson</a>  (Labour) <a href="https://twitter.com/MaisieA">@MaisieA</a></li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=50000696">Sarah King</a>  (Labour) <a href="https://twitter.com/sezking78">@sezking78</a></li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=50000664">Hamish McCallum</a> (Lib Dem) <a href="https://twitter.com/hamishmccallum">@hamishmccallum</a></li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=909">Darren Merrill</a> (Labour) <a href="https://twitter.com/MerrillDarren">@MerrillDarren</a></li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=334">Michael Mitchell</a> (Conservative)</li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=50000717">Jamille Mohammed</a> (Labour)</li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=161">Adele Morris</a>  (Lib Dem) <a href="https://twitter.com/AdeleCathedrals">@AdeleCathedrals</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifesto for the Destruction of Council Estates]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/28/manifesto-for-destruction-of-council-estates/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-28T13:22:05+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/28/manifesto-for-destruction-of-council-estates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/adonis.png" width="300" height="200">The prestigious <strong>Institute of Public Policy Research (IPPR)</strong> has published a <a href="http://www.ippr.org/publications/city-villages-more-homes-better-communities">policy paper</a> that proposes the wholesale demolition of London&rsquo;s council estates, in the name of regeneration and to allow for the creation of so-called &lsquo;City Villages&rsquo;.</p>

<p>The paper is the brainchild of New Labour peer <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Adonis,_Baron_Adonis">Lord Adonis</a> and includes a chapter by Southwark council leader Peter John.</p>

<p>Adonis was a Greek god who was the epitomy of masculine beauty; our Lord Adonis is a more mundane character: a Blairite zealot who <a href="http://labourlist.org/2014/09/could-we-see-a-jowelladonis-ticket-for-london-mayor/">fancies himself as London&rsquo;s Deputy Mayor</a>. He has gathered together a group of like-minded cronies including London borough council leaders and <a href="http://www.grosvenorestate.com/">property developers</a> to pen a policy proposal entitled <strong>&ldquo;City Villages: More homes, better communities&rdquo;</strong>.</p>

<p>The idea is simple: London needs lots of new homes; they could all be built on brownfield sites; council estates are on brownfield sites - so let&rsquo;s demolish council estates. The land is worth a lot of money, so friendly property developers can be enlisted to help. Demolishing council estates would also get rid of that awful <strong> <em>&ldquo;mono-tenure&rdquo;</em> </strong>housing that breeds crime and anti-social behaviour.</p>

<p>His Lordship draws on various provocative examples to make his case, including the Heygate estate. Southwark council leader Peter John writes a chapter on this great success story, which our readers will know from <a href="http://35percent.org/affordable-housing/">previous posts</a> destroyed 1200 council homes, replacing them with 79 social rented units, plus 200 unaffordable &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; units, <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2013/06/08/the-heygate-diaspora/">ripping off leaseholders</a> along the way - or, in Councillor John&rsquo;s words creating <strong> <em>&ldquo;a genuine mix of private owned, private rented, shared ownership and social rented homes for people of all incomes.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/pjgrin.png" width="400" height="300">Councillor John further redefines the word success when he praises the Strata Tower&rsquo;s <strong> <em>&ldquo;distinctive three wind turbines&rdquo;</em> </strong>, <a href="http://35percent.org/strata-tower">which</a> do not turn, do not work and do not generate any electricity - a fitting symbol of the Elephant &amp; Castle regeneration after all.</p>

<p>Lord Adonis laments the fact that only a <strong> <em>&ldquo;tiny fraction&rdquo;</em> </strong> of London&rsquo;s estates are currently being redeveloped and cites amongst these the massive <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/davehillblog/2015/mar/26/andrew-adonis-and-estate-regeneration-some-pros-and-cons">Earls Court redevelopment</a>, which will require the <a href="https://westkengibbsgreen.wordpress.com/">demolition of the West Ken &amp; Gibbs estate</a> and of course our very own <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">Aylesbury redevelopment</a>.</p>

<p>Both his Lordship and Councillor John acknowledge that this can all be a bit controversial, in that <strong> <em>&ldquo;redevelopment of estates is sometimes assumed to mean that existing tenants and residents will be displaced by wealthier incomers&rdquo;</em> </strong>, but according to Lord Adonis <strong> <em>&ldquo;this need not, nor should it be the case&rdquo;</em> </strong>, since redevelopment should offer ample opportunity for residents to remain in new homes once completed.</p>

<p>We beg to differ; over the past 10 years estate regenerations have <a href="https://www.london.gov.uk/media/assembly-press-releases/2015/02/8000-social-homes-lost-in-a-decade">lost us 8,000 social rented units</a>, while increasing free-market housing ten-fold and doubling the overall housing density. The lessons that we&rsquo;ve learned are that anyone who stands in the way of a regeneration - whether council tenant or leaseholder - is going to lose their home and will unlikely be able to afford any of the new homes.</p>

<p>We are not the only ones to take issue with Lord Adonis&rsquo;s policy proposals; Duncan Bowie, member of the EC of London Labour Housing Group and former advisor to Ken Livingstone has published a <a href="https://redbrickblog.wordpress.com/2015/03/31/city-villages-the-wrong-solution-to-londons-housing-crisis/">detailed critique</a> of Adonis&rsquo;s proposals, which he describes as <em>&lsquo;grossly out of touch&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<h2>Aylesbury planning application - get your tickets now!</h2>

<p>The date of the planning committee meeting for the Aylesbury redevelopment applications has been set back from the 14th April, possibly to the 21st April. The council has said it is expecting &lsquo;much interest&rsquo; and it&rsquo;s likely that the meeting will be ticketed, which requires anyone wishing to attend to register with the council beforehand. Health and safety concerns are clearly uppermost in Southwark council&rsquo;s mind and will no doubt mean that numbers will also be limited.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/chilterngroup.png" width="400" height="300">However, the date for the Compulsory Purchase Order Public Inquiry is fixed (28th April - 1st May at <a href="https://www.etcvenues.co.uk/venues/prospero-house">Prospero House</a>) and this will not be changed. The <a href="http://halag.wordpress.com">Aylesbury Leaseholders Action Group</a> has published its Statement of Case ahead of the Inquiry. Their objections explain how replacement housing will be unaffordable to existing residents and explore the lack of transparency about the proposed tenure mix. You can read through their Statement of Case on their campaign website <a href="https://halag.wordpress.com/2015/03/27/cpo-public-inquiry-help-required/">here</a>.</p>

<h2>P.S. - IPPR makes a couple of good suggestions</h2>

<p>To return to the IPPR policy paper - it does make one or two constructive suggestions, such as the recommendation that <strong> <em>&ldquo;At a minimum, tenants should be balloted on regeneration schemes&rdquo;</em> </strong>. Cllr John couldn&rsquo;t have read this bit, because of course the Aylesbury residents <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2001/dec/27/1">gave a resounding &lsquo;NO&rsquo;</a> to regeneration when they were balloted in 2001.</p>

<p>Another recommendation <strong> <em>&ldquo;Transparency about the future tenure mix is essential from the outset&rdquo;</em> </strong> is also absent from the Aylesbury redevelopment; as we saw in our last two blog posts, Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s definition of social rented tenure is as clear as mud and it has also been <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2015/mar/29/tenants-face-70m-rent-rise-as-social-housing-converted-to-affordable-homes">reported</a> to be converting its existing social tenancies at an alarming rate.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stand Up for More Social Housing (at 80% Market Rent)]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-18T09:29:17+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/homesforbritain.jpg' width='250' height='500' title='Notting Hill Director Kate Davies'><span class='caption-text'>Notting Hill Director Kate Davies</span></span><strong> <em>&ldquo;Let&rsquo;s all of us stand up for more social housing&rdquo;</em> </strong> was the <a href="https://twitter.com/NottingHillHG/status/577771553842167808">call to arms</a> during the <a href="http://www.24dash.com/news/housing/2015-03-18-The-Homes-for-Britain-bus-relay-reaches-Westminister">&lsquo;impassioned speech&rsquo;</a> from Notting Hill Housing Trust&rsquo;s Director Kate Davies at yesterday&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2015/mar/17/london-housing-rally-protesters-gather-at-homes-for-britain-event">&lsquo;Homes for Britain&rsquo;</a> rally. The rally was part of an ongoing campaign organised by the <a href="http://www.housing.org.uk/">National Housing Federation</a>, of which NHHT is a founding member.</p>

<p>We have blogged previously about NHHT&rsquo;s dodgy definition of social housing and its <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/customers/permanent-rented-housing/information-for-permanent-rented-housing-tenants/affordable-rent-update">blanket policy</a> of converting all its existing social rented properties to <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/housing-network/2014/feb/03/affordable-housing-meaning-rent-social-housing">affordable rent</a> when tenancies expire.</p>

<p>So we have taken a closer look at the kind of &lsquo;social&rsquo; housing Notting Hill&rsquo;s Director wants us all to stand up for more of.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/theexchange.jpg' width='' height='' title=''The Exchange' - Notting Hill's 205 unit development at the Bermondsey Spa regeneration scheme (site 5C)'><span class='caption-text'>&lsquo;The Exchange&rsquo; - Notting Hill&rsquo;s 205 unit development at the Bermondsey Spa regeneration scheme (site 5C)</span></span>
This is <a href="http://www.the-exchange-london.com/">&lsquo;The Exchange&rsquo;</a> in Bermondsey, Notting Hill&rsquo;s latest completed development in Southwark and part of the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200180/bermondsey_spa/1144/bermondsey_spa_masterplan">Bermondsey Spa regeneration scheme</a>.
All but three private and two shared-ownership units in this 205-home development have been sold and of those that remain the private flats are <a href="http://www.the-exchange-london.com/availability?tenure=TH">priced</a> at over £1m and the shared-ownership flats <a href="http://www.the-exchange-london.com/availability/so">require</a> a minimum salary of £73,986 to qualify.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://www.downwelldemo.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/P6060031.jpg' width='350' height='300' title='Demolition of 54 council homes on the site'><span class='caption-text'>Demolition of 54 council homes on the site</span></span>The development should also have had 44 social rented units, to replace the 54 council homes demolished to make way for <strong>&lsquo;The Exchange&rsquo;</strong>.</p>

<p>44 social rented units were duly proposed in Notting Hill&rsquo;s <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?casereference=10/AP/3010&amp;system=DC">planning application</a> for the site and that&rsquo;s what was confirmed in the <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7B%7B%7B!7lhb2IoB57lo6iUf2g/V0A==!%7D%7D%7D">planning officer&rsquo;s report</a>. Paragraphs 27 &amp; 29 of the GLA <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/GLABermondseySpaReport.pdf">planning report</a> also confirmed that the development proposed 44 social rented homes. However, after approval was given Southwark Council and Notting Hill signed-off the <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7B%7B%7B!v0IQJeAkBHGLkpIJJYfrTA==!%7D%7D%7D">s106 legal agreement</a> with something completely different - 44 &lsquo;affordable rented&rsquo; units (ie. up to 80% market rents) <strong>not</strong> 44 social rented units.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/BermondseySpaS106.png' width='' height='' title='Officers report states 44 Social Rented homes but S106 Agreement says Affordable Rented units'><span class='caption-text'>Officers report states 44 Social Rented homes but S106 Agreement says Affordable Rented units</span></span></p>

<p>The change in wording is subtle but the consequences aren&rsquo;t; according to <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">Southwark&rsquo;s own figures</a>, a 1-bed social rented flat in Bermondsey(SE16) costs an average £97 per week, compared to £273 per week for &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; at 80% market rent.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s hard not to conclude that the public has been deceived over this development: it was led to believe that it was getting social rents at all stages up to planning approval, then a switch was effected when the legal documents were drawn up after approval was granted.</p>

<p>We showed in our last blog how this sleight-of-hand is becoming commonplace in Southwark&rsquo;s planning process.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.png' width='400' height='200' title='Extract from Aylesbury estate Development Agreement'><span class='caption-text'>Extract from Aylesbury estate Development Agreement</span></span>We have also shown in <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">previous blog posts</a> how Notting Hill is using the terms &lsquo;social&rsquo;, &lsquo;target&rsquo; and &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; rent interchangably in its forthcoming application for the Aylesbury estate redevelopment and <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/10/affordable-rent-is-not-social/">blogged</a> about the worrying fact that affordable rents of up to 80% are included in the Notting Hill development agreement for the Aylesbury.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburySelection.jpg' width='' height='' title='Notting Hill's Director & Southwark council leader celebrate demolition of Aylesbury redevelopment's phase 2'><span class='caption-text'>Notting Hill&rsquo;s Director &amp; Southwark council leader celebrate demolition of Aylesbury redevelopment&rsquo;s phase 2</span></span>
So, we have to ask the question - will the Aylesbury go the same way as the Bermondsey Spa regeneration with affordable rent slipped in quietly through the back door?</p>

<p>One way of finding out would be to for details of Notting Hill&rsquo;s funding allocation for the Aylesbury redevelopment. It has currently secured a total of £92m in funding from the Mayor&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.london.gov.uk/priorities/housing-land/increasing-housing-supply/affordable-homes-programme">Affordable Homes Programme</a> and is by far the largest single recipient of funding from it. London Assembly member Darren Johnson recently tabled a formal <a href="http://questions.london.gov.uk/QuestionSearch/searchclient/questions/question_281359">question</a> to the Mayor about the tenure mix linked to Notting Hill&rsquo;s £92m allocation. We will be watching out for the Mayor&rsquo;s response.</p>

<p>We need to let the council know that the game is up and that we are not going to accept this disingenuous racket. The Aylesbury planning application is due to be heard by committee on 14th April and we will be making our voices heard. We invite you to support us by objecting to the planning application online using our <a href="http://commentform.herokuapp.com">automated objection form</a>.</p>

<h2>Postscript update (3rd April 2015)</h2>

<p>The people at <a href="http://southwarknotes.wordpress.com">Southwark Notes</a> couldn&rsquo;t quite believe that Notting Hill had passed off affordable rent as social rent at its Bermondsey Spa site, so they attempted to seek confirmation via twitter:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/NottingHillHG">@NottingHillHG</a> Hiya NHHT. Is it true that 44 units of social housing at your Exchange site will be &#39;affordable rent&#39;? <a href="http://t.co/gUvnsYQjZX">http://t.co/gUvnsYQjZX</a></p>&mdash; Southwark Notes (@SouthwarkNotes) <a href="https://twitter.com/SouthwarkNotes/status/578173781019111424">March 18, 2015</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>Notting Hill unashamedly confirmed that Bermondsey Spa&rsquo;s 44 &lsquo;social rented&rsquo; units were indeed let at affordable rather than social rents, but that these generally averaged just 58% of market rent:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-cards="hidden" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/SouthwarkNotes">@SouthwarkNotes</a> Yes, affordable rent (average 58% of market rent) due to Gov changes to rent setting in 2011. See <a href="http://t.co/2tThW5DZGZ">http://t.co/2tThW5DZGZ</a></p>&mdash; Notting Hill Housing (@NottingHillHG) <a href="https://twitter.com/NottingHillHG/status/583639651702943744">April 2, 2015</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>Notting Hill&rsquo;s twitter reply also blamed its change of tenure on <strong> <em>&ldquo;Government changes to rent setting&rdquo;</em> </strong> and provided a <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/customers/permanent-rented-housing/money/how-we-set-your-rent-and-charges/rent-increases">link to its website</a> for further details. Below is an extract from that website link, where Notting Hill explains what affordable rent is and confirms that <strong> <em>&ldquo;Approximately 10% of all our &lsquo;social rented housing&rsquo; properties are rented at affordable rents&rdquo;.</em> </strong><br/>
<img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/NHHTAffordableRent.png" width="550" height="500"></p>

<p>We note that Notting Hill has written the term <strong>&lsquo;social rented housing&rsquo;</strong> in inverted commas. It seems that - thanks to Notting Hill Housing Trust - this might be the way <strong>&lsquo;social rented housing&rsquo;</strong> needs to be written from now on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Affordable Rent Is Not Social Rent]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/10/affordable-rent-is-not-social/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-10T20:37:50+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/10/affordable-rent-is-not-social</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/279910_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/wolvertons106SR2.png" width="400" height="400"></a>We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">blogged previously</a> about the last phase of the Aylesbury redevelopment, where we saw plans waved through as social rent, only to discover afterwards that the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/279910_1.pdf">s106 legal agreement</a> defined social rent as encompassing the <a href="http://cfg.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/affordable-rent">HCA&rsquo;s definition of affordable rent</a> (80% market rent).
</br>
</br></p>

<p><a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk/Manor-Place-Exhibition-Banners.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Manorplace_socialrent2.png" width="300" height="320"></a>Notting Hill Housing Group, which is developing all subsequent phases of the Aylesbury estate, has taken a different approach: instead of substituting affordable rent for social rent via the back door, it is openly defining affordable rent as a subcategory of social rent.
Those familiar with housing policy will know that social rents are not determined by Housing Associations; they are determined by the National Rent Regime regulatory framework - and that they are not set in relation to market rents; they are set in relation to average household incomes.</p>

<p>This hasn&rsquo;t deterred Notting Hill Housing; its <a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk/Manor-Place-Exhibition-Banners.pdf">consultation document</a> for another Walworth scheme, the <a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk">Manor Place development</a> (a former Council <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/10070/recycling/1364/reuse_and_recycling_centre">refuse depot</a>) shows it will be setting rents for its new social rented homes at <em>&ldquo;up to 50% of local market rents&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/RentsRising.jpg" width="300" height="200">50% of local market rents may sound like a good deal to some, but in an area where rents have increased by 17% in the last 3 years<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> to an average £300 per week for a 1-bed flat<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, 50% of market rents is roughly double existing council rents. The crucial difference is also that market rents rise well beyond wages in property hotspots like Southwark; an important consideration in a borough where the average household income of a council tenant is £9,100 per year<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> and definitely not rising at the same rate as local market rents.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/affordablerentstudy.png" width="350" height="300"></a>Southwark council has undertaken <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/download/2914/affordable_rent_in_southwark_2011">a study</a> of the affordability of affordable rent in the borough, so it is entirely aware that these ridiculous &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; rents are unaffordable to most of its residents. Indeed, it has said as much in <a href="http://35percent.org/images/fionacolleyresponsetolondonplan.pdf">representations to the Mayor</a> rejecting the new tenure policy. <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">This spreadheet</a> from the council&rsquo;s study shows the minimum household income needed for one of Notting Hill&rsquo;s new 50% market rent &lsquo;social rented&rsquo; homes is £39,860 per year - well beyond the £21,000 mean average household income in Walworth.</p>

<p>We don&rsquo;t yet know what percentage of market rent the replacement &lsquo;social&rsquo; housing on the new Aylesbury estate will be, but we do know that the <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.pdf">Agreement</a> signed for the sale of the estate allows notting hill to set the new affordable rents at up to 80% market rent:</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.png"></a></p>

<p>Some might see all this as an inevitable consequence of the market and beyond the control of public authorities, but this would ignore the fact that the Aylesbury and Manor Place depot are on council-owned land, being bought in turn by a publicly-funded Housing Association. Southwark and Notting Hill should be fulfilling their duty to build truly affordable and truly social rented homes on this land, not playing games with dodgy &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; housing definitions.
</br></p>

<h2>More from the Notting Hill Mob</h2>

<p>Notting Hill are also involved in the Council&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/823/regeneration_projects/1798/elmington_regeneration/4">Elmingtion estate regeneration</a> in Camberwell, where the council has just <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s48494/Report%20CPO%20for%20Elmington%20Estate.pdf">issued a Compulsory Purchase Order</a> on 144 homes in phase 3 of the scheme. Phases 1 &amp; 2, where Notting Hill has already <a href="http://directobjective.blogspot.co.uk/2011/12/elmington-estate-revisited.html">demolished 373 council homes</a>, are nearing completion and the new &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; homes are currently being marketed in the development rebranded <a href="http://www.camberwellfields.com/">&lsquo;Camberwell Fields&rsquo;</a>.
<a href="http://www.camberwellfields.com/"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/camberwell-fields-logo.png"></a></p>

<p>Paragraph 12 of this <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s30291/Report%20Disposal%20of%20the%20Councils%20freehold%20interest%20in%20Elmington%20estate%20sites%20C%20D%20E%20and%20G%20Camberw.pdf">Council report</a> confirms that all replacement 1 &amp; 2 bed social housing in the redevelopment will be set at 65% market rent. According to <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">Southwark&rsquo;s figures</a> this will amount to £194 per week: double the existing council rents. Tenants who have been &lsquo;decanted&rsquo; from the estate and wish to exercise their right to return, will therefore need to be able to afford a 100% rent hike.</p>

<p>But the main component of the new &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; housing comprises shared ownership units. Notting Hill has just released the <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/CamberwellFields.pdf">price list</a> for these, and the cheapest will be £380k for a 1-bed flat. For this you will need to buy a minimum 40% share, have a minimum household income of £51,824 and will pay a total of £1,438 per month in rent, mortgage and service charge payments. The average income of Camberwell households is £24,400pa, so they are obviously out of luck.</p>

<h2>Not Notting Hill (but not better neither)..</h2>

<p><a href="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/properties/lq-trafalgar-place/?preview=true"><img class="left" src="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/LQ-@-Trafalfar-Place-Brochure.jpg" width="250" height="300"></a>Last week, L&amp;Q <a href="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/properties/lq-trafalgar-place/?preview=true">launched</a> its shared ownership homes on the redeveloped Heygate estate. The launch coincided with the latest phase of marketing at a <a href="http://www.thestandard.com.hk/news_detail.asp?art_id=154851&amp;con_type=3">sales event in Hong Kong</a>. According to L&amp;Q&rsquo;s <a href="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/LQ-@-Trafalgar-Place-Pricelist-12-bed-launch-2.pdf">price list</a>, the cheapest of the Heygate&rsquo;s new &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; shared ownership homes will set you back £126k for a 30% stake in a 1-bed flat, for which you will need to buy a minimum 30% share, requiring a household income of at least £57,500k per year. A 25% share in a 2-bed duplex will set you back £185,625, but with a minimum household income requirement of £64,500 it won&rsquo;t be long before you will be able to staircase up to full ownership of the flat, priced at a mere £742,500. It seems our council leader is finally delivering on his housing <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7585">pledge</a> to help poor Southwark residents on <em>&ldquo;£60-£80,000 a year – but who have absolutely no hope of buying&rdquo;</em>.   <br/>
</br></p>

<h2>Southwark seeks help</h2>

<p><a href="http://southwark.communitymaps.org.uk/#/project/15?center=51.4653:-0.0707:12"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/interactivemap.png" width="250" height="250"></a>While council estates tumble across the borough Southwark Council has launched an <a href="http://southwark.communitymaps.org.uk/#/welcome">interactive map</a>, inviting people to suggest where it should build its pledged 11,000 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes. Vacant land is limited so it will be a difficult task; back in December the Council even <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/12/06/11000-new-private-and-social-council-homes-on-target/">suggested</a> exploring the purchase of land on the open market from developers. Given its <a href="http://35percent.org/heygate-regeneration-faq/">track record</a> in negotiating with developers, a better alternative would be to build the new council homes on the vast estates that the Council is &lsquo;regenerating&rsquo; (Heygate, Aylesbury, Wooddene &amp; Elmington etc). Even now it’s not too late and surely preferable to selling these sites off to developers and corporated-minded Housing Associations, who provide nothing but a few unaffordable affordable homes in return?</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Source: <a href="http://data.london.gov.uk/dataset/average-private-rents-borough/resource/73b9fb07-b5bb-4a53-88b7-c17269879a08">Greater London Authority - Dataset 2014</a><a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See data for SE17 in Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">Dec 2014 Affordable Rent Study dataset</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See sheet 8, row 9 of the Council&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">Dec 2014 Affordable Rent Study update</a>.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Greenwich Developers Ordered to Show Their Sums]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/02/04/developers-ordered-to-show-their-sums/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-04T15:19:21+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/02/04/developers-ordered-to-show-their-sums</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://gsa-studios.com/images/uploads/projects/1168x650_greenwich.jpg" width="300" height="200">We reported last year how a residents group in Greenwich had followed our lead and requested the viability assessments justifying decisions to reduce affordable housing in the £5bn Greenwich Peninsula redevelopment. Similar to our request for the Heygate figures, Greenwich residents had won the support of the Information Commissioner but were then taken to appeal by the Council and developer Knight Dragon. We put them in touch with our legal friends at Leigh Day &amp; Monckton Chambers and expert witness <a href="http://www.northampton.ac.uk/directories/people/bob-colenutt">Dr Colenutt</a> who helped the campaigners take on the Council &amp; developer&rsquo;s barristers at an Information Tribunal hearing in October last year.</p>

<p>After a two month wait, the Tribunal issued its <a href="http://bit.ly/1zS9Qc0">decision notice</a> earlier this week. The decision was conclusive and damning; it rejected the Council&rsquo;s arguments and pointed out that councillors on Greenwich&rsquo;s planning committee had no more information about the viability figures than did the general public. Hong Kong developer Knight Frank&rsquo;s arguments about commercial confidentiality were also given short shrift by the Judge <strong> <em>&ldquo;This is a case where a company, robust enough to take on the development of a huge site over a period of 20 years.. immediately asks to be relieved of a planning obligation freely negotiated by its predecessor. It justifies this change on the basis of a downturn in house prices it knew about at the time of purchase, using a valuation model that looks at current values only and does not allow for change in the many factors that may affect a valuation over time. It seems to us that in those circumstances the public interest in openness about the figures is very strong.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>In contrast to the Heygate decision where developer Lend Lease was allowed to withhold its financial model in appendix 22 of the assessment, the Greenwich decision took a much tougher line: <strong> <em>&lsquo;once it is accepted that the EIR regulations apply, it is necessary to apply them in their full rigour.  There is no room for an “EIR lite” approach&rsquo;</em> </strong> (para. 24) <br/>
There are more details about the Greenwich decision on the <a href="http://853blog.com/2015/02/03/greenwich-peninsula-social-cleansing-council-loses-battle-to-keep-developer-document-secret/">853 blog</a>.</p>

<h2>Viability for dummies</h2>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/viabilityfordummies.pdf"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/viabilityfordummies.png" width="300" height="400"></a>In terms of EIR case law, there was still some doubt following the Heygate decision about exactly what developers are allowed to withhold, especially in light of the ongoing legal battle over the interpretation of the Heygate decision notice. The Greenwich decision appears to have addressed that ambiguity and provided a clear steer as to what exactly is subject to disclosure - everything.</p>

<p>This should now clear the path for other community groups to obtain viability information and participate more meaningfully in planning issues.</p>

<p>In an attempt to help them do so, we have drafted a <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/viabilityfordummies.pdf">&lsquo;dummies&rsquo; guide</a> to viability, part 1 of which explains how to obtain viability information using EIR requests.</p>

<h2>Heygate Tribunal battle continues</h2>

<p>The ongoing battle over the interpretation of the Tribunal&rsquo;s May 2014 <a href="http://www.informationtribunal.gov.uk/DBFiles/Decision/i1279/London%20Borough%20of%20Southwark%20EA.2013.0162%20%2809.05.14%29.pdf">decision notice</a> continues. The decision allowed Lend Lease to withhold its financial development model projections on retail and office floorspace. The notice ordered the parties to get together and agree on dividing up the information for disclosure along those lines. It acknowledged that there may be &lsquo;grey areas&rsquo; and stated that if parties are unable to reach agreement then it will reconvene to settle the argument.
After many months of stalling and heel dragging by Southwark and Lend Lease, the Tribunal reconvened partially in October and was due to reconvene for a full hearing on 11th Dec last year. But Lend Lease&rsquo;s Commercial Director was unable to attend so the hearing was postponed. The hearing was finally able to take place on 21st January when parties made their arguments on how the information should be divided up according to the Tribunal&rsquo;s May 2014 decision.</p>

<p>During the hearing Lend Lease&rsquo;s counsel argued that protecting its financial model in appendix 22, also extended to protecting the inputs and outputs to the model found elsewhere in the report and its appendices. Mr Glasspool&rsquo;s counsel pointed out that the inputs and outputs did not form &lsquo;part of the model&rsquo; and would not expose the model&rsquo;s underlying formulas that Lend Lease had so vehemently argued were its &lsquo;trade secret&rsquo;.</p>

<p>The Tribunal is expected to issue a decision notice detailing exactly which information can be withheld some time in the next few weeks.</p>

<h2>Southwark joins 35% campaign</h2>

<p>Southwark Council issued a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1903/southwark_council_slams_plans_to_reduce_affordable_housing_contributions">press statement</a> earlier this week entitled <strong> <em>&ldquo;Southwark Council slams plans to reduce affordable housing contributions.&rdquo;</em> </strong> The statement says it <strong> <em>&ldquo;has hit out at government plans to allow developers to reduce affordable housing contributions&rdquo;</em> </strong>. It is referring to the governments new <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2015/feb/01/property-developers-affordable-housing-councils-empty-building">&lsquo;vacant building credit&rsquo;</a>, which is said to cut back even further the amount of affordable housing delivered through planning gain.</p>

<p>Much as we applaud Southwark&rsquo;s sentiment, we point out that it first needs to sort out its problem of allowing developers to get away with avoiding affordable housing by viability assessments. Two such examples are these developments currently under construction at the Elephant, both of which are being built on land sold to developers by the Council. Thanks to Southwark&rsquo;s failure to question the viability assessments submitted at planning, neither of these will provide any affordable housing and the payments in-lieu are a fraction of what they should have been according to Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://affordable.heroku.com/images/affordablehousingspg.pdf">in-lieu tariff</a>.     <br/>
<img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/tribecaonetheelephant.jpg"></p>

<p>You can read more detailed info about the Tribeca Square development <a href="http://35percent.org/tribeca-square/">here</a> and One The Elephant <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/01/11/flogging-the-elephant/">here.</a></p>

<h2>Aylesbury Occupied</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/B8_4AbdIAAAb-ir.jpg" width="300" height="600"> Housing activists have occupied empty homes on the Aylesbury estate. The activists took up occupation directly following last weekend&rsquo;s <a href="http://marchforhomes.org">March for Homes</a> and are protesting at the failure to address London&rsquo;s growing housing crisis.</p>

<p>In an <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/development/protestors-occupy-estate-earmarked-for-15bn-regeneration/7008068.article">interview</a> with Inside Housing, Councillor Williams, Southwark&rsquo;s Cabinet member for Regeneration claimed that the protesters <strong> <em>&ldquo;are risking the delivery of the very homes they claim to be campaigning for.&rdquo;</em> </strong> He went on to explain that <strong> <em>&ldquo;The scheme will be 50% affordable, with 75% of these rented and 25% for shared ownership.&rdquo;</em> </strong> We are unsurprised to note the semantic subtlety of Cllr Williams&#8217; omitting to use either the word <strong>&lsquo;social&rsquo;</strong> or <strong>&lsquo;affordable&rsquo;</strong> in conjunction with the word <strong>&lsquo;rented&rsquo;</strong>.</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyTLF.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyTLF.png" width="300" height="400"></a>Cllr Williams also claims that the protestors don&rsquo;t represent the Aylesbury residents, but <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyTLF.pdf">this flyer</a> suggests that at least <a href="http://aylesburytenantsfirst.org.uk/">one tenants group</a> on the estate disagrees.</p>

<p>The Aylesbury occupiers have set up a website for their campaign <a href="http://fightfortheaylesbury.wordpress.com">http://fightfortheaylesbury.wordpress.com</a> and Twitter account: @OccupyAylesbury
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>Concrete Heartland</h2>

<p>Concrete Heartland, a film about the Heygate regeneration by Steven Ball and Rastko Novaković has now been released online. Following a number of screenings last year, it has now been uploaded for popular consumption and can be viewed online at <a href="http://concreteheartland.info">http://concreteheartland.info</a><br/>
Assembled from 12 years of archive materials, the film charts the struggles of the local community to keep their homes, stay living in the area and maintain communal benefits in the face of the advance of this now notorious &lsquo;urban redevelopment programme&rsquo;.</p>

<h2>West Hendon estate</h2>

<p>BBC&rsquo;s The One Show featured a piece on the West Hendon estate on Monday. Due to the notorius viability arguments, residents there are being forced out of the area after developers Barratt argued that it was no longer possible to rehouse them in the new development. The story sounds all too familiar to us down here in Southwark.
</center></p>

<iframe width="350" height="197" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5OXc814Q9ps" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p></center></p>

<h2>Affordable housing tenants excluded from communal gardens</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/media/brochure/b2678/files/assets/common/page-substrates/page0015.jpg" width="300" height="200">Southwark&rsquo;s planning committee <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/8077">has agreed</a> to a variation in planning conditions for the <a href="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/new-homes/london/tower-bridge/one-tower-bridge">One Tower Bridge development</a>, to prevent affordable housing tenants being able to use the communal garden available to private residents. Simon Bevan, Southwark&rsquo;s director of planning, told the planning committee that the exclusion of social tenants from the garden was <strong> <em>&ldquo;not seen as any significant restriction on how they enjoy their property&rdquo;.</em> </strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Peabody's Philanthropic Glass Towers - 0% Social Housing]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/01/27/peabody-borough-triangle-development/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-27T09:08:17+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/01/27/peabody-borough-triangle-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/BoroughTriangle.png" width="400" height="300">Peabody Housing Association has finally submitted a <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9556404">Planning application</a> for its long-awaited <em>Borough Triangle</em> development at Elephant &amp; Castle. This large triangle of land sits between Southbank University, Borough road and the Crown Court on Newington Causeway.</p>

<p>The site is currently home to the <a href="https://www.ipsos-mori.com/">IPSOS MORI</a> buildings and Baptist church on Borough road, which will be the only buildings to survive the redevelopment. The Georgian-built <a href="http://www.ioo.org.uk/">Institute of Optometry</a> and <a href="http://www.thestage.co.uk/news/2015/01/london-school-musical-theatre-relocate-southwark-site-demolished/">London School of Musical Theatre</a> (formerly the Institute for the Blind) will both be demolished under Peabody&rsquo;s plans. The latter being replaced by <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/NewMinistryOfSound.png">new premises</a> for the Ministry of Sound, which Peabody will build in its place.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/boroughtriangle.jpg"></p>

<p>The shops and warehouse spaces on the Newington side of the site will also be demolished. These are currently being used as a Pop-up arts and cultural space by <a href="http://www.hotelelephant.co.uk/">&lsquo;Hotel Elephant&rsquo;</a> and <a href="http://www.thepaperworks.co.uk/">&lsquo;The Paperworks&rsquo;</a>.<br/>
<img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/HotelElephant_Paperworks.jpg"></p>

<p>Besides new premises for the Ministry of Sound night club totalling ca. 6,000 sqm (allowing an extra capacity of 400 people over its current venue), Peabody plans to build some retail space; 10,000 sqm of office space in a shiny new corporate HQ for its staff; and a total of 529 new homes in a number of (predominantly glass) buildings of up to 38 storeys.</p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/388339_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Peabody_BoroughTriangle.png"></a></p>

<p>We originally had high hopes that this site would provide the desperately needed social rented housing that local people need. Unfortunately Peabody appears to have followed the trend of going for the more profitable &lsquo;affordable rented&rsquo; housing with rents of up to 80% market rent. It has also followed the trend of fudging and misleading about the precise nature of the affordable housing it is providing. In its <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387231_1.pdf">Housing Statement</a> Peabody states that it will be providing 96 <strong>intermediate</strong> units (16.7% of total) and 78 units at <strong>affordable rent</strong> (16.5% of total).</p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387231_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/affordable_rent_peabody.png" width="400" height="300"></a></p>

<p>However, Peabody&rsquo;s <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387199_1.pdf">Planning Statement</a> starts off by explaining the council&rsquo;s affordable housing policy: <strong> <em>&ldquo;5.117 In terms of affordable housing tenure, the Core Strategy at Strategic Policy 6 identifies that for development within the Elephant and Castle Opportunity Area the affordable housing should be delivered at 50% intermediate and 50% social rented.&rdquo;</em> </strong> but then dropping the word &lsquo;social&rsquo; from social rented, astonishingly goes on to claim that the application is policy compliant: <strong> <em>&ldquo;The proposal provides 16.7% intermediate and 16.5% for rented which is considered to comply with policy.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Peabody_ApplicationForm.png">We checked the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387188_1.pdf">application form</a> to see what had been written in the useful boxes that Southwark provides showing detailed tenure mix information. We found that the 78 units had indeed been entered under the category social rented, but that the applicant had doctored the application form to include the word &lsquo;AFFORDABLE&rsquo; over the title &lsquo;Social Rented&rsquo;.</p>

<p>We also checked the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/388020_1.pdf">Design &amp; Access Statement</a> which states not only that the units will be affordable rent, but that they will be <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Peabody_TenureMix.png">segregated</a> from the other tenures (the high-rise towers will be exclusively private and intermediate housing).</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/EmailDanielDavies.png" width="400" height="300">Finally, we wrote to the Council&rsquo;s planning department asking for some clarity on whether the 78 units were for social rent or affordable rent; this is the baffling response we received.</p>

<p>Southwark recently published a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/download/2914/affordable_rent_in_southwark_2011">detailed study</a> of the impact of the introduction of affordable rent in the borough. From its <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">underlying data</a> we can see that a 1-bed social rented flat in SE1 would cost an average £97 per week, but a 1-bed flat at the new &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; of 80% market rent would cost £316 per week. Given that the median household income for council tenants in Borough and Bankside is £9,100 per year, it is clear that Peabody&rsquo;s affordable housing offer will be of no help to local people in housing need.  <br/>
</br>
Borough Triangle is the second largest development in the Elephant &amp; Castle opportunity area after the Heygate. No doubt lengthy discussions have taken place between Peabody, the Ministry of Sound and Southwark about what should be delivered on this key regeneration site. It is very dissapointing that a Housing Association with Peabody&rsquo;s reputation is not only failing to provide social housing, but is also seeking to mislead people about the fact. It is doubly dissapointing - but not surprising on past record - that Southwark is going along with it.</p>

<p>It seems Peabody has come a long way from the philanthropic intentions it was founded on in 1862, by George Peabody who wanted to <a href="http://www.peabody.org.uk/about-us/our-story"><strong> <em>&ldquo;ameliorate the condition of the poor and needy in this great metropolis&rdquo;</em> </strong></a>.</p>

<p>You can object to Peabody&rsquo;s application (ref:14/AP/3130) by sending an email to <a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#x74;&#111;&#x3a;&#x70;&#108;&#x61;&#110;&#x6e;&#x69;&#110;&#103;&#46;&#97;&#x70;&#x70;&#x6c;&#105;&#x63;&#97;&#x74;&#105;&#111;&#110;&#115;&#64;&#115;&#x6f;&#x75;&#116;&#x68;&#119;&#97;&#x72;&#x6b;&#x2e;&#x67;&#x6f;&#x76;&#46;&#117;&#x6b;">&#112;&#108;&#x61;&#x6e;&#x6e;&#x69;&#110;&#103;&#x2e;&#x61;&#112;&#x70;&#x6c;&#105;&#x63;&#x61;&#x74;&#105;&#111;&#110;&#115;&#64;&#x73;&#111;&#x75;&#116;&#x68;&#119;&#97;&#x72;&#x6b;&#46;&#x67;&#111;&#118;&#46;&#x75;&#107;</a></p>

<h2>Peabody engages &lsquo;political intelligence&rsquo; services</h2>

<p>Peabody&rsquo;s application includes the mandatory <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387210_1.pdf">Statement of Community Involvement (SCI)</a>, which is required to show evidence that it has consulted on its plans with the local community. Peabody instructed a public affairs company called <a href="http://www.bellenden.co.uk/about-us/specialist-expertise/property-development/">Bellenden</a> to advise on its application, conduct the consultation exercise and prepare its SCI.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.bellenden.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/MarkGloverColour.jpg">Bellenden was founded and is run by former Chair of Southwark Labour and local councillor <a href="https://uk.linkedin.com/in/glovermark">Mark Glover</a>. It was named after the road in which <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/4075/statement_of_persons_nominated_and_notice_of_poll">he lives</a>, Bellenden road in Peckham. Glover stepped down as councillor in May 2014. Amongst other things, Bellenden offers its clients a <a href="http://www.bellenden.co.uk/public-affairs/political-intelligence/">&lsquo;political intelligence&rsquo; service</a>, which it says involves <strong> <em>&ldquo;learning how political parties and their individual members are thinking on any given issue&rdquo;</em> </strong> and then <strong> <em>&ldquo;seeks to enlarge and inform their thoughts on behalf of our clients.&rdquo;</em> </strong><br/>
With his 12 years as a senior Southwark councillor, we don&rsquo;t doubt that Mr Glover is very well placed to provide this service.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Council Housing - Going Up or Coming Down?]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/01/11/march-for-homes/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-11T12:21:55+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/01/11/march-for-homes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11416/housing_estates_and_sites_for_new_council_homes"><img class="right" src="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/Pictures/web/y/z/m/New-Council-Homes-deliver_633.jpg" width="400" height="270"></a>Just before Christmas Southwark Council issued a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1878/southwark_maps_out_1500_new_council_homes_in_just_four_years_as_part_of_the_most_ambitious_council_house_build_in_the_country">press release</a>, accompanied by a lovely <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11416/housing_estates_and_sites_for_new_council_homes">map</a> entitled <em>&ldquo;Housing Estates and Sites for New Council Homes&rdquo;</em>, which shows where 1500 of Southwark&rsquo;s 11000 new council homes will be built.</p>

<p>But as we showed in the <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/12/06/11000-new-private-and-social-council-homes-on-target/">previous blog</a>, this council-house building programme is not all it seems. For example, the 19 new homes planned on the East Dulwich estate (Gatebeck &amp; Southdown House), will be offset by 50 council homes which are being sold off on other parts of the estate - a net loss of 31 council homes in total<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://s0.geograph.org.uk/geophotos/02/70/11/2701156_6a4b82c2.jpg" width="300" height="200">Another site on the map, <em>Maydew House</em> will also show a net loss once completed. This 24-storey block containing 144 council flats overlooking Southwark Park, has been decanted <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Save-Maydew-House/316012601837">(amidst protest)</a> after the council <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/00,news,20152,440,00.htm">declared</a> the cost of repair <em>&ldquo;difficult to justify&rdquo;</em>. It is now being refurbished and 5 extra penthouse floors added to provide a total of 180 units, but only 74 will remain as council flats - a net loss of 70 council homes<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. The remaining 106 flats will all be sold off on the open market.</p>

<p>Building council homes is a popular pledge and one that we unquestionably support – it’s the best, most economical way of providing decent housing to those who most need it - but we are reminded of <a href="http://35percent.org/images/500newhomes.png">similar promises</a> from the not-so-distant past that were used to mask over the loss of the Heygate estate’s 1200 council homes<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>.</p>

<p>When we <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">blogged in October</a> about concerns that the new homes would only be replacements for council homes  sold off or demolished,  council leader Peter John reassured everyone that there would be a net gain of 11,000 council homes; he said -
<em>“To be absolutely clear, the 11,000 new homes that we promise to deliver will be new homes additional to our existing stock. ……These are new homes and do not include the existing stock of council housing.”</em></p>

<p>These latest findings show a different picture.  A council house building programme that depends upon ‘asset disposal’ and ‘estate renewal’ needs close scrutiny, if it is not going to end up leaving us with fewer council homes than we started with.</p>

<h2>March for Homes</h2>

<p><a href="http://marchforhomes.org"><img class="left" src="http://marchforhomes.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/MARCH_FOR_HOMES_SITE_LOGO.gif"></a>Housing (or the lack of it) is set to be a key issue in the parliamentary and mayoral elections in May. A <a href="http://marchforhomes.org/">&lsquo;March for Homes&rsquo;</a> has been called for Jan 31st by the <a href="http://www.southlondonpa.org/">South London People&rsquo;s Assembly</a>. It has an impressive list of supporters (including the 35% campaign) and is now to have two legs: one starting from South London and one from East London, both to converge on City Hall.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://li.zoocdn.com/c72dcb6efccb9584389cccf5dacc9330082f26fa_354_255.jpg" width="250" height="160">The South London leg will assemble at St Mary&rsquo;s Churchyard - in the shadow of <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/05/05/manx-connections-the-off-shore-home-of-the-elephants-developers/">Strata Tower</a>, <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/01/11/flogging-the-elephant/">One the Elephant</a> and the planned <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2013/08/10/towering-disgrace/">360 Tower</a>: three towers comprising 1162 new homes with zero social housing; the perfect place to start.<br/>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>West Hendon residents fight for their homes</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="https://fbcdn-sphotos-b-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xfp1/t31.0-8/c0.145.851.315/p851x315/10714465_1542589322623724_2087822952488384127_o.jpg" width="450" height="200">Meanwhile, residents of the <a href="http://www.londontenants.org/Pages/projectsderrick.htm">West Hendon estate</a> face a <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/legal/public-inquiry-to-investigate-misuse-of-compulsory-purchase-orders/7007668.article">public inquiry</a> into the compulsory purchase of their homes. The West Hendon regeneration is for 2,000 new homes and requires the demolition of 500 social rented units to be replaced by 250 affordable rent (up to 80% market rent).<br/>
They have organised a day of events on Jan 22nd:</p>

<ul>
<li>2pm: <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Focus-E15-Mothers/602860129757343">Focus E15 Mothers</a> talk about their campaign</li>
<li>4-5pm: Hot soup and rolls</li>
<li>5pm: March from the estate to the Public Inquiry at Hendon Town Hall</li>
<li>6pm: Rally outside Hendon Town Hall, joined by Women from The <a href="http://newera4all.org/">New Era campaign</a>, speakers from the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Our-West-Hendon/1476545849228072">Our West Hendon Group</a>, <a href="http://radicalhousingnetwork.org/">Radical Housing Network</a> , <a href="http://www.unitetheunion.org/">Unite The Union</a> and other estates in Barnet.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Fifty shades of embarrassment</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.independent.co.uk/incoming/article9969422.ece/alternates/w620/shades-of-gross.jpg" width="300" height="200">A marketing video for <a href="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/new-homes/london/southwark/one-blackfriars">One Blackfriars</a> tells us who this housing is really for, if we were in any doubt - people who can afford to go househunting in helicopters.</p>

<p>The video features a sexy affluent white young professional couple, indulging in Fifty Shades of Grey fantasies as they view One Blackfriars&#8217; swish appartments. The video was quickly removed from the web after widespread ridicule in the national press: <br/>
<a href="http://www.standard.co.uk/news/london/luxury-london-flat-advert-branded-the-creepiest-thing-you-will-ever-see-9966793.html">Evening Standard - &lsquo;London flat advert branded the creepiest thing you will ever see&rsquo;</a> <br/>
<a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/business/news/one-blackfriars-shades-of-gross-ad-for-luxury-flats-is-dropped-9969098.html">The Independent - &lsquo;Gross ad for luxury flats is dropped&rsquo;</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/architecture-design-blog/2015/jan/05/american-psycho-redrow-property-promo-pulled-after-twitterstorm">The Guardian - &lsquo;Property promo pulled after twitterstorm&rsquo;</a></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.savoyrealty.co.uk/sites/default/files/field/image/18360_lg.jpg?slideshow=true&slideshowAuto=false&slideshowSpeed=4000&speed=350&transition=elastic" width="200" height="250"><em>One Blackfriars</em> was granted planning permission by Southwark Council in July 2007, despite objections from English Heritage, Lambeth Council, Westminster Council and the Royal Parks. It will have 274 flats, none of which will be social rented or affordable. Instead an in-lieu payment of £29m is to be paid by developers St George, which is a fraction of the <a href="http://www.propertyweek.com/berkeley-buys-london-beetham-tower/5026546.article">£700m</a> Gross Development Value i.e. the total estimated sales value of all the appartments.</p>

<p>An FOI request for the viability assessment which justified this generous deal has been <a href="https://www.whatdotheyknow.com/request/2nd_economic_viability_study_for">lodged</a> with Southwark Council.</p>

<h2>Viability on the agenda</h2>

<p>The viability assessment fiasco is firmly on the agenda in the run up to the elections. In an <a href="http://www.24dash.com/news/housing/2015-01-08-My-housing-career-Peter-Marsh">interview</a> with <em>24Dash Housing</em>, a former housing quango chief has estimated that viability assessments caused the loss of £1bn of affordable housing and that many in the sector <em>&ldquo;consider these appraisals something of a joke&rdquo;</em>. The Guardian&rsquo;s editorial has <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/jan/01/guardian-view-affordable-housing-developers-must-made-show-sums">branded</a> the appraisal loophole a <em>&lsquo;public betrayal&rsquo;</em> and has called for developers to <em>&ldquo;show their sums&rdquo;</em>. A reporter who <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2014/sep/17/truth-property-developers-builders-exploit-planning-cities">wrote</a> about the problem earlier in the year has also put it at the top of his New Years wishlist, calling for <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2014/dec/29/what-i-want-cities-2015-severe-tax-on-empty-homes"><em>&ldquo;opening up this shady world of cooked books&rdquo;</em></a>.</p>

<p>We are also looking forward to helping lift the lid on the viability assessment scam. We have been talking to professionals from the across the sector, who will be helping us analyse the viability assessments obtained from the forthcoming Heygate &amp; Greenwich Peninsula Tribunal cases and put forward ideas for policy changes that could close the loophole. Watch this space!</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See paragraph 16 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s36276/Report%20East%20Dulwich%20Estate%20Regeneration%20Scheme%20and%20Scheme%20Finance%20Update.pdf">this March 2013 Cabinet Report</a><a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See paragraph 132 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s49973/Report%20Qtr%202%202014-15%20Capital%20Monitor.pdf">this November 2014 Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>This is an extract from the <a href="https://www.scribd.com/doc/198503633/EandC-RegenMk1SLRplans">2002 E&amp;C Regeneration Masterplan</a><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Council Sells Council Homes to Build New (Social &amp; Private) 'Council' Homes]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/12/06/11000-new-private-and-social-council-homes-on-target/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-06T09:16:18+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2014/12/06/11000-new-private-and-social-council-homes-on-target</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">wrote</a> in October about the council&rsquo;s plan to earmark a number of its housing estates for demolition using an <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SNhat.pdf">&lsquo;Asset Performance Evaluation Tool&rsquo;</a>, which would take into account factors like residents&#8217; income. The results of its survey were supposed to be presented at next week&rsquo;s Cabinet meeting, but the <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50476/Report%20Pipeline%20for%20the%20Delivery%20of%201500%20New%20Council%20Homes.pdf">December Cabinet report</a> shows that this has now been postponed until January.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50476/Report%20Pipeline%20for%20the%20Delivery%20of%201500%20New%20Council%20Homes.pdf">December Cabinet report</a> makes interesting reading: it concedes that its estate renewal programme alone may not provide enough capacity for its 11,000 proposed new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes and suggests two additional strategies:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Buying affordable housing built through s106 agreements directly from developers. (see <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50476/Report%20Pipeline%20for%20the%20Delivery%20of%201500%20New%20Council%20Homes.pdf">para. 58</a>).</p></li>
<li><p>Purchasing land that becomes available on the open market. (see <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50476/Report%20Pipeline%20for%20the%20Delivery%20of%201500%20New%20Council%20Homes.pdf">para. 60</a>)</p></li>
</ol>


<p>We can see two obvious problems with these new strategies:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Southwark&rsquo;s track record on securing affordable housing through s106 obligations is extremely poor. The viability assessment loophole means that developers often get away with building no affordable housing whatsoever. In those cases where affordable housing is provided, it normally takes the form of shared ownership and affordable rent (80% market), which are of little benefit unless these are the kind of &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes that Southwark is looking to provide.</p></li>
<li><p>We have already <a href="http://35percent.org/heygate-regeneration-faq/">reported</a> on Southwark&rsquo;s loss on the sale of its 25-acre Heygate site at a knock-down price to developer Lend Lease. We don&rsquo;t know how much it sold the Aylesbury for, but we think it&rsquo;s unlikely to recover the estimated £150m cost<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> of demolishing the 60-acre estate. So it doesn&rsquo;t need us to point out the absurdity of selling off structurally-sound council estates on the cheap and then buying back land from the private sector in order to build new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes.</p></li>
</ol>


<p><a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50478/Appendix%202%20Direct%20Delivery%20Sites.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/DirectDeliverySites.png" width="400" height="750"></a>The December Cabinet report also provided an update on the council&rsquo;s progress with its 11,000 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes &lsquo;Direct Delivery&rsquo; programme. Phase one of the programme involving the &lsquo;delivery&rsquo; of 1,500 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes by 2018 is now being finalised, with sites for 837 of these new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes now identified. <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50478/Appendix%202%20Direct%20Delivery%20Sites.pdf">Appendix 2</a> of the report gives a detailed schedule of these 837 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes and where they are to be located.</p>

<p>However, a closer look at the schedule reveals that many of these won&rsquo;t be council homes and that some are being funded by selling off existing stock. For example, the first two entries on the list are supposedly providing 27 new council homes on the East Dulwich estate (Gatebeck House:9 &amp; Southdown House:18). But it doesn&rsquo;t say that a third of these will be for shared ownership<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>; neither does it mention that these 27 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes on the East Dulwich estate, are being funded by selling off land and 50 existing council homes on other parts of the estate: <em>&ldquo;with £2.2m to be raised from the sale of 24 drying room conversions; £8.76m from the sale of 50 voids-for-sale and £4.1m to be raised from the disposal of land&rdquo;</em>.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<p>The next entry on the Direct Delivery schedule is Willow Walk near Old Kent Road, which is supposedly providing 75 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes. However, according to paragraphs 5 &amp; 6 of the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/284022_1.pdf">planning report</a> for this development, the 75 units comprise only 21 social rented homes, plus 54 rooms for temporary accommodation (replacing the existing temporary accommodation unit) - very welcome no doubt but not 75 council homes.</p>

<p>Next on the schedule is the site of the former Nunhead Community Centre, which is supposedly providing 8 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes. What it doesn&rsquo;t mention is that a large (1000 sqm) council-owned community centre is being demolished to make way for these and that the 8 new council homes will be <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/304415_1.pdf">accompanied</a> by 14 new homes for private sale.</p>

<p>Another council-owned community centre and some workshops are being demolished in Sumner road, Peckham. The schedule says that this site will provide 112 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes. What it doesn&rsquo;t say is that less than half of these (50) will be social-rented; 20 will be shared ownership and the remaining 42 units will be &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes for private sale. (see <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9555190">planning docs</a>)</p>

<p>Of the 25 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes built on the former Masterman House garages in Camberwell, only 15 will be social rented; the remainder will also be &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes for private sale. Just 34 of the 116 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes planned for Commmercial Way will be social rented and so the list goes on. We can&rsquo;t find details for many of the sites listed in the schedule, but we estimate that only around half of the 837 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes listed will be &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes as we know them. The remainder will be shared ownership and &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes for private sale, which doesn&rsquo;t come as a surprise in the wake of the revelations stemming from <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/18/southwark-mipim-and-the-11000-new-council-homes/">our reporting</a> of Southwark&rsquo;s MIPIM attendance this year.</p>

<h2>Footing the bill of regeneration</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://i.huffpost.com/gen/1713650/thumbs/o-ELEPHANT-AND-CASTLE-STATION-facebook.jpg" width="300" height="175">The <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/5293">long-running dispute</a> over who should pay for the capacity upgrades to the northern line tube station in order to meet increased demand from developments, has finally come to an end. Southwark News <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SNroundabout.pdf">reports</a> that of the £154m total cost, TFL have agreed to pay £91m while the council is left to find the remaining £63m. The council&rsquo;s regeneration partner Lend Lease is making a contribution of just £16.3m<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> towards the council&rsquo;s bill - proof that the regeneration partnership is not an equal one, with Southwark bearing the lion&rsquo;s share of costs and Lend Lease reaping the Elephantine profits.</p>

<h2>Untrustworthy imagery</h2>

<p>Lend Lease got a <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/private_eye.jpg">mention</a> in the latest edition of Private Eye. This time for a development in Chiswick, where its PR firm have been accused of producing misleading imagery. The column also pointed out that Paul Dimoldenberg, the head of Lend Lease&rsquo;s PR firm which created the images, also happens to be leader of the Labour group at Westminster council. We can add that Cllr Dimoldenberg also used to be a senior council officer at Southwark.</p>

<p>Our hats go off to Mr Dimoldenberg&rsquo;s firm for its PR image trickery. The following is a visualisation image from the Heygate application. <br/>
<img src="http://www.elephantandcastle-lendlease.com/wp-content/uploads/Homepage-Header-2-Not-sure-if-this-size-image-will-work1.jpg"></p>

<p>Looks nice doesn&rsquo;t it? but what the image doesn&rsquo;t tell you is that this is one of the developments&#8217; 12 &lsquo;raised courtyards&rsquo;, which are enclosed by buildings and will have zero public access:<br/>
<a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/267119_1.pdf"><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/heygate_raised_courtyards2.png"></a></p>

<h2>Coronet uncorrugated</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.theatrestrust.org.uk/store/ttdb/ttt0048/lowres/010997_regular.jpg?1410824878" width="300" height="600">New photographs have been <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SNcoronet.pdf">published</a> showing what the Art Deco Coronet building looks like behind its corrugated blue facade. <br/>
The Coronet is currently under threat of demolition from the shopping centre redevelopment. The shopping centre and neighbouring site are being redeveloped by real estate hedge fund DV4. George Soros backed DV4 is based in the British Virgin Islands and managed by <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2041229/Tory-donor-Jamie-Ritblat-snaps-Olympic-Village-knock-price--costing-275m.html">Delancey&rsquo;s Jamie Ritblatt</a>.</p>

<p>The Theatres Trust has recently submitted an application to have the Coronet listed. You can read more about the campaign on the <a href="http://www.theatrestrust.org.uk/resources/theatres/show/3344-coronet-london">Theatres Trust website</a>, the Save the Coronet campaign <a href="http://coronettheatre.co.uk/home/save-the-coronet/">web page</a> and <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/davehillblog/2014/dec/07/how-the-coronet-can-help-the-elephant">this article</a> by the Guardian&rsquo;s Dave Hill. <br/>
</br></p>

<h2>Unfair trial</h2>

<p>After being unlawfully evicted from his home, having his possessions destroyed and being left street homeless by Southwark council, a Sudanese refugee <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/crime/judge-blasts-southwark-council-for-evicting-sudanese-tenant-and-destroying-his-possessions-9796994.html">won</a> a long-running court case against the council in October. After spending six-figure sums on top QCs to fight the case against the claimaint (who had no legal representation), the council declared last week that the trial was &lsquo;unfair&rsquo; and &lsquo;clearly wrong&rsquo;. An <a href="http://nearlylegal.co.uk/blog/2014/11/southwark-not-appealing/">article</a> about the case by the Giles Peaker, a partner specialising in housing at solicitors Anthony Gold, sums up Southwark&rsquo;s attitude well: <em>&ldquo;disingenuous in the extreme&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<h2>Heygate viability assessment FOI/EIR appeal</h2>

<p>The ongoing battle to disclose the Heygate development viability assessment continues. The Information Tribunal has called a final hearing on 21st January to resolve the ongoing dispute concerning the implementation of its <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/FirstTierDecisionHeygate.pdf">May 2014 decision notice</a>. The hearing will be in closed session attended only by Lend Lease &amp; Southwark&rsquo;s counsel, who will recieve directions as to exactly which of the 22 appendices can be withheld. The Tribunal had previously ruled that the financial model in appendix 22 and the figures related to commercial negotiations for its retail floorspace could be withheld, but there has been a dispute over exactly which of the 22 appendices are related to these. We are expecting the Tribunal to order the viability assessment be disclosed within a short period after the hearing (barring further appeals and heeldragging by Lend Lease &amp; Southwark). After nearly 3 years of battling for its disclosure we are looking forward to finally being able to see why Lend Lease has been so reluctant to show its sums.</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See paragraph 142 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s43556/Report%20Selection%20of%20a%20Preferred%20Partner%20to%20Work%20with%20the%20Council%20to%20Deliver%20the%20Regeneration%20of%20the.pdf">this Jan 2014 council briefing report</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See paragraph 19 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s36276/Report%20East%20Dulwich%20Estate%20Regeneration%20Scheme%20and%20Scheme%20Finance%20Update.pdf">this March 2013 Cabinet report</a>.  <a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See paragraph 16 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s36276/Report%20East%20Dulwich%20Estate%20Regeneration%20Scheme%20and%20Scheme%20Finance%20Update.pdf">this March 2013 Cabinet report</a>.  <a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>See &lsquo;E&amp;C Strategic Transport&rsquo; contributions in each of Lend Lease&rsquo;s planning applications: <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/249091_1.pdf">One the Elephant (£2m)</a>, <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/224053_1.pdf">Heygate masterplan (£11.7m)</a> &amp; <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/238280_1.pdf">Heygate phase 1 (£2.6m)</a> <a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury Estate - Back to the Drawing Board?]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/15/aylesbury-estate-back-to-the-drawing-board/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-15T15:13:56+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/15/aylesbury-estate-back-to-the-drawing-board</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/pagenotfound.png" width="300" height="200">The planning documents for the Aylesbury estate outline masterplan have been <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557153">removed</a> from Southwark council&rsquo;s planning portal. The documents for the first development site under the masterplan have also been <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557152">removed</a>. The applications were <a href="http://35percent.org/images/scan0027.pdf">lodged</a> on 25th September and the documents uploaded about a month later. On inquiry, Southwark said that the applications had been <em>&ldquo;uploaded in error, they are currently invalid and not open to consultation.&rdquo;</em> It also said that <em>&ldquo;as soon as the relevant documentation has been received .. and been made valid they will be posted on the website&rdquo;</em>. It is not clear whether the applications have been withdrawn and now need to be re-submitted. Our <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">previous blog</a> on the Aylesbury applications pointed out - amongst other things - that 934 social rented homes are to be lost if the development goes ahead as planned.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, Aylesbury leaseholders are fighting to get a fair deal from the council and its development partners Notting Hill Housing &amp; Barratt Homes. A leaseholders&#8217; <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50093/Report%20Deputation%20Requests.pdf">deputation</a> will be submitting <a href="https://halag.files.wordpress.com/2014/11/alag_depuation18nov_finalversion.pdf">5 demands</a> to the council&rsquo;s Cabinet meeting on Tuesday. Amongst their very sensible requirements is one that any council officer who values their homes is actually qualified to do so, as it turns out this is not always the case: a leaseholder&rsquo;s complaint to the recognised professional body (RICS) could not be dealt with because the officers concerned were not RICS qualified or registered. The leaseholders have requested instead that valuations are conducted by the District Valuer Service.</p>

<p>At the same meeting, Southwark will also be receiving a deputation from the <a href="http://www.sgto.org.uk/">Southwark Group of Tenants Organisation</a>, who also have some <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s49943/Appendix%206%20Six%20alternative%20pledges%20from%20SGTO.pdf">suggestions</a>, this time about improving the six pledges Southwark has made for conducting its consultation on building 11,000 new council homes. Southwark should adopt these improved pledges, it will be a step in the right direction, but it is also <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/08/southwark-fails-to-deliver/">clear</a> that the Council already has definite ideas about how these new homes will be provided, including estate regeneration and estate infill.</p>

<h2>Head in the clouds</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/betterelephant/status/531882170424786944"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/tweet.png" width="400" height="800"></a>Southwark&rsquo;s Head of Regeneration Councillor Mark Williams, obviously got a bit giddy last week at the topping out ceremony of Lend Lease&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.onetheelephant.com/apartments/browse-apartments"><strong>One the Elephant</strong></a> tower (or maybe Lend Lease plied him with too much champagne). He <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/01/11/flogging-the-elephant/">tweeted</a> from the rooftop ceremony about the wonderful view as well as the <em>&ldquo;new homes, jobs and leisure centre for local residents&rdquo;</em>. A second tweet claimed that the development was providing £12.5m towards the new leisure centre (costing £25m), but as we can see below from the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/305818_1.pdf">legal agreement</a> the figure is actually only £3.5m. Lend Lease got out of providing any on-site affordable housing or making any payment in-lieu for the development through the magic of viability assessments and as we showed in a <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/01/11/flogging-the-elephant/">previous blog</a> Southwark should have netted £33.2m under its <a href="http://35percent.org/images/affordablehousingspg.pdf">in-lieu affordable housing payment tariff</a>.<br/>
<a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/305818_1.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/leisurecentrecontribution.png"></a></p>

<p>Southwark also <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LandRegistry_OneTheElephant.pdf">sold</a> the <strong>One the Elephant</strong> land to Lend Lease for the price of £6.5m (£4.6m per acre), which is a bargain considering that the gross development value of the tower will be upwards of £230m<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Our interactive map also shows how this compares to other land sales at the Elephant:</p>

<center>
<iframe src="http://35percent.org/map.html" width="800" height="600"></iframe>
</br><font size="2">Click <a href="http://35percent.org/map.html">here</a> to view our interactive map in a separate browser window</font>
</center>


<p></br></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/robertabwMP/status/531797457492250624"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/blackmanwoods.png" width="400" height="650"></a>While Cllr Williams&#8217; head was in the clouds, Labour shadow minister for planning, Roberta Blackman-Woods, was keeping her feet firmly on the ground when she visited the Heygate site last week, <a href="https://twitter.com/robertabwMP/status/531797457492250624">tweeting</a> that Lend Lease&rsquo;s scheme was <em>&ldquo;very interesting&rdquo;</em>. Ms Woods might also be interested in the risks local authorities run when they enter into partnership agreements with global property giants like Lend Lease, as illustrated by <a href="http://www.architectureanddesign.com.au/news/lend-lease-nsw-government-dispute-halts-barangaroo">this story</a> from its other major development site in Sydney, Australia, where city authorities stand to lose millions after losing a bitter court battle with Lend Lease over a profit-share agreement.</p>

<p></br>
</br>
</br></p>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>This is based on an expected average sales value of £815 per sq foot, which was the average sales price <a href="http://www.colliers.com/~/media/Files/EMEA/UK/research/residential/201202-central-london-residential-market.pdf">achieved</a> by the Strata tower.  <strong>One the Elephant</strong> comprises 269,000sq ft of residential floorspace in total; the total expected residential sales is therefore £219m (269k X £815), plus 13,000 sq ft of retail in <strong>One the Elephant</strong>&rsquo;s pavilion with an approximate value of £10m.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Southwark Fails to Deliver]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/08/southwark-fails-to-deliver/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-08T19:10:35+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/08/southwark-fails-to-deliver</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/viability.png" width="300" height="200">The Heygate viability assessment saga took a new turn last week. Southwark Council failed to produce the assessment by the given deadline and all parties have been called back to a Tribunal hearing on 11th Dec.</p>

<p>We can only speculate on the cause of the delay, but Southwark Council is beginning to look a bit ridiculous. After spending a six-figure sum and two and a half years appealing against the Information Commissioner, last week Southwark claimed that it has <em>&ldquo;always been keen to see this matter resolved as quickly as possible&rdquo;</em> and that <em>&ldquo;the final version of the document is now on its way to Mr Glasspool&rdquo;</em> .</p>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/SN29Oct2014.pdf"><img class="left" src="http://allpeoplesparty.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/11/Southwark-Council-Release-Heygate-Deal-Now.png" width="500" height="300"></a></p>

<p>There are still serious oustanding questions about many aspects of the redevelopment, not just about the amount of affordable housing that the assessment can help answer (see our <a href="http://35percent.org/heygate-regeneration-faq/">FAQ</a> for a summary of the issues). Both the Information Commissioner and Information Tribunal have ruled that it is heavily in the public interest for this document to be revealed; Southwark should release the assessment without any further delay.</p>

<h2>Spot the difference</h2>

<p>While the tribunal case drags on, Lend Lease are motoring forward with the latest detailed planning application for the Heygate (now known as <a href="http://www.elephantpark.co.uk/">&lsquo;Elephant Park&rsquo;</a>). The application for <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1779/lend_lease_submits_detailed_planning_application_for_around_600_new_homes_at_elephant_park">West Grove (phase MP2)</a> comprises 593 new homes and 43,000 square feet of new retail space.</p>

<p>One thing we have noticed is that the <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/5621">visualisations</a> of the new Heygate supplied during public consultations on the outline application, were based on minimum plot/building sizes. To nobody&rsquo;s surprise it is the maximum plot sizes that Lend Lease are applying for in their detailed applications and as we can see from the image below<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, it makes for a significant difference. It seems that it&rsquo;s only now that we are becoming privy to the true scale of development.</p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/389783_1.pdf"><img src="http://35percent.org/images/parameterheights.png"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/389805_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/mp2affordablehousing.png" width="300" height="300"></a>Despite its size however, Lend Lease can only find room for 26 social rented flats in its latest phase, which won&rsquo;t make much of a dent in Southwark&rsquo;s 20,000-strong housing waiting list.
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>More viability struggles</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not just in Southwark where people are challenging the viability trump card and fighting developers for properly affordable housing. Two notable examples elsewhere are <a href="http://www.wcdg.net/content/waterloos-don-quixote-one-man-against-world">Riverside Communities vs Braeburn estates</a> at the Southbank&rsquo;s Shell Centre development, where developers are getting away with building just 11% affordable housing; and <a href="http://www.eastlondonlines.co.uk/2014/11/stokey-local-votes-to-take-planning-proposal-fight-to-court-of-appeal/">Stokey Local Community Group vs Sainsburys</a> who want to build a new supermarket and flats, but have reduced their offer of affordable housing from 50% to 17%. In both cases, campaigners are trying to get to the truth about viability and pierce the legal smoke screens of commercial confidentiality.</p>

<h2>Cooltan stuffed</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/11/img_0363.jpg?w=208&h=182" width="300" height="200">A new housing and student residence development was approved for Walworth road&rsquo;s Blanchard site last week, to the great disappointment of local mental health charity <a href="http://www.cooltanarts.org.uk/">Cooltan Arts</a> and its many supporters.  A previously approved application contained a legally binding agreement to supply Cooltan (who were previous occupants of the site) with new premises. The site (plus agreement) was sold to another developer, the planning agreement lapsed and the new developer said it was not economically viable to provide Cooltan with what it needed. Southwark Council claimed it had no power to enforce the lapsed agreement and the application was duly approved.</p>

<h2>Coming soon&hellip; a fairer future</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/fairerfuture.png">Southwark Council is beginning its consultation on the New Southwark Plan, which will both incorporate and replace the existing Southwark Plan and Core Strategy planning policy frameworks. It will determine how all land in Southwark will be developed - or not as the case may be. Contentious issues are likely going to be the possible regeneration of council estates, the density of new developments and the protection of green spaces.</p>

<p>The paragraph below in the foreword of the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11161/new_southwark_plan">draft new Plan</a> caught our eye. Southwark&rsquo;s intention to use infill land and pursue estate regeneration as a way of providing 11,000 new council homes, explains why it feels the need to make a <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s47489/Appendix%201%20Draft%20Charter%20of%20Principles.pdf">Charter of Principles</a> of good behaviour when it consults with its council estate residents.<br/>
<img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/newsouthwarkplan.png"></p>

<p>The consultation period for this first draft of the New Southwark Plan and this proposal lasts until 6th March 2015, but Southwark isn&rsquo;t wasting time: an &lsquo;asset management&rsquo; process is already <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">in train</a> and will be making recommendations about potential renewal/regeneration sites to Southwark&rsquo;s Cabinet in December.</p>

<h2>Estate renewal conference</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk/2014/09/30/conference-delivering-estate-renewal/"><img class="right" src="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk/futureoflondon/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/Delivering-Estate-Renewal-postcard-front-1024x721.jpg" width="400" height="300"></a>Last week saw a <a href="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk">Future of London</a> conference entitled <a href="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk/2014/09/30/conference-delivering-estate-renewal/">&lsquo;Delivering Estate Renewal&rsquo;</a>. The conference was co-sponsored by Lend Lease who are described in the <a href="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk/2014/09/30/conference-delivering-estate-renewal/">conference programme</a> as &lsquo;estate-savvy developers&rsquo;. The speakers included representatives from Lend Lease, Notting Hill&rsquo;s CEO Kate Davies and Southwark&rsquo;s Head of Regeneration, Stephen Platts.</p>

<p>A detailed <a href="http://chrisbrown.regen.net/2014/11/10/estate-renewal-community-coproduction/">write-up</a> of the event by Chris Brown from <a href="http://www.iglooregeneration.co.uk/">Igloo Regeneration</a> describes the arithmetic behind the crude logic of estate renewal: a council estate&rsquo;s rental income is subtracted from forecasted maintenance costs to give a &lsquo;net present cost&rsquo;; this is then compared against the estimated development value of the estate as a cleared site, so that local authorities can <em>&ldquo;get rid of the financial underperformers&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Brown says that he was <em>&ldquo;taken to task&rdquo;</em> during the conference, by Southwark&rsquo;s Stephen Platts over his <em>&ldquo;description of the Heygate estate renewal as a social disaster&rdquo;</em> and that his attempts to highlight the social cost of displacing communities seemed to fall on deaf ears.</p>

<h2>Baby shard gets go-ahead</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/imageuploads/1415187088_46.233.112.163.jpg" width="300" height="400">Irvine Sellar and son James attended Southwark&rsquo;s planning committee meeting last Tuesday evening (in a chauffeur-driven limousine). They were there to watch the the council&rsquo;s labour controlled planning committee <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7931">wave through</a> their plans for a 26 storey shard satellite tower.
In presenting the proposals, James Sellar claimed that <em>&ldquo;the proposal before you tonight will for the first time bring residents into the heart of this regeneration. It will create homes and bring vibrancy, ensuring that people working in London Bridge have the opportunity to live there as well.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>However, the Sellars had submitted a viability assessment showing that they couldn&rsquo;t afford to provide any on-site affordable housing provision. Instead, they first <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7915">proposed</a> to meet their affordable housing obligations by funding the stalled redevelopment of the Wood Dene Estate in Peckham. After criticism from opposition councillors the developers have now promised to &lsquo;try&rsquo; and find somewhere in the north of the borough instead. Failing this they have agreed to make an in-lieu payment of £18m - somewhat less than the price of some penthouses currently <a href="http://www.altomagazine.com/news/inside-londons-premier-penthouse-at-neo-bankside-4283694">being sold</a> in the area.</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Image taken from the planning <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9556728">application&rsquo;s</a>&rsquo;s <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/389783_1.pdf">reconciliation statement</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury Estate Planning Applications - 934 Social Rented Homes to Be Lost]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-01T07:57:54+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/398988_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/aylesburynetloss.png" width="450" height="450"></a>After waiting over a month for them to be &lsquo;validated&rsquo; by the council, the planning documents for the Aylesbury estate revelopment are now online.
The application for the First Development Site seeks permission to demolish the Bradenham, Chartridge &amp; Chiltern blocks comprising 630 homes and replace them with 815 new homes (<a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557152">ref:14-AP-3843</a>); 362 of these will be at &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; - a net loss of 204 units (provided that target rent is equivalent to social rent). The amount of free market housing on this first phase will increase from 64 homes (initially bought under right-to-buy) to 412 and there will also be 102 intermediate units.</p>

<p>The 204 social rented units lost on the first phase is a fraction of the total net loss from the Aylesbury regeneration as a whole.  The <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/398988_1.pdf">Housing Statement</a> for the outline application <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557153">(2,735 new homes - ref:14/AP/3844)</a> shows that the social rented housing provision will be reduced by over a third, with a net loss of 934 social rented homes across the estate once the regeneration is completed.</p>

<h3>Target Rent = affordable rent or social rent?</h3>

<p>The table in paragraph 5.11 of the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/398988_1.pdf">Housing Statement</a>, describes &lsquo;Estate Baseline&rsquo; homes as &lsquo;Target and Affordable Rent&rsquo; which they never were; they were council homes at council rents. Using &lsquo;target rent&rsquo;, &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; and &lsquo;social rent&rsquo; as if they are all the same thing confuses and misleads. What people really need to know is how much total rent will new-build tenants be paying, whatever the housing is called?</p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/279910_1.pdf"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/wolvertons106SR.png" width="450" height="450"></a>The previous phase of the Aylesbury redevelopment currently under construction by L&amp;Q gives good reason to worry on this point: as we reported in a <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/05/05/manx-connections-the-off-shore-home-of-the-elephants-developers/">previous blog post</a>, the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/279910_1.pdf">legal agreement</a> for <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/lq-wins-work-on-next-phase-of-aylesbury-plan/6522708.article">that phase</a> contains a definition of &lsquo;social rented&rsquo;, which refers to the <a href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/affordable-rent">HCA definition</a> of Boris Johnson&rsquo;s &lsquo;affordable rented&rsquo; housing product of up to 80% market rents:</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/heygates106SR.png" width="450" height="400">One would normally expect to find a reference to the National Rent Regime under the definition of social rented housing in such documents. This is the regulatory framework which decides the level of social rents based - among other things - on the average level of income. Here is an example of the wording normally used in Southwark&rsquo;s legal agreements securing planning obligations.</p>

<p>Before the legal agreement securing the Aylesbury planning obligations can be signed, the application has to be approved by Southwark&rsquo;s planning committee;  Southwark is also a partner in the regeneration, so it is up to Southwark to ensure that this situation is not repeated and we don&rsquo;t end up with &lsquo;social rented housing&rsquo; that is nothing of the kind.</p>

<h3>Cycling and car parking</h3>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/aylesburycycling.png"><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/aylesburycycling.png" width="400" height="300"></a>The council recently <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7895">announced</a> plans for a &lsquo;Southwark Spine&rsquo; cycle route linking the south to the north of the borough, which is due to cut straight through the new Aylesbury development<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. However, cycle campaign groups have pointed out that the planning applications make no provision for any segregated cycle lanes, instead cyclists will be forced to continue to compete for road space on Thurlow street with buses and cars as the illustrations here show. A <a href="http://www.change.org/p/southwark-council-s-planning-committee-and-transport-department-we-want-physically-segregated-cycle-lanes-on-albany-rd-thurlow-st-and-dutch-standard-prioritised-protected-crossings-for-cyclists-pedestrians-at-cycle-route-junctions-in-the-aylesbury-es">petition</a> has been set up by cycle campaign group <a href="http://stopkillingcyclists.org.">http://stopkillingcyclists.org.</a></p>

<p>Paragraph 2.5 of the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/397955_1.pdf">Transport Statement</a> also confirms that <em>&ldquo;the proposals are for 1378 residential car parking spaces across the development&rdquo;</em>. We think this is excessive in an area with such strong public transport links on the border of zone 1 London. The aerial photo below, taken from the application&rsquo;s <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/397933_1.pdf">Design &amp; Access statement</a> shows the Aylesbury estate masterplan in its geographical context:</p>

<p><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/aylesburyincontext.png"></p>

<h3>Environmental Impact</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2011/1824/schedule/4/made">Planning regulations</a> require major redevelopment applications to provide <em>&ldquo;An outline of the main alternatives studied by the applicant or appellant and an indication of the main reasons for the choice made, taking into account the environmental effects.&rdquo;</em> This is to ensure that developers have properly considered the environmental impact of their proposals against the possible lower impact of alternatives and refurbishment. It would appear that no such appraisal or any detailed cost/benefit analysis has been undertaken in relation to the Aylesbury redevelopment.</p>

<p>UCL&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.engineering.ucl.ac.uk/engineering-exchange/">Engineering Exchange</a> recently published a detailed <a href="http://www.engineering.ucl.ac.uk/engineering-exchange/demolition-refurbishment-social-housing/">report</a> showing that <em>&ldquo;refurbishment of housing is often preferable to demolition and reconstruction&rdquo;</em> when taking into account environmental and social factors. We saw with the Heygate that wholesale decant and demolition costs can far outstrip refurbishment costs: the council spent £65m emptying<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> &amp; £15m demolishing<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> the Heygate when comprehensive refurbishment would have cost just £35m<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>.</p>

<h3>Equalities Impact</h3>

<p><a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/Data/Executive/20050927/Agenda/Item%2007%20-%20The%20AylesburyEstate%20Revised%20Strategy%20-%20Annex%20D.pdf">Council papers</a> state that <em>&ldquo;the Aylesbury is a very diverse community with 67% of people belonging to a minority ethnic group&rdquo;</em>. According to the Equalities Act 2010, the planning application should have included a detailed equalities impact assessment to consider whether the planning proposals will have an adverse effect on any Black and Minority Ethnic(BME) groups. We have been unable to find any such assessment in the supporting documents for either application.</p>

<p>Should you wish to object to the Aylesbury applications you can use the template we have set up on our online comments submission form. Simply click on the following link, enter your details and click to send the objection to the council&rsquo;s planning department:<br/>
<a href="http://commentform.herokuapp.com">http://commentform.herokuapp.com</a></p>

<h2>Southwark suddenly &lsquo;keen to disclose viability assessment&rsquo;</h2>

<p>Southwark&rsquo;s spin doctors were in full spin this week when they <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SN29Oct2014.pdf">announced</a> that the council is about to disclose the Heygate viability assessment. Having spent two years and a sum running into six figures fighting the Information Commissioner&rsquo;s order to disclose the document, Southwark&rsquo;s new regen boss Mark Williams claimed <em>&ldquo;Southwark Council has always been keen to see this matter resolved as quickly as possible.&rdquo;</em> <br/>
The council&rsquo;s sudden keenness to &lsquo;resolve the matter&rsquo; has surely got nothing to do with the fact that at a recent Case Management Hearing, the Tribunal judge gave Southwark a deadline of 5th Nov to disclose the viability assessment&hellip;</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See pg 52 of the council&rsquo;s <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s49335/Appendix%201%20Cycling%20strategy.pdf">draft cycling strategy</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See paragraph 50(ix) of the <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/rnblpa0ajaxk8em/LON_LIB1-%239487917-v1-Lend_Lease_EA_2013_0162_Response_to_LBS_Grounds_of_....pdf">Heygate Tribunal evidence</a> - <em>&ldquo;The Council’s costs as at January 2013 amounted to about £47.5 million in capital expenditure and just under £18 million in review costs managing the estate&rdquo;</em>.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See paragraph 18 of this <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s30387/120709%20Heygate%20Estate%20Demolition%20Business%20Case%20signed%20report.pdf">council report</a> - <em>&ldquo;The baseline budget for the Heygate demolition is estimated to be a total of £15.225m including 10% contingency.&rdquo;</em><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>See this <a href="http://heygateestate.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/genslerheygate.pdf">2012 cost appraisal study</a> by global architects <a href="http://gensler.com">Gensler</a> and construction consultancy <a href="http://baqus.co.uk">Baqus</a>. <a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MIPIM, Southwark and Its 11000 New 'Private and Social' Council Homes]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/18/southwark-mipim-and-the-11000-new-council-homes/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-18T11:54:16+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/18/southwark-mipim-and-the-11000-new-council-homes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://static.guim.co.uk/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2014/10/15/1413393213631/Mipim-property-conference-011.jpg" width="300" height="200">The MIPIM Jamboree last week attracted much protest and media comment, including articles in the <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/oct/14/yacht-cannes-selling-homes-local-government-officials-mipim">Guardian</a> and on the <a href="http://leftfootforward.org/2014/10/the-mipim-property-fair-everything-wrong-with-regeneration/">Left Foot Forward</a> blog, which noted that <em>&ldquo;the Heygate Estate has become the paradigmatic example of the MIPIM-model of property development&rdquo;</em>.
</br></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.lbhf.gov.uk/Images/cllr-stephen-cowan-at-nipim_432_tcm21-191385.jpg" width="250" height="200">MIPIM itself revealed the contrasting attitudes of 3 London Labour boroughs towards developers:
Hammersmith &amp; Fulham <a href="http://www.lbhf.gov.uk/Directory/News/Homes_for_residents_not_overseas_investors.asp">used their stand</a> to make a strong case for development that provides <em>&ldquo;Homes for residents, not overseas investors&rdquo;</em>. It highlighted developers using <em>&ldquo;ridiculous viability assessments that offer piffling amounts of affordable homes&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Islington council leader Richard Watts said in <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/islington.pdf">his response</a> to <a href="http://www.unitetheunion.org/news/labour-councillors-urged-to-boycott-property-developers-fair-as-londons-housing-crisis-mounts/">Unite&rsquo;s call</a> for a boycott: <em>&ldquo;neither I nor anyone else from Islington council will be attending the event&rdquo;</em>. He explained that he was <em>&ldquo;deeply concerned at the lack of genuinely affordable housing in London .. and the increase in foreign investors who are pushing up housing prices to the detriment of our residents.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Southwark council leader Peter John&rsquo;s <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SouthwarkUniteResponse.pdf">response</a> took a different view. He said he would be unable to attend himself, but <em>&ldquo;does not agree with the request and the reasoning behind it&rdquo;</em> because the council needs to <em>&ldquo;continue working with the private sector to ensure that we can deliver as many homes as we can&rdquo;</em>. He concludes by reiterating his <em>&ldquo;commitment to build 11,000 new council homes at social rents.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>This commitment to build 11,000 new council homes has come under increasing scrutiny. Our <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">previous blog post</a> and <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2014/oct/07/southwark-london-regeneration-urban-renewal-social-cleansing-fears">this recent Guardian article</a> show how questions are being asked about whether they will be council homes and whether existing council homes will have to be lost for there to be any gains. So it&rsquo;s not reassuring that Southwark&rsquo;s MIPIM stand display describes the 11,000 new council homes as comprising <em>&ldquo;both private and social&rdquo;</em> housing as this image below shows:<br/>
<a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/southwarkMIPIMstand.png"><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/southwarkMIPIMstand.png"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/MipimStevePlattsJonAbbott.JPG"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/MipimStevePlattsJonAbbott.JPG" width="300" height="200"></a> Heckling protesters spotted Southwark&rsquo;s Head of Property Steve Platts and Head of Regeneration Jon Abbott attending the fair. It&rsquo;s a day out of the office, but they looked a little downcast; no doubt disappointed that Southwark was <a href="http://blog.mipimworld.com/2014/10/announcing-winners-mipim-uk-estates-gazette-awards/">beaten</a> by Croydon and Lambeth to the awards of &lsquo;Best UK Planning Authority&rsquo; and &lsquo;Best Public/Private Partnership&rsquo;.</p>

<p>If you would like to enjoy the full MIPIM experience without the canapés and champagne, click on this <a href="http://www.inspiredlabs.com/mipimuk/?project=MIPIM/Mipim-Uk-2014/GroundR/main&amp;bubble=day&amp;yaw=0.09&amp;fov=65&amp;location=loc000&amp;pitch=0">interactive floorplan</a> of the property fair.</p>

<h3>Developers ride the bus</h3>

<p><a href="http://t.co/LZwNl9yC2T"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/mipimbus.png" width="300" height="200"></a>We hope if you live in Southwark, you didn&rsquo;t see this bus driving down your street last week. It was full of MIPIM property developers making a quick trip from Earls Court, no doubt scoping out sites in the developer-friendly <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/11/southwark-gets-its-reward/">&lsquo;can do&rsquo;</a> borough of Southwark.
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>Evicting Aylesbury</h2>

<p><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/4/3941/14931046894_7eca1011dd_n.jpg" align="right">A High Court ruling <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/crime/judge-blasts-southwark-council-for-evicting-sudanese-tenant-and-destroying-his-possessions-9796994.html">condemning</a> Southwark officers for having conspired to evict a tenant from an estate in its North Peckham regeneration, is followed by news of a temporary tenant on the Aylesbury estate <a href="http://housingactionsouthwarkandlambeth.wordpress.com/2014/09/27/keeping-people-in-their-homes-a-southwark-council-guide-to-homelessness/">evicted</a> and left entirely homeless. HASL staged a protest in the Council&rsquo;s HQ on Thursday accompanied by the Focus E15 mums and the evictee; and refused to leave the lobby until the poor disabled woman was given a roof over her head. Southwark <a href="http://housingactionsouthwarkandlambeth.wordpress.com/2014/10/16/massive-housing-solidarity-southwark-council-ineptitude/">acquiesced</a> to the request and she was offered temporary accommodation (albeit with stairs..)</p>

<h3>Aylesbury estate SGTO meeting</h3>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SGTO25OctLeaflet4.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SGTOFlyer.png" width="200" height="350"></a>The disruptive impact of regenerations like the Heygate and the Aylesbury on people throughout Southwark has become more apparent day by day. It is not just that council tenants lose their homes, but that leaseholders get displaced and that housing and rehousing opportunities are lost for anyone on the council waiting list. The Southwark Group of Tenants Association has called a <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SGTO25OctLeaflet4.pdf">public meeting</a> about the future of the Aylesbury estate and the demolition of council homes. <a href="http://halag.wordpress.com/">Threatened Aylesbury leaseholders</a> will also be taking part in the meeting. In the meantime - 3 weeks since their submission - the Aylesbury planning applications have appeared on Southwark Council&rsquo;s planning portal (ref. numbers <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557152">14/AP/3843</a> and <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557153">14/AP/3844</a>) but we can&rsquo;t tell whether the applications meet with affordable housing requirements because there are still no planning documents online. Last week we emailed the council&rsquo;s planning dept to ask about the delay and we have still had no reply.</p>

<h2>Heygate FOI/EIR Tribunal Case</h2>

<p>Parties to the Heygate FOI/EIR Tribunal case reconvened at a &lsquo;Case Management Hearing&rsquo; last week. The hearing was called by respondent to the case Adrian Glasspool, who had complained that disclosure of the viability assessment had still not taken place following the Tribunal&rsquo;s decison at the beginning of May. After hearing an account of progress so far, Southwark, Lend Lease and the Information Commissioner were directed to meet on 29th October to try to resolve any outstanding issues concerning the final disclosure. The judge also asked for parties&#8217; availability for a further hearing - should it be needed - in December.</p>

<p>Another <a href="http://discussion.theguardian.com/comment-permalink/42351530">challenge</a> against a developer&rsquo;s use of viability assessments in Stoke Newington can be added to the list of challenges in our <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/11/southwark-gets-its-reward/">previous blog post</a>. Again the developer is arguing that local people simply would not understand what it is all about, just as was the argument in the Heygate FOI/EIR Tribunal case. After 3 days of argument in the High Court, the judge has retired to consider his verdict.</p>

<h2>Lyons Review reviews viability</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/lyonsreview.png" width="200" height="75">Viability assessments are also rapidly rising up the political agenda: the <a href="http://www.yourbritain.org.uk/uploads/editor/files/The_Lyons_Housing_Review_2.pdf">Lyons Housing Review</a> commissioned by the Labour Party and published last week, has identified <em>&ldquo;substantial concerns about the way in which the viability of local plans, CIL charging schedules and sites are tested. Evidence to the review suggested that this is compounded by the fact that there is no agreed methodology for viability assessment, which allows different parties to pick the methodology most to their advantage .. evidence to the review suggested that the current arrangements create a great deal of uncertainty and complexity, which works in favour of the partner with the most skilled consultants acting for it.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>The report then makes some suggestions for how the viability testing process can be improved:</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Definitive guidance should be produced to ensure a single and robust methodology for viability assessments to reduce the scope for different interpretations of viability and reduce uncertainty.&rdquo;</em> It argues that an <em>&ldquo;&lsquo;open-book&rsquo; approach to negotiating site specific viability is required, to increase transparency and speed of negotiations.&rdquo;</em> It also proposes <em>&ldquo;an arbitration service for S106 on large scale developments to be funded by the parties involved in the negotiation&rdquo;</em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Southwark Gets Its Reward]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/11/southwark-gets-its-reward/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-11T13:06:21+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/11/southwark-gets-its-reward</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.mipimuk-awards.co.uk/mipimukawards2014/shortlist"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/MipimAwards.jpg" width="350" height="230"></a>Southwark prides itself on being a &lsquo;developer friendly&rsquo; borough. It has been <a href="http://vimeo.com/71882474#t=125s">endorsed</a> by Lend Lease Director Rob Deck as a <strong>&lsquo;can do&rsquo;</strong> council and it has been <a href="http://www.mipimuk-awards.co.uk/mipimukawards2014/shortlist">shortlisted</a> (by developers) for the award of <strong>&lsquo;Best UK Planning Authority&rsquo;</strong> at next week&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.mipimuk.co.uk/"><strong>MIPIM</strong> jamboree</a>. But pressure is mounting on all councils including Southwark to withdraw from the MIPIM backscratching get-together. Over two dozen community groups, charities and trade unions have <a href="http://radicalhousingnetwork.org/mipim-uk/whos-opposing-mipim/">opposed MIPIM</a>. Unite, Britains largest union has <a href="http://www.unitetheunion.org/news/labour-councillors-urged-to-boycott-property-developers-fair-as-londons-housing-crisis-mounts/">written</a> to all of London&rsquo;s Labour-controlled councils  asking them to <em>&ldquo;withdraw from participation in MIPIM and the close relationships with private developers that the event seeks to foster.&rdquo;</em>; three have done so but not Southwark.</p>

<p><a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BzdVDNBCAAMCUu0.png"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BzdVDNBCAAMCUu0.png" width="350" height="230"></a>So it is a particulary embarrasing moment for Lend Lease to <a href="http://www.asx.com.au/asxpdf/20141009/pdf/42ss0tfmnqrw92.pdf">announce</a> on the Sydney Stock Exchange pre-sales totalling £312m (AUD$ 570m) from just 20% of the 3,000 homes it is building at the Elephant &amp; Castle. As we detailed in our <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/09/20/setting-the-record-straight/">previous blog</a>, Southwark is going to have to wait 11 years before it gets a sniff of any profit from the Heygate and so far Southwark has received just £15m of its £50m Heygate land receipt while having spent over £65m emptying and demolishing the estate.</p>

<h2>Developers behaving badly</h2>

<p>Some good examples of bad behaviour by developers using viability assessments to avoid building affordable housing are beginning to emerge.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/neobanksidecomparison.jpg" width="400" height="300">In Southwark, properties in the Neo Bankside development, opposite Tate Modern, were  <a href="http://www.colliers.com/~/media/Files/EMEA/UK/research/residential/201202-central-london-residential-market.pdf">reported</a> to be selling for an average of <strong>£1,326 per square foot</strong> in 2012, nearly double that claimed by developer <strong>Grosvenor</strong> when planning permission was granted: <strong>Grosvenor</strong>&rsquo;s <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6014_1.pdf">viability assessment</a> claimed its residential properties would sell for an average of just <strong>£754 per square foot</strong><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. These figures also take no account of the <a href="http://online.wsj.com/articles/europe-house-of-the-day-luxury-penthouse-on-the-bank-of-the-thames-photos-1412674116">unsold penthouses</a>, which are <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7512">currently on the market</a> for £22m (each). Put simply: the developer undervalued its development by at least £143m in order to avoid affordable housing requirements<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/NEOBanksidePenthouse.jpg" width="300" height="200">Southwark Council didn&rsquo;t refer the Neo Bankside viability assessment to the <a href="http://www.voa.gov.uk/DVS/index.html">District Valuer</a> or other independent expert for appraisal, but had its Internal Property Division look it over instead<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>. Its Property team recommended that the council accept the developer&rsquo;s poverty plea and settle for a <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/5356">conciliatory offer of a £9m in-lieu payment</a>. Based on Southwark&rsquo;s in-lieu affordable housing tariff <sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> this was a whopping gain to the developer of £16.2m.
The absence of any review or reappraisal mechanism in the planning approval, means that there is no chance that Southwark - or anyone in Southwark who needs affordable housing - will benefit from the properties being sold for twice the developer&rsquo;s original estimate.</p>

<p>Developer <strong>Grosvenor</strong>&rsquo;s viability assessment can currently be <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6014_1.pdf">viewed</a> on the council&rsquo;s planning portal. We presume this was a mistake by Southwark, so in the event that it gets removed we have uploaded a backup copy which can be viewed online <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6014_1.pdf">here</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SKMBT_DVSReport.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/DVSReport.png" width="200" height="350"></a>In Kensington &amp; Chelsea, the <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SKMBT_DVSReport.pdf">District Valuer&rsquo;s report</a> evaluating the developer&rsquo;s viability assessment for the Earl&rsquo;s Court regeneration was <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/development/earls-court-developer-ignored-house-price-rises/7005985.article">finally disclosed</a> thanks to the efforts of local campaigners. The report was highly critical, stating that the developer&rsquo;s assessment <em>&ldquo;ignores residential growth in values that occurs between construction start on site and the commencement of marketing and phased release of the dwellings&rdquo;</em>. The report concluded by recommending that the council implement a <em>‘review mechanism’</em> so that it could increase the level of affordable housing in line with changing market conditions throughout the 22 year scheme. Unfortunately, no such review mechanism was put in place.</p>

<p>In Fitzrovia, developer <strong>TMCT Associates</strong> has adopted a different tack: instead of underestimating sales values it has inflated build costs in its application for an office to residential conversion at Eastgate House, just around the corner from Tottenham Court Rd. As is usually the case here and elsewhere, Westminster planning committee were initially denied access to the viability assessment, but councillors have now demanded to see it. <a href="http://fitzrovia.org.uk/">Fitzrovia Neighbourhood Association</a> has got there first, and it has published <a href="http://news.fitzrovia.org.uk/2014/10/09/affordable-housing-viability-and-profit/">an account</a> of what it found in its newspaper Fitzrovia News. The Developer has estimated that it will cost a staggering £1.2m <strong>per flat</strong> to convert from offices to residential.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://ystudio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/gp2.jpg" width="300" height="200">Over in the huge <a href="http://knightdragon.com/greenwich-peninsula/current">Greenwich Peninsula regeneration</a> of 10,000 homes, Hong Kong developer <a href="http://knightdragon.com/"><strong>Knight Dragon</strong></a> has secured a reduction in the amount of affordable housing from 38% to 21%. Local campaigners City Peninsula Residents Association are fighting back and are due to appear at an Information Tribunal hearing in January in their efforts to reveal the viability assessment, which justifies the loss of around 1,700 affordable homes. The use of viability assessments in Greenwich <a href="http://www.thisislocallondon.co.uk/news/11500983._Pushing_poor_people_out____Greenwich_accused_of_affordable_housing_failure/">appears to be rampant</a>: none of the approved major developments over the last 12 months meets Greenwich&rsquo;s minimum requirement for 35% affordable housing.</p>

<h2>The benefit of review mechanisms</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BprjPdsCQAEG0ze.png" width="300" height="200">A recurring feature of planning approvals involving viability assessments is the absence of any review mechanism. This means that any uplift in London property prices between the approval of planning and sale of new homes will not be reflected in an increased affordable housing offer. This will be the case on the Heygate estate, where Southwark failed to follow the District Valuer&rsquo;s recommendation that a <em>&lsquo;review mechanism linked with delivery&rsquo;</em> should be made a condition of planning approval<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>. The 37% increase in Southwark&rsquo;s property prices since The Heygate planning application was submitted, will therefore be translated directly into developer profit; the £101m worth of affordable housing that Lend Lease said it couldn&rsquo;t afford to provide remains permanently written off. The Heygate development is not due to be completed until 2025. Any further increase in London property prices over the next 11 years will be converted into Lend Lease profit; the measly affordable housing offer of 79 social rented units out of 2,735 new homes will remain unchanged.</p>

<p>Review/re-appraisal mechanisms for viability assessments don&rsquo;t just make good sense: as well as being in Southwark&rsquo;s case a policy requirement<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>, they are recommended in the official RICS guidance on viability testing[^6].</p>

<p>Some other councils are starting to wake up to the problem of the misuse of viability assessments: Inside Housing <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/islingtons-planning-backlash-at-developer-super-profits/7005936.article">reported</a> that Islington Council plans to <em>&ldquo;clamp down on ‘artificially pessimistic’ viability studies used by developers to minimise affordable housing obligations.&rdquo;</em> Islington Council said it comes after it had <em>&ldquo;received a ‘significant number’ of viability studies that do not provide underlying methodology and modelling. These studies are ‘unsupported by robust evidence’ and create ‘an artificially pessimistic outcome’.&rdquo;</em></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See page 11 of the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6014_1.pdf">viability assessment</a> submitted by the developer and which is currently published (we presume mistakably) on the council&rsquo;s planning portal.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>£1,326 - £754 = £572 x 250,000 (<a href="http://www.native-land.com/development-portfolio/neo-bankside">total sqft residential</a>) = undervalued by £143m.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See paragraph 46 of the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/159669_1.pdf">Officer&rsquo;s report.</a><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://35percent.org/images/affordablehousingspg.pdf">planning policy</a> requires all developments in the North of the borough without on-site affordable housing to pay a minimum of £100,000 per habitable room in lieu of each affordable housing unit not provided (i.e. 35% of the total number of habitable rooms which in this case is <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6006_1.pdf">720 habitable rooms</a> = 252 x £100k = £25.2m). Indeed, developments on the riverside should provide more and are determined on a &lsquo;case-by-case&rsquo; basis. <a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>See paragraph 3.6.4 of RICS Guidance <a href="http://www.pas.gov.uk/c/document_library/get_file?uuid=2c5c4f63-5010-4839-83f9-4955cf09e0a9&amp;groupId=332612">Financial Viability in Planning 2012</a><a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>See paragraph 7.3.4 of Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/6069/draft_affordable_housing_spd_2011">Affordable Housing SPD</a><a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let's Talk About... Peter's Promises]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-04T15:21:48+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SNHeygateOverage.pdf"><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SN1100homes.png" width="400" align="right"></a>Southwark Council leader Peter John has pledged that the 11,000 new council homes to be built over the next 30 years will not entail the demolition of the same number of existing council homes. In an <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10997/an_open_letter_from_cllr_peter_john_leader_of_southwark_council">open letter</a> to all residents Cllr John says;</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;To be absolutely clear, the 11,000 new homes that we promise to deliver will be new homes additional to our existing stock. These will be council homes on council rents for those that need them. It has been said that what we are intending to do is demolish 11,000 existing council homes and replace them to reach our target of 11,000. This is just not true. These are new homes and do not include the existing stock of council housing.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200463/community_conversations/2923/lets_talk_about_new_council_homes_for_southwark"><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/communityconversation.png" width="300" height="200" align="left"></a>This emphatic promise has been prompted by residents’ concern about some of the questions Southwark are asking in their <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200463/community_conversations/2923/lets_talk_about_new_council_homes_for_southwark">resident survey</a> entitled <strong>‘Let’s talk about&hellip;new council homes for Southwark’</strong>. The survey seeks resident approval of a Charter of Principals for how the Council <em>‘will work with residents on our programme of investment and renewal’</em>. The <a href="http://www.sgto.org.uk/">Southwark Group of Tenants Association</a>&rsquo;s newsletter (issue 15) says that the survey <em>‘seems to confuse the building of 11,000 homes with the ‘renewal’ or ‘redevelopment’ of estates’</em>. Southwark Defend Council Housing puts it stronger - <em>‘Southwark Council threatens massive redevelopment of its housing estates in Camberwell &amp; Peckham’</em>, and links the questions to Southwark’s new CIL <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/07/23/mystery-objector-1301/"><em>‘Estate Renewal Zone&#8217;</em></a>.</p>

<h3>..the price tag</h3>

<p><img src="http://35percent.org/images/CILChargingZones.png" width="200" align ="right">All agree that building 11,000 council homes is a good promise and is off to a good start<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, but the promise now looks as if it has a price attached, a price which the resident survey is very artfully concealing. The survey talks of ‘principles’ and ‘pledges’ but makes no mention of the asset appraisal study of council stock that will determine which estates are chosen for redevelopment, nor the part the survey itself will play in making those choices. The asset appraisal study is due to be completed by December and is described in a recent council <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">cabinet report - ‘Next steps on Developing Long Term Plans for the Delivery of New Council Homes’</a>. The report says that the council must <em>‘identify as much potential land as possible for development opportunity’</em><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. This requires <em>‘a detailed and comprehensive appraisal be undertaken of the performance of the Housing Revenue Account (HRA) assets’</em><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> (ie council homes), leading to <em>‘an assessment of their worth to the housing business’</em><sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>.</p>

<h3>..the <strong>Asset Performance Evaluation Tool</strong></h3>

<p>Establishing the financial ‘worth’ of each council home does not end the process. Southwark will also look at ‘non-financial’ factors – income, employment, health, education and social exclusion – to see which stock <em>‘prevents the council effectively meeting its social housing objectives’</em><sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>. An <em>&lsquo;Asset Performance Evaluation Tool&rsquo;</em>, which includes <em>‘a measure of social return based on feedback from engagement with residents’</em><sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>, will ‘enable’ the council to reach its decisions.</p>

<p>Finally Southwark will make <em>‘a correlation of these results with open market values and development potential across the stock will identify candidate groups of assets where more detailed options appraisal could result in either opportunities for additional homes or improvements in values to the overall HRA business plan, increasing the surpluses that may be available to subsidise new developments.’</em><sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" rel="footnote">7</a></sup></p>

<p>Putting all this into plain English, Southwark will put a financial value on each of its estates, take a look at the lifestyles of its tenants and residents and estimate how much the land is worth to developers. The ‘options’ will then open up, including sell-offs (aka ‘improvements in value to the overall HRA business plan’). Putting it even more simply, it looks like Southwark will;</p>

<ul>
<li>see how much each council estate is worth&hellip;</li>
<li>see which ones it doesn’t like&hellip;.</li>
<li>see which ones it wants to ‘redevelop’&hellip;.</li>
</ul>


<p>This all paints a rather alarming picture, particularly in light of the Heygate experience where an <a href="http://betterelephant.org/blog/2012/12/23/1998-southwark-housing-stock-survey/">options appraisal study</a> which recommended retaining half the estate&rsquo;s buildings was ignored. The 35% campaign has requested a copy of the <strong>&lsquo;Asset Performance Evaluation Tool&rsquo;</strong> given the key part it looks like playing in the future of every Southwark council estate resident.</p>

<h2>Aylesbury - Stop Press</h2>

<p>The long-anticipated outline planning application and phase 1b/1c demolition applications have been submitted to Southwark Council. Residents in the first phase have received <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/scan0027.pdf">this letter</a> from agents acting on behalf of Notting Hill Housing Trust and Barratt. However, despite having been submitted on 25th September, there are no planning documents online yet. All we know at the moment is that the outline application is for 2,745 new &lsquo;private and affordable units&rsquo; including 1,070 parking spaces plus retail, office &amp; community space. The detailed application proposals include 815 new homes, new roads and some <em>&lsquo;public and private open space&rsquo;</em>.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Phases 1 &amp; 2 of the programme will deliver 447 social rented homes out of 669 total units by early 2016. <a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See para. 41 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See para. 50 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>See para. 50 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>See para. 51 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>See para. 55 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:7">
<p>See para. 53 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elephant Traders - Not in the Pink]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/09/27/penrose-street-sorting-office/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-27T09:31:46+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2014/09/27/penrose-street-sorting-office</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://tradingplaces-elephant.tumblr.com/"><img class="right" src="http://33.media.tumblr.com/eb768bd9c749502c3d8926ced246593f/tumblr_nbcjwdMLuv1tklzg2o1_1280.jpg" width="200" height="300"></a>We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/07/12/the-more-rent-seeking-elephants-at-elephant-the-better/">blogged</a> on 12th July about <a href="http://www.social-life.co/blog/post/Trading_Places_Elephant_and_Castle_regen/"><em>Social Life</em></a>, a social enterprise based on the Pullens estate. They have now completed their research on the Elephant &amp; Castle shopping centre redevelopment and how it is affecting the traders there. A concise and impressive report is now available <a href="http://tradingplaces-elephant.tumblr.com/">here</a>. Its conclusions will not surprise people familiar with the shopping centre. It says: <em>&ldquo;Overall, traders are anxious and concerned about the redvelopment. Many of the traders have mixed feelings about the plans.&rdquo;</em>;<em>&ldquo;The shopping centre is an important social space for traders, local people and regular customers and it plays a hugely important role in the social life of the local community.&rdquo;</em>;<em>&ldquo;The shopping centre supports dense networks of social relationships in the local area, across London and globally.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>We hope developers Delancey have read this report and are giving it full weight in their forthcoming planning application for the shopping centre&rsquo;s redevelopment. However, we hear from several sources that they are not treating the current occupants very well: rents are being raised and new rental agreements are in the form of licences rather than leases, which points towards them getting rid of shopkeepers rather than keeping them. An <a href="http://www.theprisma.co.uk/2014/09/21/how-changes-in-elephant-castle-will-affect-the-latino-community/">interview</a> with respected academic and Director of <a href="http://latinelephant.wordpress.com/">Latin Elephant</a> Patria Roman paints a similar picture. Nevertheless, one shopping centre leaseholder and popular venue for Latin American events appears to be fighting back - the <a href="https://www.change.org/p/southwark-council-save-the-coronet">&lsquo;Save the Coronet&rsquo; petition</a> now stands at 3,856 signatures.</p>

<h2>Sorting Office sorted?</h2>


<p><img class="left" src="http://walworthsociety.co.uk/images/Copy%20of%20image%20001%20-%20resized.jpg" width="300" height="150">Two contentious planning applications are pending just down the road from the Elephant in Walworth. One of these would see the effective demolition of a local heritage asset - the former sorting office on Penrose street, the other could jeopardise the future of much loved and valued local mental health charity <em>Cooltan Arts</em>.</p>

<p>The Sorting Office was built in 1897 and the Walworth Society has long been <a href="http://walworthsociety.co.uk/index.php/blog/116-31-penrose-street-walworths-victorian-sorting-office">campaigning</a> to have it retained as part of the extensive redevelopment of the area. A previous planning application was refused after a large number of objections to its demolition. Its owner is now back with <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9554889">another application</a> which looks like a prime example of &lsquo;facadism&rsquo;: an increasingly common practice which has been <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/architecture-design-blog/2014/aug/25/front-facade-bad-developments-ruining-historic-buildings">described</a> in the development industry as a <em>&ldquo;wilful two fingers up&rdquo;</em> to local planners.</p>

<p>The application is for 6 x 3 storey and 2 x 2 storey town houses, 8 being just below Southwark&rsquo;s threshold for an affordable housing contribution. They will be squeezed behind the retained facade and side wall, but require the demolition of the rest of the sorting office and surrounding outbuildings.</p>

<h2>Cooltan Arts - threat</h2>


<p><img class="right" src="http://www.cooltanarts.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/DSCF4054-lr.jpg" width="300" height="200">Cooltan Arts, long term residents of the Walworth road were relocated last year on the <a href="http://www.cooltanarts.org.uk/2013/10/cooltan-arts-community-space-for-237-walworth-road/">promise</a> that they would be able to return to redveloped premises on their former site off the Walworth road. But a revised planning application for the site no longer contains this promise to reprovide space for Cooltan (nor does it contain the amount of affordable housing required by policy). Objections to the application <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeResultDetail&amp;TheSystemkey=9553921">ref:(14/AP/0830)</a> can still be sent to <a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#x6c;&#116;&#111;&#58;&#x70;&#108;&#x61;&#x6e;&#110;&#105;&#110;&#x67;&#x2e;&#97;&#112;&#x70;&#x6c;&#105;&#99;&#x61;&#116;&#x69;&#x6f;&#x6e;&#115;&#64;&#x73;&#x6f;&#x75;&#116;&#x68;&#119;&#97;&#x72;&#107;&#46;&#x67;&#x6f;&#x76;&#x2e;&#x75;&#107;&#46;">&#x70;&#108;&#97;&#110;&#x6e;&#105;&#110;&#103;&#x2e;&#x61;&#112;&#112;&#108;&#105;&#99;&#x61;&#116;&#105;&#111;&#110;&#x73;&#x40;&#x73;&#x6f;&#x75;&#116;&#104;&#119;&#97;&#114;&#x6b;&#x2e;&#103;&#x6f;&#x76;&#x2e;&#117;&#x6b;&#46;</a></p>

<h2>Developers award Southwark top marks</h2>


<p>Southwark Council has been <a href="http://www.mipimuk-awards.co.uk/mipimukawards2014/shortlist">shortlisted</a> for two awards at the latest property developers&#8217; jamboree <strong>&lsquo;MIPIM UK&rsquo;</strong>, due to be held at Kensington Olympia on 15th-17th October. Southwark is in the running to be both <em>&ldquo;UK best planning authority of the year&rdquo;</em> and <em>&ldquo;Public-Private Partnership of the Year&rdquo;</em> for the Aylesbury estate. The MIPIM awards <a href="http://www.mipimuk-awards.co.uk/mipimukawards2014/shortlist">web page</a> claims that for developers, Southwark is both <em>&ldquo;welcoming and demanding&rdquo;</em>. We agree that it is certainly welcoming but as we have shown, it is not so demanding - especially when it comes to enforcing its own minimum policies on affordable housing contributions.</p>

<p>MIPIM also states in the citation for the Aylesbury partnership award that 75% of its affordable housing will be social rented. We doubt very much that all the new social rented homes will be at social rents and suspect that the forthcoming Aylesbury outline planning application will replace at least some of it with the new so-called &lsquo;affordable rents&#8217;of up to 80% market rent.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/09/peter-j-mipim.jpg?w=500&h=409" width="375" height="375">MIPIM itself is usually held in sunny <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/6687">Cannes</a>. In 2013 the Council leader was <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/SNCannesMipim.pdf">accused</a> of <em>&lsquo;going on a jolly&rsquo;</em> to the event paid for by developer Lend Lease and last year he <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7449">withdrew</a> after protests and demonstrations. This year it is proving equally controversial: several Councils have pulled out after media pressure and an <a href="http://southwarknotes.wordpress.com/2014/09/21/open-letter-to-southwark-council-to-not-attend-mipim/">open letter</a> signed by several local campaign groups asks Southwark to join them. So far Council leader Peter John is unimpressed.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://radicalhousingnetwork.org/">Radical Housing Network</a> is organising protests during the exhibiton on 15th - 17th October.</p>

<h2>Heygate viability assessment latest</h2>


<p>After a long appeal against the Information Commisioner&rsquo;s decision, the Information Tribunal ordered Southwark Council and Lend Lease to disclose the Heygate viability assessment back in May. The Tribunal extended the time for forwarding the assessment to the Information Commissioner back in June, but the assessment has still not been revealed. After inquiries to the Tribunal by Mr Glasspool who requested the information, a case management hearing has now been scheduled for 15th October.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting the Record Straight]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/09/20/setting-the-record-straight/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-20T13:15:14+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2014/09/20/setting-the-record-straight</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Southwark Council has had its feathers ruffled by both the Guardian and the BBC lately. A <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2014/sep/17/truth-property-developers-builders-exploit-planning-cities">Guardian article</a> by Oliver Wainright uses the redevelopment of the Heygate estate as an example of how developers are <em>&lsquo;exploiting planning authorities and ruining our cities&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Southwark Council has posted a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1785/setting_the_record_straight_the_true_value_of_the_elephant_and_castle_regeneration">press statement</a> <strong>&lsquo;setting the record straight&rsquo;</strong>, in which it claims it will receive <em>&ldquo;phased payments as the scheme progresses&rdquo;</em> and this will amount to <em>&ldquo;hundreds of millions&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/HeygateLandReceipts.png"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/rapage70.png" width="400" height="620"></a>It is true that there will be phased payments amounting to £50m (£46m for the main site + £4m for the Rodney road site) - this figure is now well known from the leaked <a href="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf">Regeneration Agreement</a>, but getting the <em>&ldquo;hundreds of millions&rdquo;</em> of pounds depends upon the so-called &lsquo;overage&rsquo; or &lsquo;super-profit&rsquo; and how much this will be, if anything, won&rsquo;t be known until the project is completed in 2025.</p>

<p>The overage will be what is left over after building costs, a 2.6% management fee and 20% priority developer return is deducted from the total sales revenue and it will be calculated according to Lend Lease&rsquo;s financial model, as detailed in a 3000 page spreadsheet known as Appendix 22 of the Heygate viability assessment. This complicated accounting process is entirely under Lend Lease&rsquo;s control and while the Council has the right to inspect the financial model, this may not guarantee the expected overage windfall as the Barangaroo Delivery Authority in Sydney Australia <a href="http://www.smh.com.au/nsw/barangaroo-public-works-in-doubt-after-government-loses-court-battle-with-lend-lease-20140821-106lke.html">is finding out</a> to its cost.</p>

<p>Any reckoning of the gain due to Southwark must also take into account the £65m<a href="#footnote-1">[1]</a> it has spent on Heygate decant costs plus an unquantified amount of public money devoted to regeneration since the wider E&amp;C scheme was conceived, starting with the £25m Single Regeneration Budget (SRB) funding received back in 1999.</p>

<p>On top of the Guardian’s Heygate story the BBC has taken up the plight of Aylesbury leaseholders being &lsquo;forced out of the city&rsquo;, with an <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-london-29098960">online article</a> and televised reports on both its London News and <a href="http://youtu.be/RtvghCKNJjQ">Inside Out programme</a> on 8th Sep. Inside Out did not think much of the paltry amount of compensation leaseholders on the Aylesbury estate were being offered, particularly in comparison to the £340k cost of one-bed properties in the area and described the situation as <em>&lsquo;the Right to Buy dream turned sour&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<center>
<iframe width="350" height="197" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/RtvghCKNJjQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</center>


<p>Southwark again &lsquo;sets the record straight&rsquo; and <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1767/southwark_councils_full_response_to_bbc_inside_out_programme">insists</a> that offers such as <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/05/16/southwark-gives-green-light-to-slum-landlords/">£85k for a 1-bed flat</a> are based on <em>&ldquo;actual market evidence of properties being sold on the Aylesbury estate&rdquo;</em>. This method of basing valuations on the sales prices of other properties depressed by the prospect of demolition has been <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/05/30/aylesbury-leaseholder-fights-incestuous-valuation/">criticised</a> by the Lands Tribunal. Southwark Council&rsquo;s valuers are also pretty imaginative in the way they gather &lsquo;market evidence&rsquo;, using a <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/05/16/southwark-gives-green-light-to-slum-landlords/">1-bed property which had been illegally converted</a> to 4 beds flat as the basis of the compensation for one unfortunate leaseholder.  The derisory compensation offered to Aylesbury leaseholders is in stark contrast to the abundant profit that the builder of the Aylesbury redevelopment Barratt has just <a href="http://www.thisismoney.co.uk/money/markets/article-2750592/Booming-UK-housing-market-fuels-doubling-annual-profits-Barratt.html">announced</a>.</p>

<p>The Guardian and BBC stories reflect a wide-spread public view that developers and housebuilders are making big profits at local people’s expense and taking Southwark for a ride (an <a href="https://www.change.org/p/heygate-estate-scandal-demand-an-investigation">online petition</a> demanding an investigation into the Heygate development has gained over 700 signatures in 3 days) and a couple of press releases from Southwark won’t change this view.</p>

<p><font size="2"><p id="footnote-1">[1] See paragraphs 5.34 &amp; 5.35 of the Project Director&rsquo;s Jan 2013 <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/8171/proofs_of_evidence_%E2%80%93_jon_abbot_%E2%80%93_final_proof">CPO public inquiry evidence.</a> </p></font></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
