<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[35% Campaign]]></title>
  <link href="http://35percent.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://35percent.org/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-03T11:09:09+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://35percent.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[EAN]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Completing London's Clearances]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2016/01/31/completing-londons-clearances/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-31T13:16:31+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2016/01/31/completing-londons-clearances</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://35percent.org/images/david-cameron_peter-john.jpg">
David Cameron&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-minister-pledges-to-transform-sink-estates">announcement</a> that the government will be regenerating 100 council estates across the country, should send a chill down the spine of every council tenant and leaseholder in the country.</p>

<p>This, combined with the Housing &amp; Planning Bill that&rsquo;s being railroaded through parliament, has been interpreted by many as the end of social housing. It is hard to disagree.</p>

<p>Here in Southwark, we know how these estate regenerations - full of <a href="http://35percent.org/affordable-housing/">promises</a> of replacement &lsquo;social&rsquo; housing and <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2013/06/08/the-heygate-diaspora/">rights to return</a> - usually end up. The Heygate is the most notorious example, but it is just one of many:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>   </th>
<th> Estate  </th>
<th> Council homes demolished  </th>
<th> Total new homes  </th>
<th> of which social rented  </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> <img src="http://35percent.org/images/silwood.jpg" width="150" height="150"> </td>
<td> <a href="http://35percent.org/silwood-estate-regeneration/">Silwood estate</a>  </td>
<td> 63  </td>
<td> 127  </td>
<td> 22  </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <img src="http://35percent.org/images/BermondseySpaDemolition.jpg" width="150" height="150">  </td>
<td> <a href="http://35percent.org/bermondsey-spa-regeneration/">Bermondsey Spa</a>  </td>
<td> 131  </td>
<td> 2000  </td>
<td> 314  </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <img src="http://35percent.org/images/elmingtondemolition.jpg" width="150" height="150"> </td>
<td> <a href="http://35percent.org/elmington-estate-regeneration/">Elmington estate</a> </td>
<td> 294  </td>
<td> 279  </td>
<td> 41  </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <img src="http://35percent.org/images/wooddene1.jpg" width="150" height="150"> </td>
<td> <a href="http://35percent.org/wood-dene-estate-regeneration/">Wood Dene estate</a> </td>
<td> 316 </td>
<td> 333 </td>
<td> 54 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <img src="http://35percent.org/images/heygatedemolition.jpg" width="150" height="150"> </td>
<td> <a href="http://35percent.org/heygate-regeneration-faq/">Heygate estate</a> </td>
<td> 1034 </td>
<td> 2704 </td>
<td> 82 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <img src="http://35percent.org/images/aylesburydemolition.jpg" width="150" height="150"> </td>
<td> <a href="http://35percent.org/aylesbury-estate/">Aylesbury estate</a> </td>
<td> 2402 </td>
<td> 3575 </td>
<td> 1471 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <img src="http://35percent.org/images/northpeckham5.jpg" width="150" height="150"> </td>
<td> <a href="http://35percent.org/north-peckham-estate/">North Peckham estate</a> </td>
<td> 3203 </td>
<td> 2019 </td>
<td> 1184 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>   </td>
<td> <strong>Total:</strong> </td>
<td> <strong>7443</strong> </td>
<td> <strong>11037</strong> </td>
<td> <strong>3168</strong> </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p></br>
That&rsquo;s a net loss of 4,275 social rented homes as a direct result of Southwark&rsquo;s regeneration schemes. In addition, we can&rsquo;t even be sure that the replacement social rented housing provided isn&rsquo;t actually affordable rent or won&rsquo;t morph into it - see the <a href="https://youtu.be/x0CIUdfA-JU?t=4m12s">CPO Public Inquiry</a> and our <a href="http://35percent.org/images/Corporate_Complaint_15_Dec_2015Final.pdf">corporate complaint</a> for evidence of this.</p>

<h2>Southwark&rsquo;s estate regeneration pipeline</h2>

<p>Despite widespread criticism, Southwark is <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/28/manifesto-for-destruction-of-council-estates/">ploughing ahead</a> with further regeneration plans, largely informed by a Savills <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s55626/Appendix%204%20Savills%20Evaluation.pdf">&lsquo;Asset Performance Evaluation&rsquo;</a> undertaken last year (the assets being our council homes).</p>

<p>Savills&rsquo;s evaluation informed the Council&rsquo;s <a href="https://consultations.southwark.gov.uk/housing-community-services-department-community-engagement-team/asset-management-consultation/supporting_documents/Asset%20Management%20Strategy.pdf">Housing Asset Management Strategy</a>, which says that <em>&ldquo;11.5% of the stock (4,167 units) has an NPV [Net Present Value] which is below zero&rdquo;</em>. These negative value assets are located on a number of <em>&lsquo;High Investment Needs Estates&rsquo;</em><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> and Savills has recommended that in their case <em>&ldquo;options be explored with residents as to whether a small scale redevelopment or regeneration scheme may deliver better outcomes than direct refurbishment.&rdquo;</em><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/hines.png"><img class="center" src="http://35percent.org/images/hines.png"></a></p>

<p>We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/12/20/heygate-sell-off-how-much-are-we-getting/">blogged</a> about this in December and noted that Savills is just as happy selling off Southwark&rsquo;s high-value assets, as it is identifying those low-value assets that could be candidates for demolition. Savills also prepared the notorious <a href="http://35percent.org/collated-viability-assessments/">viability assessment</a> that <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/06/25/heygate-viability-assessment-finally-revealed/">allowed</a> Lend Lease to slash the social rented housing on <a href="http://www.elephantpark.co.uk">Elephant Park</a> (the New Heygate) to just 82 social rented units.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/savillsauction.jpg' width='' height='' title='Southwark Council homes auctioned off by Savills in Nov 2015'><span class='caption-text'>Southwark Council homes auctioned off by Savills in Nov 2015</span></span></p>

<p>So it comes as no surprise to learn that Savills are the brains behind David Cameron&rsquo;s big idea of &lsquo;regenerating&rsquo; 100 council estates, supplied by their Cabinet Office report <a href="http://www.savills.co.uk/research_articles/141285/198087-0">&lsquo;Completing London&rsquo;s Streets&rsquo;</a>. The report happens to feature a photo of a Southwark estate, the Brandon, to illustrate how the estate&rsquo;s generous green spaces constitute a <em>&ldquo;housing typography&rdquo;</em> that is <em>&ldquo;deeply inappropriate for current and coming decades&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/completing-londons-streets-brandon.png' width='' height='' title='Page 18 of the Savills report (Completing London's Streets)'><span class='caption-text'>Page 18 of the Savills report (Completing London&rsquo;s Streets)</span></span></p>

<p>The report also uses the Nelson/Portland estate in Walworth as one of 6 case study sites to expound its ideas (Site C). Two other estates identified by the 35% Campaign are the Glyndon estate in Woolwich (Site B) and the Ampthill Square estate in Camden (Site A). The estates are not easily identified in the report, they are not named and have been disguised by flipping and rotating their layout plans.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/completing-londons-streets.png' width='' height='' title='Nelson/Portland estate revealed as Site C on page 99 of the Savills report'><span class='caption-text'>Nelson/Portland estate revealed as Site C on page 99 of the Savills report</span></span></p>

<p>Below Savills explains that their case study estates <em>&ldquo;do not represent any current, existing or proposed scheme&rdquo;</em>, so the residents of Nelson/Portland, Glyndon and Ampthill Square estates can rest easy in their beds&hellip;</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://35percent.org/images/ybarthes.png"></p>

<h2>There is an alternative</h2>

<p>If local communities are to be protected then regeneration has to mean something other than state-sponsored gentrification championed by the property services industry, which makes great profit from it in every which way.</p>

<p>Refurbishment needs to be considered. And if building new council homes <a href="http://www.estatesgazette.com/blogs/london-residential-research/2015/07/costs-southwark-council-528149-build-council-flat/">is costing £383k</a> each, when homes on <em>&lsquo;high investment needs estates&rsquo;</em> can be brought up to Decent Homes Standard for a fraction of this, then there is no reason not to do that.</p>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/dhscosts.png"><img class="center" src="http://35percent.org/images/dhscosts.png"></a></p>

<h2>PS: Housing News from Australia</h2>

<p>Lend Lease has taken all the lessons it has learnt in London back home to Sydney, where it has offered the Heygate’s redevelopment as a model for solving the city’s own housing problems – fortunately not everyone is convinced: <a href="http://www.smh.com.au/nsw/will-poor-be-cleared-aside-for-key-workers-in-revamped-sydney-housing-estates-20160129-gmh7n8.html">http://www.smh.com.au/nsw/will-poor-be-cleared-aside-for-key-workers-in-revamped-sydney-housing-estates-20160129-gmh7n8.html</a></p>

<p><strong>Footnotes:</strong>
<meta name="twitter:card" content="summary" />
<meta name="twitter:title" content="Completing London's Clearances" />
<meta name="twitter:description" content="Savills advises David Cameron and Peter John how to clear London's council estates." />
<meta name="twitter:image" content="http://35percent.org/images/david-cameron_peter-john.jpg" /></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See paragraph 3.2.3 of the Council&rsquo;s <a href="https://consultations.southwark.gov.uk/housing-community-services-department-community-engagement-team/asset-management-consultation/supporting_documents/Asset%20Management%20Strategy.pdf">Housing Asset Management Strategy</a><a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See Paragraph 5.10 (page 22) of the Savills <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s55626/Appendix%204%20Savills%20Evaluation.pdf">Asset Performance Evaluation</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Heygate Sell-off: How Much Are We Getting?]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/12/20/heygate-sell-off-how-much-are-we-getting/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-20T19:54:10+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/12/20/heygate-sell-off-how-much-are-we-getting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Local activist Peter Tatchell went head-to-head with Council leader Peter John on a recent <a href="https://youtu.be/Emvo16iBxFE">BBC Politics show</a>. Tatchell accused the leader of selling off the 25-acre Heygate estate for £50m when the Council had <a href="http://35percent.org/heygate-regeneration-faq/">valued</a> the site previously at £150m.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Emvo16iBxFE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Peter John responded to Tatchell&rsquo;s claim by asserting that the Council will also receive a 50% share of the profits from the estate&rsquo;s redevelopment. However, we know from the leaked <a href="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf">Regeneration Agreement</a> that this is not entirely accurate: the agreement doesn&rsquo;t say that the Council will receive 50% of the profits; it says the Council will receive 50% of any &lsquo;overage&rsquo; profit. This is any surplus profit which might be left over, after developer Lend Lease has pocketed a 20% “Priority Return” profit plus a 2.6% “Management Fee”<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<p>In Feb 2013, Southwark’s Cabinet Member for Regeneration admitted in a <a href="http://heygatewashome.org/img/SNDocumentBlunder7Feb2013.pdf">press article</a> that <em>“currently viability tests suggested there was unlikely to be any profit”</em> from the Heygate deal.</p>

<p>We recently took a closer look at the Regeneration Agreement and found that it required Lend Lease to send a cash flow statement to the Council on a quarterly basis, showing key figures in the development account, including any currently estimated profit overage.</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;The Developer shall provide a copy of the Project Cash Flow to the Council quarterly, together with such calculations relating to the calculation of the Planning Overage and the Profit Overage as the Council may reasonably require.&#8221;</p><footer><strong>Regeneration Agreement</strong> <cite>Paragraph 3.5</cite></footer></blockquote>


<p></p>

<p>On 16th October we made an <a href="https://www.whatdotheyknow.com/request/heygate_regeneration_agreement_a">FOI request</a>, asking the Council how much profit overage it is expecting according to its most recently received quarterly cash flow statement. After two months and four extensions the Council finally responded to our request. It said <em>&ldquo;The council does not currently hold this information. While the Regeneration Agreement does include a clause requiring the developer to provide this on a quarterly basis, the council has taken the view that it will collect this information at the end of each phase of the scheme, as this represents a point in the process when information on costs and receipts will be available to enable a full evaluation of overage available at that stage of the project. The first phase of the project [known as Trafalgar Place] has now reached practical completion. As a consequence the council expects to receive information from the developer which will satisfy this condition in the New Year. Once we have received the information the council will determine the extent to which the material can be made publically available.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>This is poor practice on Southwark&rsquo;s part. If the Regeneration Agreement were adhered to, Southwark would receive 60 audit reports from Lend Lease over the 15 year construction period, but now it looks as if it will be content with just five (one for each phase). Southwark is entirely dependent on Lend Lease&rsquo;s management of the development account for its overage, while Lend Lease is self-financing and completing the scheme using its own in-house construction arm - it controls the whole situation. Southwark should also note that last year City Authorities in Sydney <a href="http://www.smh.com.au/nsw/barangaroo-public-works-in-doubt-after-government-loses-court-battle-with-lend-lease-20140821-106lke.html">lost</a> a <a href="http://www.smh.com.au/nsw/valuation-dispute-poses-threat-to-1b-return-from-barangaroo-20121206-2ay9e.html">court battle</a> with Lend Lease over the calculation of profit overage in a similar-size public/private regeneration scheme.</p>

<p>The audit requirements set out in the Regeneration Agreement allow ongoing monitoring of Lend Lease&rsquo;s development account on a quarterly basis, precisely so that such outcomes can be avoided. Council leader Peter John should enforce the terms of the agreement and publish the audit reports with profit overage calculations on a quarterly basis, on the Council&rsquo;s website for all to see.</p>

<p><img src="http://35percent.org/images/heygatesale.png"></p>

<h2>Greater Numbers</h2>

<p>Southwark should also stop fudging about the affordable housing figures for the site. During the BBC debate, the Council leader claimed that social rented housing would be provided <em>&ldquo;in greater numbers than Peter Thatchell described&rdquo;</em>, but without saying what number.</p>

<p>Lend Lease&rsquo;s <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!cvj%2buF2v8VRqQhUGaBSuKw%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">Affordable Housing Statement</a> for the redevelopment is clear. It shows that of the 2,469 new homes on the main Heygate site, just 74 will be social rented:</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!cvj%2buF2v8VRqQhUGaBSuKw%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/UpdatedAHStatement.png"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!4nJ1uGIIlYSyiAOv1lBXfA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/phaseones106.png' width='300' height='300' title='Phase 1 tenure mix'><span class='caption-text'>Phase 1 tenure mix</span></span></a>Combined with the 8 social rented homes provided as part of its <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200183/elephant_and_castle/1124/heygate_estate/2">separate phase one</a> application - <a href="http://trafalgarplace.com">Trafalgar Place</a> (235 units), that&rsquo;s 2,704 new homes on the redeveloped Heygate estate of which 82 will be social rented. A further 198 will be &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; and 316 will be shared ownership homes.</p>

<p>We would be glad to hear that the Council leader has since secured additional social rented housing, but fear that this is once again just an attempt to pass off the 198 &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; homes in the development as social rented.</p>

<h2>Epic Regeneration - the spirit of Southwark</h2>

<p>Meanwhile, Southwark&rsquo;s regeneration drive gathers pace. Its regeneration department has launched an energetic recruitment drive branded the Spirit of Southwark, and is <em>‘looking for leaders who relish the challenge’</em> of <em>‘transforming areas from Elephant and Castle to Canada Water to Peckham’</em>.<br/>
<a href="http://www.southwarkregeneration.co.uk">http://www.southwarkregeneration.co.uk</a> -
<a href="http://www.spiritofsouthwark.co.uk">http://www.spiritofsouthwark.co.uk</a></p>

<p>Last month it also organised a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/file/12902/welcome_to_southwark_regeneration">&lsquo;bidders day&rsquo;</a>, inviting developers to bid on the first two &lsquo;lots&rsquo; of council-owned sites earmarked for regeneration.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/12902/welcome_to_southwark_regeneration"><img class="center" src="http://35percent.org/images/Welcome_to_Southwark.png"></a></p>

<p>These &lsquo;lots&rsquo; comprising <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s57187/Appendix%201%20SRPP%20Site%20List.pdf">19 sites</a>, include community centres and council homes that will be demolished and redeveloped as part of the Council&rsquo;s <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s57186/Report%20Gateway%201%20-%20SRPP%20Procurement%20Approval.pdf">Regeneration in Partnership Programme (SRPP)</a>. The <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/sh/rx9s4mcl31w6pj9/AACi9ND8ia6XmfATNrwc9Pspa?dl=0">lots</a> should deliver about a thousand new homes, with roughly equal amounts of social rented, intermediate and private sale homes - the private sales supposedly cross-subsidising the &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; housing.</p>

<p>The sites are part of the first phase of Southwark’s pledge to build 11000 council homes and include several that are well described as ‘easy wins’. The recent publication of  Southwark’s draft <a href="https://consultations.southwark.gov.uk/housing-community-services-department-community-engagement-team/asset-management-consultation">&lsquo;Asset Management Strategy&rsquo;</a> for the borough’s council stock, indicates that further gains will be much less easy. In its <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/your-home-is-worth-less-than-nothing-council-report-evaluates-southwark-properties/">appraisal</a>, property consultants Savill’s has identified 4,167 council homes as having a negative Net Present Value (NPV), making them candidates for redevelopment.</p>

<p><img src="http://35percent.org/images/AssetManagementStrategy4.png"></p>

<p><img src="http://35percent.org/images/AssetManagementStrategy7.png"></p>

<h2>Housing &amp; Planning Bill 2015</h2>

<p>Southwark Council has <a href="http://www.southwarklabour.co.uk/latest-news/southwark/news.aspx?p=102359">warned</a> that <em>&ldquo;by forcing councils to sell off vacant properties in “high value” areas, the Government’s new Housing and Planning Bill would have a ‘devastating impact’ on Southwark&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>We have to agree, while also pointing out that Since 2011 the Council has had a <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s19458/Report%20Review%20of%20Void%20Disposal%20Strategy.pdf">blanket policy</a> of selling off all void Council homes valued at £300k or above.</p>

<p>Since 2010 more than 1,500 council homes have been <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/just-65-council-homes-built-in-five-years/">sold or demolished</a>. Southwark can argue that the proceeds of their sales go towards new council homes elsewhere in the borough, whereas the Government’s idea is that in future the money goes to the Treasury; nonetheless the practice leaves the Council exposed and opens an obvious door for the Tory government to walk through.</p>

<p>Below are two of a number of council homes sold by Southwark under its voids policy at a <a href="http://catalogue.auctions.savills.co.uk/london-national/Previous-Auctions/#&amp;&amp;s=1">Savills auction</a> last month.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/savillsauction.jpg' width='' height='' title='Two of a number of Southwark council homes sold by Savills in November'><span class='caption-text'>Two of a number of Southwark council homes sold by Savills in November</span></span></p>

<p>We&rsquo;ll be writing more about the Housing &amp; Planning Bill and its potential impact on Southwark residents in forthcoming blog posts. Watch this space.</p>

<p><meta name="twitter:card" content="summary" />
<meta name="twitter:title" content="Heygate Sell-off: Just what exactly is the deal?" />
<meta name="twitter:description" content="Council leader Peter John explains why he sold the Heygate for one third of its value." />
<meta name="twitter:image" content="http://35percent.org/images/heygatesale.png" /></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See “Developer’s Priority Return” and “Development Management Fee” on pg 83 of the leaked <a href="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf">Regeneration Agreement</a>  <a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CPO Powers to Be Used on Shopping Centre Traders]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/11/04/southwark-resolves-to-use-cpo-powers-for-shopping-centre-retailers/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-04T08:23:20+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/11/04/southwark-resolves-to-use-cpo-powers-for-shopping-centre-retailers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Southwark Council&rsquo;s Cabinet has <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s57189/Report%20Elephant%20and%20castle.pdf">said</a> it will be prepared to use Compulsory Purchase powers to remove retailers from the Elephant &amp; Castle shopping centre, to enable its redevelopment by its owner Delancey.</p>

<p>The Cabinet has also said it plans to conduct an Equalities Impact Assessment (EqiA), which will look at how the redevelopment of the shopping centre will affect various stakeholders including Black and Minority Ethnic (BME) retailers.</p>

<p><a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/london/4532674.stm"><img class="left" src="http://heygatewashome.org/img/bbc_ouseley.png" width="400" height="300"></a>This seems like a good opportunity for the many BME traders whose livelihoods are threatened by the redevelopment to make their voices heard. Back in 2005, Mayor Ken Livingstone <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2005/dec/15/regeneration.communities">called</a> for the Commission for Racial Equality to investigate the Elephant’s regeneration, after shopping centre traders <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/1906">voiced concerns</a> about how they would be accommodated in the redevelopment.  Southwark had already commissioned the Lord Herman Ouseley to <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/ouseley_report.pdf">investigate</a> its borough wide practices and the <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/Data/Council%20Assembly/20050324/Agenda/2%20-%20Independent%20Review%20ofthe%20Council's%20Equality%20and%20Diversity%20Framework%20by%20Lord%20HermanOuseley%20-%20appendix%201.pdf">report</a> of his findings made the following observations;</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;Large scale regeneration tends to favour relatively big businesses over existing small and medium sized businesses. Because of the diverse nature of the borough and because the business interests of poorer and BME communities tend to be locked in to the SME (small, medium enterprises) sector, equality and diversity competence is critical for planners and decision makers.&#8221;(para 41)</p><footer><strong>Independent Review of the Council&#8217;s Equality & Diversity Framework</strong> <cite>Lord Herman Ouseley March 2005</cite></footer></blockquote>


<p>As a result of Lord Ouseley&rsquo;s Inquiry, Southwark pledged <strong> <em>‘to place itself at the forefront of best practice in enterprise development, provision of business support services for SME/BME traders and businesses and planning and regeneration activities, which give priority to local communities at every stage of prospective development proposals and new initiatives’</em> </strong>(para 42); and in 2007 the Council&rsquo;s Executive <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/Data/Overview%20&amp;%20Scrutiny%20Committee/20070709/Agenda/Attachment%202.pdf">signed up</a> to a <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/Data/Overview%20&amp;%20Scrutiny%20Committee/20070709/Agenda/Traders%20proposedcharter.pdf">&lsquo;Traders Charter&rsquo;</a> setting out detailed policies on how traders would be secured tapered rent subsidies based on their existing leases in the redeveloped shopping centre. (paras 2.11 &amp; 2.12)</p>

<p>But the pledge has been forgotten and the charter has since been ignored, with Lord Ouseley later <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/EveningStandard23June2005.pdf">claiming</a> that he feared his Inquiry <strong> <em>&lsquo;may have been used not so much to uncover any wrongs but to help cover them up&rsquo;</em> </strong>; and a <a href="http://tradingplaces-elephant.tumblr.com/">2014 study</a> of shopping centre traders showing just how far Southwark has fallen short of its pledges and ambitions;
<strong> <em>&ldquo;Some traders feel that they are ‘hopeless’ or ‘powerless’, ‘angry’ and ‘frustrated’, but feel that there is little that they can do to influence what happens.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>In 2006 (whilst in opposition) Council leader Peter John <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/2122">claimed</a> that the Council <em>&ldquo;wasn&rsquo;t doing enough&rdquo;</em> to help shopping centre traders, and said that <em>&ldquo;the council should be using its clout to try to secure them some alternative.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Southwark’s Equalities Impact Assessment would seem like a great opportunity to remedy this, but unfortunately it looks like it might end up being used to a less noble end: the EqiA has not been prompted by any great concern for the traders, but by a request from centre owners and developers Delancey, who have asked that <em>‘the council consider exercising its compulsory powers‘</em> to remove leaseholders who have leases which <em>‘cannot be terminated….within the anticipated regeneration timescale’</em> and some freeholders too. (para 51 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s57189/Report%20Elephant%20and%20castle.pdf">Cabinet report</a>)</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.social-life.co/media/cache/7c/d8/7cd88351c83035bea1af1a55ffe6d81a.jpg" width="300" height="200">There is a lot that is questionable about this.  First, traders have been pretty much left in the dark for the last decade about what is going on, a fact no better illustrated than by this turn of events – didn’t Southwark think it would be a good idea to ask them what they thought of Delancey’s CPO request?  Second, Southwark has carried out EqiAs before, on the Heygate estate and the Aylesbury (68% BME), which failed to prevent the mass displacement of these local BME communities; the big danger is the shopping centre EqiA will just be another routine bureaucratic exercise to satisfy CPO procedural requirements. Third, while getting the CPOs isn’t in the bag yet for Delancey (Southwark will have to consider another report before a final decision), they will nonetheless have a much strengthened bargaining position with any hold-out leaseholders/freeholders (none of whom have named).
The <a href="http://35percent.org/images/ShoppingCentre_LandRegistry.pdf">Land Registry</a> shows that whilst most are on short leases, there are a handful of traders in the shopping centre with long leases as well as the superbowl, bingo hall, Charlie Chaplin pub, newsagents and dental practice on New Kent rd. There are also the traders in the railway arches who will need to be removed in order for Delancey to realise its plan to open the arches as access routes.</p>

<p>Delancey’s consultation on the redevelopment of the shopping centre has so far been extremely <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/12/shopping-centre-and-lcc-redevelopment-proposals/">poor</a>. It has not engaged with the shopping centre traders as a community in the way that it should, and has offered very little to the SME&rsquo;s that make for the centre’s diversity. Instead it is relying on its power as landlord to clear the centre through termination of shorthold leases and the Council&rsquo;s CPO powers for those it cannot terminate. As a local planning authority that has required the demoliton of the shopping centre for planning purposes, Southwark has a legal responsibility to the traders and everyone who uses the centre under the 2010 Equalities Act. It must carry put a proper EqiA - not just a tick-box exercise, and must make it clear to Delancey that unless it makes adequate provision for the retailers in its plans, it will not get its CPO.</p>

<h2>Other oustanding pledges</h2>

<p>Meanwhile we are still waiting for Southwark to deliver on its pledge to make viability assessments public. Nearly four months ago, Council leader Peter John <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/my-conscience-is-clear-council-leader-peter-john-comes-out-fighting-as-heygate-deal-scrutinised/">made the pledge</a> in response to <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2015/jun/25/london-developers-viability-planning-affordable-social-housing-regeneration-oliver-wainwright">criticism</a> arising from <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/06/25/heygate-viability-assessment-finally-revealed/">disclosure</a> of the Heygate redevelopment&rsquo;s viability assessment.</p>

<p>Last month, the Council&rsquo;s pledge was <a href="https://youtu.be/dbUYVfdC3Rc">re-iterated</a> by Cabinet member for Regeneration Mark Williams during the following interview with the BBC&rsquo;s Inside Out TV programme.</p>

<iframe width="350" height="197" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/HetrARXcTBE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>But we have still heard nothing about when this policy change will be implemented. Meanwhile developments are still routinely being approved by Southwark without the requisite 35% affordable housing, and our ongoing requests for the viability assessments underpinning them are still being routinely denied.</p>

<h3>Postscript update:</h3>

<p>Cabinet member Mark Williams has responded via twitter confirming that a policy document will go out for consultation by the end of the year, with its planned adoption in Spring 2016. Watch this space!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notting Hill Comes Clean on Rents]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/10/12/notting-hill-comes-clean/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-12T16:02:04+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/10/12/notting-hill-comes-clean</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The rents that Aylesbury tenants will have to pay to stay on their newly developed estate have finally been revealed by Notting Hill Housing Trust – and they are shocking. A one bed flat on the <a href="http://www.aylesburynow.london/regeneration/planning-information/first-development-site">first development site</a> will cost £157 per week inclusive of service charges, compared to a current inclusive council rent of about £105 per week.  A new 2-bed flat will be £166pw, against current council rents on the Aylesbury of £124pw for a 2-bed inclusive of service charges, heating &amp; hot water.</p>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/NHHT_EIR_Response.pdf"><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/nhhtrents.png' width='' height='' title='Notting Hill's table of prospective rents submitted in its GLA grant funding bid'><span class='caption-text'>Notting Hill&rsquo;s table of prospective rents submitted in its GLA grant funding bid</span></span></a></p>

<h2>These are not social rents</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/download/2513/southwark_key_housing_data"><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/averageincome.png' width='' height='' title='Southwark Key Housing Data 2012/13'><span class='caption-text'>Southwark Key Housing Data 2012/13</span></span></a>According to Notting Hill, it will use the Guidance for Rents on Social Housing and the Rent Standard Guidance for calculating Aylesbury rent levels, but it is hard to reconcile that with these forecast rents, which are way beyond the reach of anyone who depends on social housing.  The median average household income of a council tenant in Southwark is £9,100 per year, according to the council’s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/download/2513/southwark_key_housing_data">latest housing data</a>, so any Notting Hill claim that these are social rents is ridiculous.</p>

<h2>Tenants misled again</h2>

<p>The rents information was supplied by Notting Hill Housing in <a href="http://35percent.org/images/NHHT_EIR_Response.pdf">response</a> to <a href="http://35percent.org/images/Letter_KateDavies_NHHT_Aylesbury_Redevelopment.pdf">questions</a> from the 35% Campaign.  It follows a protracted <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/18/aylesbury-planning-application-hearing/">argument</a> as to what exactly ‘target rent’ is (Notting Hill&rsquo;s preferred term for social rented housing). During consultation on the Aylesbury planning applications, Notting Hill <a href="http://www.aylesburynow.london/new-homes/rent">claimed</a> <em>&ldquo;we don&rsquo;t yet have the information to be able to calculate target rents for the new Aylesbury homes&rdquo;</em> and its excuse was repeated in answer to questions at the planning committee in April.  However the figures supplied to us date back to last year when it applied for funding to the Greater London Authority and this has been <a href="http://35percent.org/images/MGLA010905-3356.pdf">confirmed</a> by the GLA.</p>

<p>The figures are also higher than the rents for <a href="http://www.camberwellfields.com/">Edmund Street</a>, Notting Hill&rsquo;s new build scheme that Aylesbury tenants were <a href="http://www.aylesburynow.london/contact/faqs#what-does-target-rent-mean">referred to by Notting Hill</a>, in the absence of the rent figures it claimed it did not have.  A one-bed at Edmund Street is over £30pw cheaper at £123pw inclusive and a 2-bed is £18pw cheaper at £148pw.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.aylesburynow.london/contact/faqs#what-does-target-rent-mean"><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/aylesburyfaq.png' width='' height='' title='Notting Hill's FAQ web page for the Aylesbury redevelopment'><span class='caption-text'>Notting Hill&rsquo;s FAQ web page for the Aylesbury redevelopment</span></span></a></p>

<p>The new Aylesbury rents will apply from 2018, when phase 1 of the First Development Site is completed.  Both the GLA and Notting Hill add caveats to them, claiming that they are just <em>‘prospective’</em>  and <em>‘forecast’</em> rents, and <em>‘are subject to market forces and government policy.&lsquo;</em> but because the figures are the basis for funding the redevelopment, they cannot be reduced without consequences, so we think Notting Hill is unlikely to reduce them by their own volition.</p>

<h2>It gets worse</h2>

<p>The table of rents shows that rents will also rise further as the redevelopment progresses.  Phase 2 one beds will be £162.46, two-beds £172, three beds £181.57.  Phase 3 rents rise to £168.15, £178.02, £187.92 for one, two and three bed flats respectively.</p>

<h2>Another promise broken</h2>

<p>One of the big promises to Aylesbury residents, to justify knocking down their estate, was that 75% of the affordable housing, 1300 homes, would be social rented (<a href="http://pwfpwfpwf.blogspot.co.uk/2015/03/the-aylesbury-estate-utopia-when.html">referred to</a> interchangably by councillors as council rent).  Social rented housing is supposedly guaranteed in the Aylesbury Area Action Plan, the redevelopment’s planning bible. But Southwark and Notting Hill have been systematically undermining the very idea of social rent by introducing all sorts of new names for it, as we have documented – target rent being the worst and most misleading.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1738/southwark_council_keeping_social_rent_affordable_for_londoners"><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/lbs_keepingrentslow.png"></a>But the figures don’t lie and while Southwark keeps council rents in the borough below £100 per week on average (something it is quite properly <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1738/southwark_council_keeping_social_rent_affordable_for_londoners">proud of</a>), it also allows Notting Hill to rack-up Aylesbury rents to levels that make a nonsense of its <a href="http://www.redpepper.org.uk/the-aylesbury-estate-the-latest-front-in-the-battle-against-social-cleansing/">declaration</a> that they would be <em>‘similar to council rents’</em>.  Council rents remain the true benchmark for social rents and while housing association rents have always been a little higher, it&rsquo;s clear to see that rents of £157 per week are well above these levels.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ll be voicing our discontent by supporting the objectors at the <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/02/aylesbury-estate-compulsory-purchase-order-public-inquiry/">Aylesbury CPO Inquiry</a>, which resumes back at <a href="http://www.millwallfc.co.uk/tickets/how0-to-get-here/">the Den</a> tomorrow. The Inquiry kicks off at 10am on Tuesday &amp; Wednesday - come and lend your support to the <a href="http://halag.wordpress.com">Aylesbury leaseholders</a> who are fighting for their homes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Southwark Backs Down Over 'Social' Housing Definitions]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/09/24/southwark-backs-down-over-bermondsey-spa-dispute/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-24T15:55:05+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/09/24/southwark-backs-down-over-bermondsey-spa-dispute</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have been blogging for some time now about developments routinely breaching planning conditions and Southwark&rsquo;s failure to monitor compliance. In March this year we <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing/">stumbled upon</a> a development by <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/">Notting Hill Housing Association</a>, that had delivered <strong>affordable rent</strong> instead of the <strong>social rent</strong> agreed at planning approval.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://www.the-exchange-london.com/web/images/01/aerial-shot.jpg' width='' height='' title='Notting Hill's "The Exchange" development in Bermondsey'><span class='caption-text'>Notting Hill&rsquo;s &ldquo;The Exchange&rdquo; development in Bermondsey</span></span></p>

<p>These homes were part of Notting Hill&rsquo;s Bermondsey Spa regeneration, where 54 council homes had been demolished and replaced with 205 new homes of which 44 were supposed to be social rent. When we discovered that these were being let at <strong>affordable rents</strong> of up to 63% market rent, we set about campaigning for the council to take enforcement action and make Notting Hill convert them back to social rent, which according to Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/download/2914/affordable_rent_in_southwark_2011">latest housing data</a> currently equates to around 25% of market rent. The local newspaper ran a <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/southwark-council-probes-44-missing-social-homes/">story</a> on the tenure switch, in which the council promised that &lsquo;appropriate action&rsquo; would be taken on this blatant breach of planning conditions.</p>

<p>The matter was also <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/16/aylesbury-cpo-inquiry-extra-time/">picked up</a> by the Aylesbury CPO Public Inquiry in May, where it was confirmed that the parties were in dispute about the wording of the section 106 agreement and were both in the process of &lsquo;seeking legal advice&rsquo;. This week there was an <a href="http://35percent.org/images/Councils_update_statement.pdf">update statement</a> provided by the council to the ongoing CPO Public Inquiry, in which it confirmed that it <em>&ldquo;will not be taking any [enforcement] action&rdquo;</em> against Notting Hill for the breach of planning conditions at Bermondsey Spa (para 4.4).</p>

<p>This decision comes as little surprise: Notting Hill is unwilling to convert the homes to social rent because this would breach its funding agreement with the HCA (which was for the delivery of affordable rent); and the council doesn&rsquo;t want to take legal enforcement action; firstly because it allowed an ambiguous definition of social rented housing to be used in the section 106 agreement; and secondly because it doesn&rsquo;t want to draw attention to this widespread ongoing practice, which enables it to trumpet the delivery of social rented housing that is in actual fact <strong>affordable rent</strong>.</p>

<h2>Social housing is not a desirable destination</h2>

<p>Notting Hill has long since turned its back on social rented housing and was not only the first housing association to embrace the <strong>affordable rent</strong> model, but played a significant role in its conception.</p>

<p>Notting Hill&rsquo;s CEO Kate Davies is a <a href="http://www.centreforsocialjustice.org.uk/about-us/csj-fellows/kate-davies">fellow</a> of the <a href="http://www.centreforsocialjustice.org.uk">Centre for Social Justice</a>, the conservative think tank set up and chaired by Iain Duncan Smith, which conceived the idea of both <strong>affordable rent</strong> and right-to-buy for housing association tenants.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://pbs.twimg.com/media/CNUmHQlWIAAdSyI.png' width='' height='' title='Quote from Kate Davies, fellow of the CSJ chaired by Iain Duncan Smith'><span class='caption-text'>Quote from Kate Davies, fellow of the CSJ chaired by Iain Duncan Smith</span></span></p>

<p>Kate Davies co-authored <a href="http://www.centreforsocialjustice.org.uk/UserStorage/pdf/Pdf%20reports/HousingPoverty.pdf">this report</a> by the CSJ, in which she claimed that council estates are <em>‘ghettos of the poorest and neediest people’</em> that are <em>‘subsidised by the taxpayer’</em> and provide <em>‘low cost living for life funded from the public purse&#8217;</em>. She said that tenants <em>‘often pay little or no rent, and get their home maintained in good order for free.’</em> She concluded that <em>‘social housing is not a desirable destination’</em> and that <em>‘private ownership is preferable to state provided solutions’</em>.</p>

<p>When the unpopular social housing reforms were being pushed through parliament by the conservatives in 2011, Notting Hill Housing was one of the few housing providers to write in support of the <strong>affordable rent</strong> proposals. In its official <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/8483/2109183.pdf">consultation response</a> it wrote: <em>&ldquo;Notting Hill strongly welcomes the Government’s social housing reforms. They will lead to a significant increase in the provision of new social housing, with the higher levels of income that associations will receive from affordable rent tenancies.&rdquo;</em></p>

<h2>From social to target to (capped) affordable rent</h2>

<p>So how does Notting Hill&rsquo;s predilection for <strong>affordable rent</strong> fit in with its redevelopment of the Aylesbury estate, which requires social rented housing?</p>

<p>Throughout Notting Hill&rsquo;s public consultation for its Aylesbury estate planning application, it has consistently referred to the replacement social housing not as <strong>social rent</strong> or <strong>affordable rent</strong>, but as <strong>&lsquo;target rent&rsquo;</strong>.</p>

<p>We pointed out during the consultation that whilst there are &lsquo;target rents&rsquo; for both <strong>social rent</strong> and <strong>affordable rent</strong>, the standalone term <strong>&lsquo;target rent&rsquo;</strong> has no planning policy support and that the only terms recognised in planning policy definitions are <strong>social rent</strong> or <strong>affordable rent</strong>. Our concerns were addressed in the council&rsquo;s April 2015 <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!Vbu5QpckfYCnJrulzlWyuQ%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">planning report</a> for the application where it claimed that Notting Hill had <em>&ldquo;clarified that in all cases references to ‘target rent’ are referring to the social rent tenure&rdquo;</em> and that our concerns were unfounded because <strong>social rent</strong> would in any event be firmly secured in the (Section 106) legal agreement.</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!Vbu5QpckfYCnJrulzlWyuQ%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://pbs.twimg.com/media/CCoxHXoWYAAyHtv.png' width='' height='' title='Paragraph 109 of the Aylesbury application officer's report'><span class='caption-text'>Paragraph 109 of the Aylesbury application officer&rsquo;s report</span></span></a></p>

<p>In our <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/09/14/barratt-conquers-southwark/">previous</a> blog post we pointed out our concerns with the wording of the section 106 agreement. We also published the <a href="http://35percent.org/images/AylesburyS106_CllrWilliams.pdf">letter</a> we sent to Councillor Williams, which outlined our concerns and suggested amendments to the ambiguous wording of the agreement. We are yet to receive a reply from Cllr Williams and trust that this is because he is in the process of seeking advice from officers and investigating the matter throroughly.</p>

<p>We learned more about Notting Hill&rsquo;s definiton of social rent and &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; during the <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/02/aylesbury-estate-compulsory-purchase-order-public-inquiry/">CPO Public Inquiry</a> in May. During the cross examination of Notting Hill&rsquo;s Director of Regeneration (Rosemary Houseman), she reluctantly admitted there is indeed a difference between <strong>social rent</strong> and <strong>target rent</strong>, but that it <em>&ldquo;isn&rsquo;t a massive difference&rdquo;</em> (see end of following clip).</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jw7LH2SREZI" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Ms Houseman was also quizzed about the £59m funding Notting Hill had received for the redevelopment from the Mayor&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.london.gov.uk/priorities/housing-land/increasing-housing-supply/mayor-housing-covenant-2015-2018">2015-18 MHC funding programme</a>. She reluctantly conceded that this funding programme is linked to the provision of <em>affordable rent</em> not <em>social rent</em>, but argued that it was the &lsquo;capped&rsquo; not &lsquo;discounted&rsquo; version of affordable rent that would be provided.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.london.gov.uk/sites/default/files/The%20Mayor's%20Housing%20Covenant%202015-18%20Programme%20prospectus.pdf">prospectus</a> for this funding programme explains that funding is only available for shared ownership and affordable rent, which comes in two flavours: &lsquo;discounted&rsquo; affordable rent which is up to 80% market rent; and &lsquo;capped&rsquo; affordable rent which is capped at 50% market rent.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/cappedrent.png' width='' height='' title='Extract from 2015-18 MHC Funding Prospectus'><span class='caption-text'>Extract from 2015-18 MHC Funding Prospectus</span></span></p>

<p>So it seems that Notting Hill&rsquo;s definition of social rent is not the traditional one, i.e. determined by the National Rent Regime Regulatory Framework. It seems Notting Hill&rsquo;s definition of social or &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; equates to the Mayor&rsquo;s &lsquo;capped&rsquo; <strong>affordable rent</strong> product, i.e. up to 50% market rent.</p>

<p>We recently discovered that Notting Hill actually submitted detailed prospective rent levels for each and every one of its new &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; Aylesbury homes, as part of its bid submission for the mayoral funding. We believe that the confusion caused by the ambiguous terms used throughout the planning process, can only be cleared up by knowing what the actual rents will be in cash terms. So we have <a href="http://35percent.org/images/Letter_KateDavies_NHHT_Aylesbury_Redevelopment.pdf">written</a> to Notting Hill requesting details of these and look forward to their response.</p>

<p><meta name="twitter:card" content="summary_large_image">
<meta name="twitter:site" content="@35Percent_EAN">
<meta name="twitter:title" content="Aylesbury redevelopment agreement leaves door open to affordable rent">
<meta name="twitter:description" content="Southwark rolls over to Notting Hill in dispute over 'social' housing definitions">
<meta name="twitter:image" content="http://35percent.org/images/PeterJohn_IDS_KateDavies.jpg"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Barratt Conquers Southwark]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/09/14/barratt-conquers-southwark/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-14T18:01:50+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/09/14/barratt-conquers-southwark</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Barratt Homes, Britains third-largest housebuilder, has just <a href="http://www.cityam.com/223932/building-bonanza-barratt-profits-jump-45-cent">posted</a> a 45% rise in profits to £565.5m during the last financial year.</p>

<p>Barratt&rsquo;s success is due in part to its pipeline of major developments in Southwark, which include <a href="http://www.barratthomes.co.uk/new-homes/greater-london/h469201-maple-quays/"><strong>Maple Quays</strong></a> (668 homes in phase 1 of the <a href="http://35percent.org/canada-water/">Canada Water regeneration</a>); <a href="http://www.barratthomes.co.uk/new-homes/greater-london/track-record---article-pages/the-galleria/"><strong>The Galleria</strong></a> development in Peckham; <a href="http://www.barratthomes.co.uk/new-homes/greater-london/h309201-redwood-park/"><strong>Redwood Park</strong></a> (212 homes on former council land at Surrey Quays) and the 60-acre, 3,500-home Aylesbury estate redevelompent for which Barratt is Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/our-developments/aylesbury-estate-southwark">development partner</a>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='https://betterblackfriars.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/erlang-house.jpg' width='' height='' title='Barratt's Blackfriars Circus development featuring 'The Conquest Apartments''><span class='caption-text'>Barratt&rsquo;s Blackfriars Circus development featuring &lsquo;The Conquest Apartments&rsquo;</span></span></p>

<p>Barratt has also recently started work on its <a href="http://www.barratthomes.co.uk/new-homes/greater-london/H625601-Blackfriars-circus/"><strong>&lsquo;Blackfriars Circus&rsquo;</strong></a> development, comprising 336 new homes in 5 buildings ranging up to 27 storeys in height, overlooking the South Bank University campus near Elephant &amp; Castle. According to <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/8441">SE1 website</a> the tallest of these will be known as <strong>&lsquo;The Conquest Apartments&rsquo;</strong>. This is an appropriate name for a development that was able to dupe Southwark council into waiving the tenure requirements of its 35% affordable housing Policy. These would have secured a minimum 70 social rented homes in the development, but Barratt submitted a viability assessment claiming it would only be viable to provide 8 social rented homes and 48 affordable rent homes. The <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!5wmNTTJlhAE1P%2fSH390aXg%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">officer&rsquo;s report</a> explains that the council had the viability assessment appraised by the &lsquo;Borough Valuer&rsquo; and that <strong> <em>&ldquo;Whilst a number of inputs into the valuation have been agreed (including commercial values, ground rents, and professional fees) an agreement has not been reached on two fundamental matters: methodology of calculating the benchmark value of the site; and residential sale values. As such, the applicant and the Borough Valuer have not reached an agreed position about how much affordable housing can be delivered on site.&rdquo;</em> </strong> (para. 109)</p>

<p>Nevertheless the planning application was waved through and demolition works started on the site earlier this year. However, it is now being <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/8441">reported</a> that the council is planning to buy these 8 social and 48 affordable rented homes from Barratt, in order to turn them into social rented council homes at a cost of £10m.</p>

<p>The absurdity of buying homes from developers to convert to social rent when they should have been social rent anyway, is plain for all to see.
However, it also appears that Southwark is paying well over the market price: the £10m price tag for 56 affordable housing units seems an awful lot compared to the <a href="http://35percent.org/images/LR_LANDQ_TrafalgarPlace.pdf">£3.1m paid</a> by L&amp;Q for 54 affordable homes it brought from Heygate developer Lend Lease at <a href="http://trafalgarplace.com">Trafalgar Place</a>.</p>

<h2>Maple Quays</h2>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://pbs.twimg.com/media/CKr8DTiWUAAJn7n.jpg' width='300' height='200' title=''><span class='caption-text'></span></span>In 2013, Barratt completed its <a href="http://www.barratthomes.co.uk/new-homes/greater-london/h469201-maple-quays/"><strong>Maple Quays</strong></a> development at Canada Water. This first phase of the <a href="http://35percent.org/canada-water/">Canada Water regeneration</a> comprised 9 buildings ranging up to 26 storeys, providing 668 residential units of which 123 were supposed to be social rent - according to the council&rsquo;s <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!vAhB%2bWXWLqfrJmcf89aX8A%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">planning report</a> for the planning application
:</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!vAhB%2bWXWLqfrJmcf89aX8A%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/CanadaWaterSiteA_OR.png' width='' height='' title='Officer report for Site A planning permission (ref:09/AP/1870)'><span class='caption-text'>Officer report for Site A planning permission (ref:09/AP/1870)</span></span></a></p>

<p>However, when the <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!x3RgHHSbSY10notKcDq0rQ%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">section 106 legal agreement</a> was drawn up, there was no mention of social rented housing - only <strong>&lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo;</strong> (i.e. 80% market rent):</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!x3RgHHSbSY10notKcDq0rQ%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/CanadaWaterS106.png' width='' height='' title='S106 Legal agreement for Site A'><span class='caption-text'>S106 Legal agreement for Site A</span></span></a></p>

<h2>Chambers Wharf</h2>

<p>It is starting to look this these tenure switches have become routine practice for new developments in Southwark. The arrangement suits both developers and the council, who can <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/100-affordable-homes-open-on-brownfield-site/">claim the credit</a> for delivering new social rented housing, which is in actual fact affordable rent.<br/>
We recently discovered such a tenure switch at <strong>Chambers Wharf</strong>, Berkeley Homes&#8217; latest development on Southwark&rsquo;s riverside. In May this year, Councillor Williams <a href="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/press-releases/2015/southwark-development-sets-new-standard-for-affordable-housing-in-london">proclaimed</a> the completion of <strong> <em>&ldquo;106 social rented apartments and 14 social rented family homes,&rdquo;</em> </strong> which he claimed was proof that the council is <strong> <em>&ldquo;tackling the housing crisis head on and are doing all we can to build the quality affordable homes our residents so desperately need&rdquo;</em> </strong>.<br/>
But what Councillor Williams&#8217; press statement didn&rsquo;t say was that the 89 of the social rented homes had been converted to affordable rents of 65% market rent by <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/ieDecisionDetails.aspx?Id=3617">mutual agreement</a> with the council, following a &lsquo;viability review&rsquo; of the scheme in 2013.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/chamberswharf.jpg' width='' height='' title='Chambers Wharf - before and after'><span class='caption-text'>Chambers Wharf - before and after</span></span></p>

<h2>Will the Aylesbury follow suit?</h2>

<p>Questions are being asked whether the replacement <strong>social rented</strong> housing on London&rsquo;s largest council estate redevelopment scheme will meet the same fate, i.e. end up being delivered as <strong>affordable rent</strong>?</p>

<p>Three weeks ago the council published its <a href="http://35percent.org/images/AylesburyS106.pdf">Section 106 agreement</a> with Notting Hill Housing for the Aylesbury redevelopment, which covers both the <strong>First Development Site</strong> (<strong>FDS</strong> - phase one) and the <strong>Outline Development Site</strong> (the rest of the scheme). We have had a thorough read of the agreement and have got some serious concerns about the wording, which we think could open the door to interpretation as <strong>affordable rent</strong> on the Outline Site.</p>

<p>Our main concern is that the agreement&rsquo;s affordable housing schedule prescribes <strong>&lsquo;social rented&rsquo;</strong> housing for the <strong>First Development Site</strong> (<strong>FDS</strong>), but the wording for the <strong>Outline Site</strong> has omitted the word <strong>&lsquo;rented&rsquo;</strong> and says just <strong>&lsquo;social&rsquo;</strong> housing. Given the fact that there is no definition elsewhere in the agreement for the term ‘Social’, we are worried that any future legal dispute over the interpretation of this term may fall back on the statutory definition, which includes affordable rent under the broad definition of ‘social’ housing in <a href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2008/17/section/68">section 68 of the Housing and Regeneration Act 2008</a>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/aylesburyAHschedule.png' width='' height='' title='Schedule 8 of the S106 Agreement'><span class='caption-text'>Schedule 8 of the S106 Agreement</span></span></p>

<p>Of additional concern is that various references can be found in the agreement in relation to social rented housing on the <strong>FDS</strong>, but there are no specific references to social rented housing in relation to the <strong>Outline Site</strong>:</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/AylesburyS106_pg42.png' width='' height='' title='Schedule 3 of the S106 Agreement'><span class='caption-text'>Schedule 3 of the S106 Agreement</span></span></p>

<p>We have written a <a href="http://35percent.org/images/AylesburyS106_CllrWilliams.pdf">letter</a> to Councillor Williams setting out our concerns in detail and requesting that the S106 agreement be amended.</p>

<p>If the council and Notting Hill are <strong>genuinely</strong> committed to the provision of <strong>social rented</strong> rather than <strong>affordable rented</strong> housing on the Aylesbury, then we see no reason why they wouldn&rsquo;t agree to these amendments.</p>

<p><meta name="twitter:card" content="summary_large_image">
<meta name="twitter:site" content="@35Percent_EAN">
<meta name="twitter:title" content="Aylesbury redevelopment agreement leaves door open to affordable rent">
<meta name="twitter:description" content="The Aylesbury redevelopment section 106 agreement has been worded such that the door has been left open to interpretation as affordable rent rather than social rent.">
<meta name="twitter:image" content="http://35percent.org/images/aylesburyAHschedule.png"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kipling Estate's Literary Connections]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/25/kipling-and-the-quill/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-25T20:15:05+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/25/kipling-and-the-quill</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week the Guardian picked up on our <a href="http://35percent.org/neo-bankside">analysis</a> of the Neo Bankside affordable housing fiasco and ran an <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/architecture-design-blog/2015/jul/21/neo-bankside-how-richard-rogers-new-non-dom-accom-cut-out-the-poor">article</a> highlighting Southwark&rsquo;s growing problem of accepting payments in-lieu of affordable housing.</p>

<p>On Thursday the Guardian ran a <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/davehillblog/2015/jul/23/resident-led-southwark-social-housing-scheme-shows-london-the-way">different story</a> about an in-fill project to provide new council homes on a Southwark council estate, which it said <strong> <em>&ldquo;shows London the way&rdquo;</em> </strong> in solving the housing crisis.</p>

<p>As part of its <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200537/11000_new_council_homes">programme to build 11,000 new council homes</a>, Southwark council is trumpeting the construction of 30 new council homes on the Kipling estate, managed by its TMO <a href="http://www.leathermarketjmb.org.uk/category/new-homes/"><strong>&lsquo;Leathermarket CBS&rsquo;</strong></a>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/kiplingestate.png' width='' height='' title='Proposed site for new council homes on the TMO-managed Kipling estate'><span class='caption-text'>Proposed site for new council homes on the TMO-managed Kipling estate</span></span></p>

<p>But what the Guardian article or press release didn&rsquo;t say, is that the project is being funded by the developer of a new residential tower at London Bridge, who has agreed to fund it in exchange for not having to provide any affordable housing on-site in its development.</p>

<p>Developer <a href="http://investream.com"><strong>&lsquo;Investream&rsquo;</strong></a>- acting under the auspices of a shell company <strong>&lsquo;Bilford Ltd&rsquo;</strong> (<a href="http://35percent.org/images/LR_Bilford.pdf">registered</a> in Jersey) - has submitted a <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk:8190/online-applications/applicationDetails.do?activeTab=summary&amp;keyVal=_STHWR_DCAPR_9558037">planning application</a> for the demolition of <strong>Capital House</strong> (a 10 storey building leased by KCL as part of its <a href="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/innovation/research/support/grants/contact/guys.aspx">Guy&rsquo;s campus</a>) and the construction of <strong>&lsquo;The Quill&rsquo;</strong> - a 21 and 31 storey building connected via walkways and decorated with a quill-shaped spire, which the <a href="http://www.spparcstudio.com/Home.aspx">architect</a> claims  <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!lv%2bf4WD7hw9vUL41nLaBAA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><em>&ldquo;will draw on the literary connections of Southwark.&rdquo;</em></a> (para. 4.132)</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/quill2.png' width='' height='' title='CGI mockup of proposed development 'The Quill' near London Bridge'><span class='caption-text'>CGI mockup of proposed development &lsquo;The Quill&rsquo; near London Bridge</span></span></p>

<p><strong>The Quill</strong> was orginally <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7918">granted</a> planning consent in 2011, but to provide student accommodation which was exempt from affordable housing requirements. This <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk:8190/online-applications/applicationDetails.do?activeTab=summary&amp;keyVal=_STHWR_DCAPR_9558037">new application</a> seeks to convert the accommodation to private residential use, providing 119 new homes. Southwark&rsquo;s 35% policy would normally require at least 41 of these to be provided as affordable housing units on-site, of which 13 would need to be shared ownership and 28 social rented. Instead of meeting these on-site requirements, <strong>Bilford</strong> has applied to fund the construction of around 30 social rented homes off-site on the Kipling estate.</p>

<p>In November 2014 Bilford submitted a detailed <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!a%2fXn%2fIRgCqJtDcLW0mQiuA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">Affordable Housing Statement</a> with its planning application, setting out its funding offer to Leathermarket and has submitted a confidential viability assessment justifying why affordable housing on-site would not be viable.</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!a%2fXn%2fIRgCqJtDcLW0mQiuA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/quillahstatement.png' width='' height='' title='Extract from The Quill planning application's affordable housing statement'><span class='caption-text'>Extract from The Quill planning application&rsquo;s affordable housing statement</span></span></a></p>

<p>Things have apparently now changed since this original agreement between <strong>Bilford</strong> and Leathermarket. <strong>Bilford</strong> will now be making the in-lieu payment to the council&rsquo;s s106 fund instead of directly to Leathermarket. The council will in turn fund the Kipling estate project from its pooled S106 funds. This triangular accounting provides a layer of separation between the two schemes and enables Southwark to trumpet the Kipling project as part of its ambitious programme to build 11,000 new council homes.</p>

<p>New social rented homes are good, but accepting them in-lieu of ones that should be provided on-site in new developments goes directly against the council&rsquo;s policy of creating mixed communities, which it has used so vociferously in justifying the demoliton of its &lsquo;mono-tenure&rsquo; Heygate &amp; Aylesbury estates.</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!vH%2be%2bKK7uZu6GcJ8p3lqbQ%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/carvil_bilford.png' width='300' height='500' title='Kim Humphries acting on behalf of Bilford'><span class='caption-text'>Kim Humphries acting on behalf of Bilford</span></span></a>Representing and <a href="http://carvil-ventures.co.uk/node/68">advising</a> <strong>Bilford</strong> is former deputy council leader, turned development consultant Kim Humphries. Kim founded <a href="http://carvil-ventures.co.uk/about-us"><strong>&lsquo;Carvil Ventures&rsquo;</strong></a> after losing his seat in 2010 and has been helping developers obtain planning permission ever since. Among his <a href="http://carvil-ventures.co.uk/clients-partners">clients</a> are <strong>Delancey</strong>, developers of the <a href="http://carvil-ventures.co.uk/elephant-castle-shopping-centre">Elephant &amp; Castle shopping centre</a> and <a href="http://carvil-ventures.co.uk/node/36">185 Park Street</a>; <strong>Neobrand&rsquo;s</strong> <a href="http://carvil-ventures.co.uk/node/69">87 Newington Causeway development</a> and <strong>British Land&rsquo;s</strong> <a href="http://carvil-ventures.co.uk/node/30">Canada Water</a> scheme.</p>

<p>Kim also prepared Bilford&rsquo;s <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!pMcMh5jSJoLhoPr4hZ2nzw%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">Statement of Community Involvement</a> - a necessary planning document showing that the developer has consulted with the local community. Kim claims to have obtained <strong> <em>&ldquo;extensive feedback&rdquo;</em> </strong> from his public consultation, in which he claims <strong> <em>&ldquo;considerable support was expressed for Bilford&rsquo;s redevelopment plans with 60% supporting the proposals.&rdquo;</em> </strong> But page 15 of the <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!pMcMh5jSJoLhoPr4hZ2nzw%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">Statement</a>, shows that his claim of 60% support is based on a survey of just 15 people..<br/>
</br></p>

<h2>The future of &ldquo;high investment needs estates&rdquo;</h2>

<p>Last week we <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/18/all-is-to-be-revealed/">blogged</a> about the results of Savills&#8217; <strong> <em>&ldquo;Asset Performance Evaluation,&rdquo;</em> </strong> which gave rankings to each of the borough&rsquo;s council estates based on asset value and social achievement indicators. The estates were then labelled as either assets which would continue to receive <strong> <em>&ldquo;regular investment&rdquo;</em> </strong> or _ <strong>&ldquo;high investment needs estates,&rdquo;_ </strong> which would be considered for _ <strong>&ldquo;redevelopment or regeneration&rdquo;_ </strong>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/Richard-Livingstone.jpg' width='300' height='450' title='Cllr Richard Livingstone - Member for Housing'><span class='caption-text'>Cllr Richard Livingstone - Member for Housing</span></span>When Southwark News ran a <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/your-home-is-worth-less-than-nothing-council-report-evaluates-southwark-properties/">story</a> on the Savills evaluation last week, Cllr Richard Livingstone fought back insisting that it had been misunderstood and reassured council tenants that it was <strong> <em>&ldquo;only ever an exercise to see how the council could invest its funds in an informed way, to improve everyone’s living conditions.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>He claimed that it was simply <strong> <em>“an indication of where higher levels of investment are needed in the buildings alone, to make sure they are up to the standards of quality our residents deserve.&ldquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>He goes on to explain that <strong> <em>&ldquo;The report makes it very clear that there is no need for Southwark to consider any further large scale redevelopment schemes like the Heygate or the Aylesbury and that any redevelopment would only be considered as a ‘last resort.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>However, a closer look at Cllr Livingstone&rsquo;s <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s55565/Report%20Future%20Estate%20Regeneration.pdf">report</a> which accompanied the Savills evaluation, paints a very different picture of its purpose and intent:</p>

<p><a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s55565/Report%20Future%20Estate%20Regeneration.pdf"><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/CabinetReport.png' width='350' height='550' title='Cllr Livingstone's report to Cabinet'><span class='caption-text'>Cllr Livingstone&rsquo;s report to Cabinet</span></span></a>The report speaks of <strong> <em>&ldquo;high investment need estates&rdquo;</em> </strong> where there is <strong> <em>&ldquo;a legacy of poorly designed and built housing,&rdquo;</em> </strong> coupled with <strong> <em>&ldquo;opportunities  to  increase  the  amount  of  council  housing  through wider estate regeneration.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>It goes on to highlight <strong> <em>&ldquo;the  need  to  make  difficult  choices&rdquo;</em> </strong> accompanied by <strong> <em>&ldquo;the  prospect  of  leveraging  in  private  sector investment,&rdquo;</em> </strong> but with the reassurance that <strong> <em>&ldquo;the number of new council homes delivered as a result of the schemes will exceed the numbers demolished.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>The report concludes by saying that residents in those estates affected will only be consulted once officers have decided their homes should be demolished: <strong> <em>&ldquo;Prior to proceeding to engagement with residents, a cross-council panel  of relevant officers will have met to establish the feasibility of sites.&rdquo;</em> </strong> (para. 18)</p>

<p>We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/07/23/mystery-objector-1301/">blogged</a> in July last year about a council report which referred to a zone <strong> <em>&ldquo;within which the majority of housing estates identified for Estate renewal are located”</em> </strong> and in <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">December</a> last year about the commissioning of the asset performance evaluation. Two weeks ago the council leader <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s55105/Appendix%202%20-%20Members%20Questions%20with%20supplemental%20questions.pdf">claimed</a> to <strong> <em>&#8220;have identified approximately 500 sites&rdquo;</em> </strong> for its programme to build 11,000 homes (see Q4).</p>

<p>The council should stop beating about the bush with its estate renewal plans. The fate of the Heygate, Aylesbury, Wood Dene and Elmington estates were all sealed when they became labelled as <strong> <em>&ldquo;high investment needs estates.&rdquo;</em> </strong> The council needs to come clean about exactly what plans it has for the earmarked estates and start involving residents in its decision making now.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/06/staying-put-cover.jpg?w=208&h=300' width='' height='' title='The 'Staying Put' Handbook'><span class='caption-text'>The &lsquo;Staying Put&rsquo; Handbook</span></span>Southwark News has published a <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/your-home-is-worth-less-than-nothing-council-report-evaluates-southwark-properties/">list</a> of all the <strong> <em>&ldquo;high investment need estates&rdquo;</em> </strong> earmarked by the Savills evaluation. Residents on these estates would do well to start reading the <a href="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/06/staying-put-web-version-low.pdf"><strong>&lsquo;Staying Put Handbook&rsquo;</strong></a> - a guide for communities facing demolition and displacement.<br/>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Councillor John Promises to Reveal All]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/18/all-is-to-be-revealed/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-18T11:19:19+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/18/all-is-to-be-revealed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/pjflasher.jpg" width="200" height="400">Viability assessments, the secret documents that developers use to reduce the amount of affordable housing they build, will now have to be made public, according to <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/my-conscience-is-clear-council-leader-peter-john-comes-out-fighting-as-heygate-deal-scrutinised/">this interview</a> that council leader Peter John gave in the Southwark News last week.</p>

<p>Councillor John also said that we could be getting more affordable housing on Lend Lease&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.elephantpark.co.uk/"><strong>Elephant Park</strong></a> development (formerly the Heygate estate).</p>

<p>On viability assessments Cllr John is swimming with the tide. Islington council has just revealed its detailed and well thought-out <a href="http://www.islington.gov.uk/services/planning/planningpol/pol_supplement/Pages/Development-Viability-Discussion-Paper-and-Questionnaire.aspx">proposal</a> for making viability assessments transparent and ensuring developers deliver the maximum amount of affordable housing. At a <a href="https://www.thebureauinvestigates.com/2015/07/07/bureau-to-hold-debate-on-affordable-housing-and-viability-assessments-at-the-commons/">House of Commons meeting</a> last Tuesday, Islington called upon all London boroughs to join them in a pan-London response to the scandal of lost affordable housing. Greenwich council has also said that all viability assessments it receives will be made fully public and Hackney council is looking at much stronger transparency measures. Most surprising of all, Mayor Boris Johnson conceded at a <a href="http://35percent.org/images/GLA_Transcript_ViabilityMQ150715.pdf">Planning Committee meeting</a> on thursday, that viability assessments are part of a <em>&lsquo;dark art&rsquo;</em> and that something needs to be done because <em>&lsquo;developers are getting away with it&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Southwark should take the <a href="http://www.islington.gov.uk/services/planning/planningpol/pol_supplement/Pages/Development-Viability-Discussion-Paper-and-Questionnaire.aspx">Islington Supplementary Planning Document</a> as its benchmark and produce a draft right now for consultation alongside the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/856/planning_policy/3315/the_new_southwark_plan">new Southwark Plan</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/my-conscience-is-clear-council-leader-peter-john-comes-out-fighting-as-heygate-deal-scrutinised/"><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/pjsn.jpg" width="400" height="300"></a>During the interview, Cllr John also defended Southwark council&rsquo;s notorious deal with Lend Lease that slashed <a href="http://35percent.org/affordable-housing/">affordable housing on the new Heygate</a>, reducing the number of social rented units to just 74. He said that we could still get more than was agreed in future detailed planning applications. If this is a sincere promise, the very first thing we need is a new viability assessment. The one just revealed has been shown to favour Lend Lease&rsquo;s profits above all else and was heavily criticised by the District Valuer, whose recommendations Southwark ignored. It is a document which has no credibility and must not be allowed to govern the delivery of affordable housing on Elephant Park over the next ten years.</p>

<h2>Stop Press: We are all on the List</h2>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/page_17.jpg"><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/harrietharman_peniselevator.jpg' width='300' height='500' title='Article in Southwark News - 16th July'><span class='caption-text'>Article in Southwark News - 16th July</span></span></a>Southwark council is due to discuss progress on its plans to build 11,000 council homes on <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/ieListDocuments.aspx?CId=302&amp;MId=5138&amp;Ver=4">Tuesday evening</a> and will be considering a <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s55626/Appendix%204%20Savills%20Evaluation.pdf">report</a> by global property consultant <strong>Savills</strong>. This measures the performance of all Southwark&rsquo;s 406 council estates or <em>&lsquo;asset groups&rsquo;</em> as Savills calls them. Savills does not use Peter John&rsquo;s <a href="http://35percent.org/images/page_17.jpg">&lsquo;penile drugs injection&rsquo;</a> test as a measure of a community&rsquo;s success, but its pseudo-scientific approach is not much better. It lumps together stock condition and maintenance costs with socio-economic measurements such as income levels and educational attainment, to give each council estate a rating.</p>

<p>These two sets of measurements are described as Net Present Value (NPV - crudely: the cost of upkeep against rental income) and <em>&lsquo;Sustainability&rsquo;</em>, which it defines as the <em>&lsquo;social and economic performance of the neighbourhood&rsquo;</em>. The social and economic indicators include, amongst other things how poor people are, how healthy they are, how many are jobless, how many claim benefits and how much crime and anti-social behaviour there is. Sustainability is measured entirely in socio-economic terms; it includes no environmental factors.</p>

<p>All estates then fall into one of four categories: those with <strong>&lsquo;strong NPV&rsquo;</strong> (Net Present Value) and <strong>&lsquo;strong sustainabilty&rsquo;</strong>; those with <strong>&lsquo;weak NPV&rsquo;</strong> and <strong>&lsquo;strong sustainability&rsquo;</strong>; those with <strong>&lsquo;strong NPV&rsquo;</strong> and <strong>&lsquo;weak sustainabilty&rsquo;</strong>; and those with <strong>&lsquo;weak NPV&rsquo;</strong> and <strong>&lsquo;weak sustainability&rsquo;</strong>. A future course of action is prescribed for each:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Rating </th>
<th> Course of Action  </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Above Average NPV &amp; Above Average Sustainability </td>
<td>    Regular Investment </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Below Average NPV &amp; Above Average Sustainability </td>
<td>    Small scale redevelopment or regeneration </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Above Average NPV &amp; Below Average Sustainability </td>
<td>    Asset investment/community initiatives </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Below Average NPV &amp; Below Average Sustainability </td>
<td>    &ldquo;Widest range of options&rdquo; </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p></br>
Those estates that are <strong>above average NPV</strong> and <strong>above average sustainability</strong> can expect <em>&lsquo;regular investment&rsquo;</em>. Those that have <strong>below average NPV</strong> and <strong>strong social sustainability</strong> are prescribed <em>&lsquo;small scale redevelopment/regeneration&rsquo;</em> measures. Those which have <strong>above average NPV</strong> but <strong>weak social sustainability</strong> will require <em>&lsquo;community initiatives alongside asset investment&rsquo;</em>. Finally those which show both <strong>below average NPV</strong> and <strong>weak social sustainability</strong> will be dealt with on the <em>&lsquo;widest range of options possible&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/southwark_estates.png' width='' height='' title='Map showing location of Southwark council estates'><span class='caption-text'>Map showing location of Southwark council estates</span></span>
</br>
</br>
Nobody can argue with investment in council estates and social housing, but the examples of Heygate and Aylesbury give us good reason to worry and Savills&#8217; involvement is not reassuring. They were authors of a <a href="http://www.savills.co.uk/_news/article/72418/175241-0/04/2014/savills-research--london-regeneration-research-proposal">report</a> last year that led to <a href="http://www.standard.co.uk/news/politics/eric-pickles-tear-down-estates-to-boost-poor-innercity-homes-9277330.html">headlines</a> like <em>&ldquo;Eric Pickles: Tear down estates to boost poor inner-city homes&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p>We also note that Cllr Peter John is <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/28/manifesto-for-destruction-of-council-estates/">of a mind</a> that the Heygate and Aylesbury regenerations are a success and holds them up as an example for others to follow.</p>

<p>We should not accept the Savills report as any basis for estate renewal in Southwark. The whole report is set up to lead to conclusions that favour redevelopment and the displacement of local communities.  Refurbishment is not mentioned when it should be the benchmark against which the cost and social impact of any redevelopment should be compared. The Cabinet should thank Savills for its report at its meeting on Tuesday, pay them, sack them and send them on their way. It should instead look to the <a href="http://www.engineering.ucl.ac.uk/engineering-exchange/demolition-refurbishment-social-housing/">work</a> of University College London, which has conducted extensive research on the merits of council estate refurbishment versus demolition.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Completing the Masterplan - Shopping Centre Traders to Be Booted Out]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/12/shopping-centre-and-lcc-redevelopment-proposals/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-12T11:46:55+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/12/shopping-centre-and-lcc-redevelopment-proposals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/LCCAerial.jpg"><img src="http://35percent.org/images/LCCAerial.jpg"></a>
Just as the dust settles on the rubble of the Heygate estate, consultation begins on the demise of another large part of the Elephant &amp; Castle&rsquo;s local community.</p>

<p>Shopping centre owner and property developer Delancey, has publicised proposals for a <a href="http://elephantandcastletowncentre.co.uk/">&lsquo;new town centre&rsquo;</a> and its working assumption is that the shopping centre will be demolished and current traders will just up-sticks and &lsquo;move on&rsquo;.</p>

<p>An <a href="http://elephantandcastletowncentre.co.uk/exhibition.htm">exhibition</a> of the proposals, dubbed <strong>&lsquo;Completing the Masterplan&rsquo;</strong> was held last week. It displayed proposals for a mixed-use development of retail, 1000 new homes and a new campus for the London College of Communication. LCC would move from its present campus, allowing that land to be incorporated as part of the redevelopment scheme.</p>

<p>The proposals will obviously entail the demolition of the entire shopping centre including the <a href="http://coronettheatre.co.uk/home/save-the-coronet/">Coronet theatre</a>, but the exhibition does not dwell on this. In our view, demolition is not a foregone conclusion; at the time Delancey bought the shopping centre, refurbishment was the preferred option and it may look a bit tatty but for a lot of people it still has great social value.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.social-life.co/media/cache/7c/d8/7cd88351c83035bea1af1a55ffe6d81a.jpg"></p>

<p>The exhibition also failed to say what will happen to the current shopkeepers and stallholders, who depend on the centre for their living and provide a valuable service to the local community.</p>

<p>Nor did the exhibition say how much affordable housing there will be. The 1000 new homes will be entirely private rented sector, with maximum 3 year tenancies and none will be for sale, but this does not exempt Delancey from the policy requirement to provide 35% affordable housing, half of which must be social rented.<br/>
<a href="http://35percent.org/images/newhomesforlondoners.png"><img src="http://35percent.org/images/newhomesforlondoners.png"></a></p>

<p>We took up the <a href="http://35percent.org/images/delanceyinvite.pdf">invite</a> and went along to the exhibition to speak to Delancey&rsquo;s representatives, who provided answers to some of our questions; yes, there will be affordable housing but how much hasn&rsquo;t yet been decided; and no, there will be no provision for current shopkeepers, their leases are coming to an end and they will have to move on.</p>

<p>Delancey suggested that some traders may be able to pick up space in its <a href="http://35percent.org/tribeca-square">Tribeca Square</a> development next door, where there should be a small number of retail units, some at reduced rents and earmarked for displaced shopping centre retailers (see section below for more details on this).</p>

<p>This is Delancey&rsquo;s second public consultation event for its shopping centre redevelopment and despite being a statutory part of the planning process, there are three big, basic questions that Delancey has not addressed:</p>

<ol>
<li>Where are the current traders going to go?</li>
<li>How much affordable housing will there be?</li>
<li>What justifies the demolition of the shopping centre?</li>
</ol>


<p>Without public discussion of these questions there can be no meaningful consultation. Southwark council should send Delancey back to the drawing board and tell it to come up with some answers - then real consultation can begin.</p>

<h2>Our Council Leader&rsquo;s view..</h2>

<p>Council leader Peter John gave his opinions on the latest regeneration plans on BBC Radio London 94.9FM last week, where he was ably challenged by former Labour Councillor Piers Corbyn on the merits of Delancey&rsquo;s plans. Councillor John said that he had not yet seen the proposals, but thought that raising the issue of affordable housing was <em>&ldquo;premature&rdquo;</em>. He ducked the interviewer&rsquo;s question of what Southwark would do if the planning application does not come with the required 35% affordable housing; the correct answer would have been <em>&lsquo;we will reject the application&rsquo;</em>, instead he rather feebly said that he would <em>&lsquo;ask for an explanation&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/214183721&amp;color=ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false"></iframe>


<p></br></p>

<p>35% affordable housing still only gets us 175 social rented units in this scheme, a fraction of what we <a href="http://35percent.org/affordable-housing">lost on the Heygate</a>, with a further 175 shared ownership. This is the minimum Southwark&rsquo;s policy requires and it must not accept any viability assessment nonsense from Delancey. We don&rsquo;t want to see it pleading poverty once again, as on its neighbouring <a href="http://35percent.org/tribeca-square">Tribeca Square</a> development where there is no affordable housing of any kind.</p>

<h2>Delancey - a morality tale</h2>

<p>A measure of Delancey&rsquo;s sincerity in suggesting new premises for shopping centre traders at Tribeca Square, can be gauged by the following story:</p>

<p>Back in 2008, when Delancey obtained planning approval for its <a href="http://35percent.org/tribeca-square">Tribeca Square</a> site, it signed a <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!kx6tQZNPCJomdoeiotHphA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">legal agreement</a> with Southwark to provide a number of retail units for traders displaced from the shopping centre, some of which would be affordable<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. This was also one of its justifications for not providing any affordable housing<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.</p>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/tribeca_affordablebusinessunits.png"><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/tribeca_affordablebusinessunits.png' width='' height='' title='Schedule 4B of the Tribeca Square S106 legal agreement'><span class='caption-text'>Schedule 4B of the Tribeca Square S106 legal agreement</span></span></a></p>

<p>By July 2013, former owners of the shopping centre <strong>St Modwen</strong> had shelved demolition plans <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/5215">in favour of refurbishment</a>, so Delancey <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?casereference=13/AP/2302&amp;system=DC">went back</a> to the council and had the legal agreement changed to take these units away from the displaced traders and give them to Sainsburys instead. This was Delancey&rsquo;s <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!1764S3MSO%2biBJUp3XuUgYQ%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">explanation</a>: <em>&ldquo;the s106 agreement was signed at a time when it was expected that the E&amp;C shopping centre would be redeveloped, but we understand that this is no longer the case and question the requirement to offer these retail units to tenants of the centre in any event due to the change in circumstance.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>In November 2013 Delancey bought the shopping centre from <strong>St Modwen</strong> and subsequently <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7258">announced</a> its intention to demolish and redevelop the site. It has not returned to Southwark council and said the units are now needed more than ever by the shopping centre&rsquo;s small shopkeepers, can it please change the agreement again?</p>

<p>Delancey have shown themselves to be slippery customers and they are <a href="http://www.thisismoney.co.uk/money/news/article-1583098/Soros-offers-a-helping-hand-to-Ritblat-junior.html">backed</a> up by big money, including one of the world&rsquo;s richest men, George Soros. They are in this to make even more money, and Southwark council must defend local peoples&#8217; interest much better than it has done so far.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/sainsburys.png' width='' height='' title='The supermarket frontage which should have been small retail units reserved for shopping centre traders'><span class='caption-text'>The supermarket frontage which should have been small retail units reserved for shopping centre traders</span></span><br/>
</br>
</br></p>

<p><strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See pg. 22-25 (Schedule 1 provision 5) of the <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!kx6tQZNPCJomdoeiotHphA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">legal agreement</a> entitled &lsquo;Affordable Business Space&rsquo;.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See paragraph 104 of the planning case officer&rsquo;s <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!vh9yc2npGzJ28c%2fJbhd%2fLA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">report.</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crap Journalism, Crap Deal]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/04/crap-journalism/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-04T08:17:23+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/04/crap-journalism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/ViabilityAssessment.png" width="200" height="300">We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/06/25/heygate-viability-assessment-finally-revealed/">blogged</a> last week about the Guardian&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2015/jun/25/london-developers-viability-planning-affordable-social-housing-regeneration-oliver-wainwright">damning article</a>, which revealed how Southwark had rolled over to Lend Lease&rsquo;s demands to reduce affordable housing using highly questionable viability evidence.</p>

<p>Council leader Peter John claimed that the Guardian revelations were <em>&ldquo;wrong&rdquo;</em> and accused it of <em>&ldquo;crap journalism&rdquo;</em>. But after being challenged, neither Councillor John nor any other council member has come forward to set the record straight and say exactly what was inaccurate.</p>

<p>Former Southwark Regeneration chief Councillor Fiona Colley <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/development/council-to-refuse-demands-about-heygate-estate/6528392.article">had her say</a> about the viability assessment a while ago:
</br></p>

<blockquote><p>‘There is nothing I would like more than to publish this document and show the world what a fantastic deal we negotiated for the people of Elephant & Castle. However, we entered into those negotations with Lend Lease on a confidential basis, and I am not willing to break that agreement because a handful of people wrongly think the document contains something sinister.’</p></blockquote>


<p>Now that we can all see <a href="http://35percent.org/collated-viability-assessments/">the document</a>, we all know the deal wasn&rsquo;t fantastic - to paraphrase Peter John, it was crap.</p>

<h2>One Labour head rises above the parapet</h2>

<p>Newly elected Southwark MP Neil Coyle has responded more constructively to the viability revelations. On Monday he asked the Housing Minister Brandon Lewis a <a href="http://www.parliament.uk/business/publications/written-questions-answers-statements/written-question/Commons/2015-06-29/4517/">parliamentary question</a>:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.parliament.uk/business/publications/written-questions-answers-statements/written-question/Commons/2015-06-29/4517/"><img class="center" src="http://35percent.org/images/pq.png"></a></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/NeilCoyle.jpg" width="250" height="200">It&rsquo;s good that Neil&rsquo;s first parliamentary question has taken up this crucial issue and we don&rsquo;t suppose he is surprised by the Housing Minister&rsquo;s non-answer. But we must point out that the viability loophole can be closed by a local authority itself, with a simple change in planning policy. Greenwich council recently announced that it would be <a href="http://www.royalgreenwich.gov.uk/news/article/479/have_your_say_on_landmark_new_council_planning_policy">changing its policy</a> to make all viability assessments public and Islington council has been consulting on similar <a href="http://www.islington.gov.uk/services/planning/planningpol/pol_supplement/Pages/Development-Viability-Discussion-Paper-and-Questionnaire.aspx">policy changes</a>. We hope that Neil&rsquo;s parliamentary question is an indication that Southwark is about to follow Greenwich and Islington&rsquo;s lead; including viability transparency in the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/856/planning_policy/3315/the_new_southwark_plan">draft New Southwark Plan</a> would be a good start.</p>

<p>Neil also made his <a href="http://www.parliamentlive.tv/Event/Index/67063140-a0b0-46b2-abd2-a09b8b3e2cdb">first speech</a> in the House of Commons, during which he <a href="http://www.theyworkforyou.com/debates/?id=2015-07-01a.1521.1&amp;#g1546.0">praised</a> the new park being provided by the Heygate redevelopment. We and many other people in the area want to see this as a truly public park adopted by the council, not the privately owned, <a href="http://35percent.org/sustainable-development/">privately managed model</a> that was approved at planning committee.
</br>
</br></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/facebook.png" width="400" height="350">In a conversation sparked by the Guardian article on Facebook, Neil Coyle also points out that the &lsquo;Heygate saga&rsquo; began under a Lib Dem administration. We feel bound to point out that Neil was <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgListDeclarationsOfInterest.aspx?RPID=0&amp;TAG=0&amp;UID=897&amp;MID=0&amp;AT=&amp;DR=13%2F05%2F2010-24%2F05%2F2011&amp;ACT=Later">Deputy Cabinet member for Estate Regeneration</a> and ward councillor at the Elephant when his administration <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/4712">signed</a> the Heygate deal with Lend Lease.<br/>
</br>
<span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/imageuploads/1280161383_62.49.27.213.jpg' width='300' height='200' title='Council leader Peter John signing deal with Lend Lease (2010)'><span class='caption-text'>Council leader Peter John signing deal with Lend Lease (2010)</span></span><br/>
</br>
The truth is that all major parties have whole-heartedly and uncritically supported the regeneration, so they can share the blame for the Heygate shambles evenly amongst themselves. The task now is to make sure that future developments such as the shopping centre scheme, don&rsquo;t end up the same way.</p>

<p>Over to you Neil..</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Heygate Viability Assessment Finally Revealed]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/06/25/heygate-viability-assessment-finally-revealed/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-25T21:47:03+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/06/25/heygate-viability-assessment-finally-revealed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Tribunalfolderssmall.jpg" width="400" height="300">
After three years of appeals by Southwark Council and its development partner Lend Lease, Adrian Glasspool has finally received the <a href="http://35percent.org/collated-viability-assessments/">viability assessment</a> for the Heygate outline masterplan in response to his <a href="https://www.whatdotheyknow.com/request/viability_assessment_for_plannin?unfold=1">May 2012 FOI/EIR request</a>. Southwark had initially rejected the request and appealed after his subsequent complaint was <a href="http://ico.org.uk/~/media/documents/decisionnotices/2013/fer_0461281.ashx">upheld</a> by the Information Commissioner. A long battle through the Tribunal system then culminated in a 6 day <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/02/11/heygate-tribunal-hearing-extended/">hearing</a> in February last year, followed by a <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/FirstTierDecisionHeygate.pdf">decision notice</a> directing Southwark to release the assessment minus some of its financial modelling figures<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Following a further dispute about exactly which figures could be withheld, the Tribunal resumed and issued a <a href="http://www.informationtribunal.gov.uk/DBFiles/Decision/i1505/London%20Borough%20of%20Southwark%20EA.2013.0162%20%2810.3.15%29%202nd%20Decision.pdf">final decision</a> in March this year. The viability assessment was then received in April and after examination by sympathetic industry experts we can now disclose our findings. The Heygate tribunal case has since triggered decisions to disclose viability information for other large regeneration schemes including <a href="http://ico.org.uk/~/media/documents/decisionnotices/2013/fer_0491596.ashx">Earls Court regeneration</a> and <a href="http://ico.org.uk/~/media/documents/decisionnotices/2014/fer_0524770.pdf">Greenwich Peninsula</a>.</p>

<p>As well as a copy of the disclosed viability assessment, the 35% campaign has also obtained via FOI a (heavily redacted) <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/DVSreport_HeygateOutline.pdf">copy</a> of the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/district-valuer-services-dvs/about">District Valuer Service</a>(DVS) appraisal of the viability assessment, commissioned by Southwark council.</p>

<h2>First impressions</h2>

<h3>This is a profitability assessment- not a viability assessment</h3>

<p>Lend Lease commissioned Savills to produce the viability assessment and the first thing that becomes clear from the disclosed information is that <strong>unviable doesn&rsquo;t mean unprofitable.</strong> Savills tested to see how the development could provide an &lsquo;acceptable&rsquo; level of developer&rsquo;s return for Lend Lease (i.e. profit margin) - and set the level of affordable housing accordingly.</p>

<h3>25% is deemed the acceptable level of profit</h3>

<p>Savills settled on 25% as the acceptable level of profit and the minimum needed to test the viability of the scheme - i.e. the &lsquo;viability benchmark&rsquo;.</p>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/HeygateViabilityAssessment_MainReport.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/viabilitybenchmark.png"></a></p>

<p>But no explanation is given as to why 25% profit was used as the viability benchmark, rather than the 20% Lend Lease had agreed contractually with Southwark in its Partnership Agreement<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> (Southwark is a development partner in this scheme); all that Savills says is this:</p>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/HeygateViabilityAssessment_MainReport.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/savillsdr.png"></a></p>

<p>In his report on the viability assessment, the District Valuer was clearly not impressed with this explanation. <a href="http://35percent.org/images/DVSreport_HeygateOutline.pdf"><em>&ldquo;I do not adopt the profit benchmark that Savills have adopted..&rdquo;</em></a>(page 30, para. 2)</p>

<p>He goes on to say:</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/DVSreport_HeygateOutline.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/DVSacceptablereturn.png"></a></p>

<p>Nonetheless, Southwark ignored his advice and accepted the 25% figure (equivalent to approx £300m<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>) as the viability benchmark in calculating the affordable housing offer. It&rsquo;s important to note that as well as the viability assessment, <em>&ldquo;the Council keeps DVS&rsquo;s report confidential also&rdquo;</em><sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>; it is not shown to planning committee councillors and there is nothing obliging the council&rsquo;s planning officers to implement, or act upon any of the District Valuer&rsquo;s recommendations.</p>

<p>The 25% required profit figure in the viability assessment serves to inflate the projected development costs and allow the consequent reduction of affordable housing. In the event, the number of social rented units was reduced from the 432<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> required by policy <a href="http://35percent.org/affordable-housing">to just 74</a>, and the total number of <a href="http://www.thelondoneconomic.com/2015/03/17/trafalgar-place-a-damning-indictment-of-affordable-housing-in-london/">&lsquo;affordable&rsquo;</a> homes from 35% to 25% (a reduction in itself of £90m worth of affordable housing<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>).</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!cvj%2buF2v8VRqQhUGaBSuKw%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/UpdatedAHStatement.png' width='' height='' title='Lend Lease's final proposed tenure mix for the Heygate masterplan site'><span class='caption-text'>Lend Lease&rsquo;s final proposed tenure mix for the Heygate masterplan site</span></span></a></p>

<p>During the Tribunal hearing, council officers acknowledged that they did not actually see the viability assessment themselves, but depended entirely upon the District Valuer. However, the District Valuer said that the 25% profit margin was too high and well above the 15% average. So with this in mind and, in the knowledge that the Partnership Agreement had stipulated a lower figure (20%), why did Southwark continue to allow the 25% to be used as the viability benchmark?</p>

<h3>Residential sales prices were grossly underestimated</h3>

<p>An important element of the viability assessment is the anticipated sales prices of the new homes. If this is underestimated it reduces the projected profitability of the development and the amount of money available for affordable housing. The viability assessment estimated that Lend Lease&rsquo;s new flats would sell for an average of £600 per sqft<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" rel="footnote">7</a></sup>.</p>

<p>The District Valuer flagged this up and expressed concern that Lend Lease&rsquo;s sales projections were <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Southwark-Simon-Bevan.pdf"><em>&ldquo;too conservative&rdquo;</em></a>(para. 81). He explained that <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/DVSreport_HeygateOutline.pdf"><em>&ldquo;much of the local sales evidence is not comparable to what is proposed&rdquo;</em> and <em>&ldquo;does not give an idea of what may be achieved following redevelopment.&rdquo;</em></a>(page 40)</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/88_LangdaleClose_SE17.JPG' width='400' height='300' title='88 Langdale Close on the Pelier estate'><span class='caption-text'>88 Langdale Close on the Pelier estate</span></span>The local &lsquo;comparable&rsquo; sales evidence provided in <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Appendix12.pdf">appendix 12</a> of the viability assessment, shows just how poor the supporting evidence is. Property number 24 on the comparables list is this 2-bed ex-council flat on the council&rsquo;s Pelier estate straddling the Walworth/Camberwell borders; a long way from the 35-storey, concierge-serviced luxury towers Lend Lease is building up at the Elephant.</p>

<p>A quick trip to Lend Lease&rsquo;s marketing showroom at the Elephant shows that its <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/WestGrovePrices.pdf">price list</a> for <a href="http://www.elephantpark.co.uk/news-and-editorial/news/west-grove-film-premiere">&lsquo;West Grove&rsquo;</a> (the latest phase to go on sale) is advertising flats for sale at an average of £1,012 per sqft - i.e. £400 per sqft more than Lend Lease&rsquo;s viability assessment estimate.</p>

<h3>Why no review mechanism?</h3>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/LLWestGrove.PNG"><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/LLWestGrove.PNG" width="400" height="300"></a>As a result of his concerns about the pessimistic sales projections, the District Valuer recommended that a &lsquo;review mechanism&rsquo; be made a condition of planning consent. He recognised that even a small increase in the sales values given could have a <a href="http://35percent.org/images/DVSreport_HeygateOutline.pdf"><em>&ldquo;significant impact on the profitability and this underlines the need to have a review mechanism.&rdquo;</em></a>(page 39, para. h).</p>

<p>Southwark however, did not think a review mechanism was worth their while; the case officer&rsquo;s <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!hgyBVuEH%2b8BxXry2bGRAtA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">report</a> for the masterplan application said:</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!hgyBVuEH%2b8BxXry2bGRAtA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><em>&ldquo;Given that the development is phased and extends over a prolonged period, it would normally be expected that the viability situation should be reviewed, so that in the event of an economic upturn an increased level of affordable housing could be secured. It should however be noted that the indicative viable level of 9.4%, indicates that a very significant economic upturn would be required in order to bring the viability to a level of affordable housing above the 25% proposed in this application. Hence it is unlikely (in light of the current viability gap) that a review would secure any increase in the quantum of affordable housing that could be supported by the scheme.&rdquo;</em></a>  (paras. 153-154)</p>

<p>Southwark council acknowledges that it did not have the expertise nor the experience to appraise the viability assessment. Southwark&rsquo;s Director of Planning said in <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Southwark-Simon-Bevan.pdf">evidence</a> given at the Tribunal that <em>&ldquo;None of the council&rsquo;s planning officers has the expertise to analyse a viability assessment. The council&rsquo;s planning officers refer all viability assessments, without exception, either to the District Valuer Service, or to the council&rsquo;s internal Property Valuation team.&rdquo;</em>(para 41).</p>

<p>This is why it had to send the viability assessment to the District Valuer Service. It had so little confidence in its own ability to understand the assessment that it did not even open the viability assessment&rsquo;s critical financial model:</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Southwark-Simon-Bevan.pdf"><em>&ldquo;The [financial] model could not be opened as the file was incompatible with the Council&rsquo;s computer systems.&rdquo;</em></a>(para. 73)</p>

<p>Nonetheless, despite being so dependent on the District Valuer, Southwark ignored his criticism of the profit level and ignored his recommendation that there should be a review mechanism. As a result Southwark has lost 358 social rented homes, while Lend Lease stands to make whacking profits.</p>

<h2>&lsquo;Something Sinister&rsquo; or &lsquo;crap journalism&rsquo;?</h2>

<p>Southwark has spent 3 years and a significant amount of taxpayer&rsquo;s money on lawyers, arguing that local people don’t have the right to see documents that their elected councillors had based important planning decisions on.</p>

<p>Southwark&rsquo;s regeneration boss justified the council&rsquo;s position by <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/development/council-to-refuse-demands-about-heygate-estate/6528392.article">claiming</a> that it had <em>&ldquo;There is nothing I would like more than to publish this document and show the world what a fantastic deal we negotiated for the people of Elephant &amp; Castle. However, we entered into negotiations with Lend Lease on a confidential basis, and I am not willing to break that agreement because a handful of people wrongly think the document contains something sinister.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>We have published the <a href="http://35percent.org/collated-viability-assessments/">disclosed viability assessment</a> on our website, and will be further exploring the information it contains in a series of blog posts to follow. In the meantime Southwark has got some serious questions to answer. As a result of the findings in a similar Tribunal case in Greenwich Peninsula, <a href="https://www.thebureauinvestigates.com/2015/05/26/dismay-doesnt-do-it-justice-how-a-secret-system-was-used-to-axe-hundreds-of-affordable-homes-on-britains-most-iconic-construction-site/">media pressure</a> forced Greenwich Council to change its policy and make all viability assessments public by default. Southwark on the other hand has shown no such humility; in response to the <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2015/jun/25/london-developers-viability-planning-affordable-social-housing-regeneration-oliver-wainwright">Guardian&rsquo;s exclusive story</a> on our findings, council leader Peter John claimed that the article was <em>&ldquo;wrong&rdquo;</em> and accused the Guardian of <em>&ldquo;crap journalism&rdquo;</em>. Guardian journalist Olly Wainwright then responded by inviting Councillor John to <em>&ldquo;get in touch if you think there are mistakes&rdquo;</em>, to which he replied <em>&ldquo;Corrected your articles previously - can&rsquo;t do it every time.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/ollywainwright/status/614174166045052928"><img src="http://35percent.org/images/PJ_HeygateViabilityResponse.png"></a></p>

<p>We have been campaigning for several years now around the Elephant &amp; Castle regeneration, much of which has involved trying to initiate some kind of reasoned debate around planning decisions affecting local people. We have made a point of ensuring that our criticisms are grounded in fact and supported by evidence (even when information has not been made readily available). To date these criticisms have been largely ignored by Southwark council. However, this time the claims are relatively serious and supported by detailed information in the disclosed viability assessment that Councillor John has spent 3 years fighting to conceal. Rather than claiming the assertions are simply <em>&ldquo;wrong&rdquo;</em> or <em>&ldquo;crap journalism&rdquo;</em>, we invite Councillor John to make a more dignified response. Beyond correcting what he believes is inaccurate, we invite him to answer two very simple questions:</p>

<ul>
<li>Why did the Council fail to follow the District Valuer&rsquo;s recommendation of imposing a viability review mechanism, linked to the delivery of the phased development over its eleven year construction period?</li>
<li>Why did the Council allow Lend Lease&rsquo;s viability assessment to assume a profit margin benchmark 5% higher than had been agreed contractually? (the 5% representing approximately £50m that could have been spent on affordable housing).</li>
</ul>


<p>The comments section at the bottom of this blog post is enabled and ready to use. Over to you Councillor John?..</p>

<p></br>
<strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>The Tribunal ruled that Lend Lease could withold its financial model in appendix 22 of the viability assessment and commercial information relating to Lend Lease&rsquo;s negotiations with other businesses - see paras 55 &amp; 56 of the <a href="http://heygatewashome.org/img/FirstTierDecisionHeygate.pdf">decision notice</a> respectively.  <a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See page 83 of the leaked <a href="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf">Regeneration Agreement</a>  <a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See column &lsquo;Scheme Profit&rsquo; on lower section of page 36 of the <a href="http://35percent.org/images/DVSreport_HeygateOutline.pdf">District Valuer&rsquo;s report</a>.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>See paragraph 49 of the Director of Planning&rsquo;s <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Southwark-Simon-Bevan.pdf">Tribunal evidence.</a><a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>Southwark&rsquo;s policy requires 35% affordable housing, 50% of which must be social rented (i.e. 17.5% of the total number of new Heygate homes (2,469) = 432).<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>Total number of habitable rooms in the Heygate masterplan application was 9052. The viability assessment justified the 10% reduction in affordable housing - 10% of 9052 is 905 habitable rooms; <a href="http://35percent.org/images/affordablehousingspg.pdf">Southwark&rsquo;s tariff</a> for in-lieu affordable housing payments at the Elephant is £100,000 per habitable room; £100,000 X 905 = £90.5m.  <a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:7">
<p>See paragraph 9.1.1.4 of the <a href="http://35percent.org/images/HeygateViabilityAssessment_MainReport.pdf">main viability assessment report</a> and <a href="http://35percent.org/images/Appendix12.pdf">Appendix 12</a>.<a href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[£63m Public Money to Build 274 Private Homes]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/06/19/housing-minister-visits-new-heygate/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/06/19/housing-minister-visits-new-heygate</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://i11.tinypic.com/49iebk5.jpg' width='300' height='500' title='CGI of London 360 Tower'><span class='caption-text'>CGI of London 360 Tower</span></span> Tory Housing Minister Brandon Lewis has <a href="http://www.egi.co.uk/news/lewis-announces-252m-prs-boost/">announced</a> the third round of successful bidders in the government&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/1000-new-homes-for-private-rent-in-london">Build to Rent fund</a>.</p>

<p>&lsquo;Build to rent&rsquo; or PRS (Private Rented Sector) funding is the Conservative government&rsquo;s answer to the housing crisis, with which it subsidises the building of homes for private rent, but without imposing constraints on how much those rents will be. Last year we <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/07/19/community-infrastructure-levy/">reported</a> that Delancey had let slip that its new PRS homes at the Elephant were expected to fetch on average £375pw for 1-bed and £500pw for a 2-bed.</p>

<p>One of the successful bidders this time round was the Richard Rogers designed, 44-storey <a href="http://35percent.org/london-360-tower">London 360 Tower</a>, which <a href="http://www.london.gov.uk/moderngov/documents/s45702/06%20Programmes%20delegated%20to%20HCA.rtf">received £45m</a> funding for 274 new PRS homes on the site of the former London Park Hotel at Newington Butts. We <a href="http://35percent.org/london-360-tower/">blogged previously</a> about the &lsquo;dreadful irony&rsquo; of this site being bought (under threat of compulsory purchase) by the government&rsquo;s regeneration agency with £18m of public money, specifically for the purpose of building affordable housing. Now we are seeing an additional £45m being poured into this development which won&rsquo;t contain a single affordable or social rented home.</p>

<p>In summary, £63m of public funds is being spent to acquire and develop a 44-storey tower comprising what is openly <a href="http://residential.jll.co.uk/en-gb/property-search/property-details.aspx?t=c&amp;id=JLLATC41432">described</a> by the scheme&rsquo;s promoters as <strong>&ldquo;274 private homes&rdquo;</strong>. That&rsquo;s a cost of £230k per home when the money could clearly be better spent elsewhere; as we have <a href="http://35percent.org/aylesbury-estate/">shown</a>, council homes on the Aylesbury estate could be brought up to Decent Homes Standard for a sum of just £20k per dwelling.</p>

<p>Most housing associations have snubbed the &lsquo;build to rent&rsquo; funding on the grounds that it doesn&rsquo;t create housing affordable for those in need. As usual, Notting Hill Housing saw pound signs and was one of the first to apply. So far it has been <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/build-to-rent-round-1-allocations/build-to-rent-round-1-signed-contracts">allocated</a> £17m in the first round of funding to build 181 PRS homes in London. We don&rsquo;t know how many of these will be on the new Aylesbury, but we do now know that despite its insistence that there would be no &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; homes on the redeveloped estate, the Mayor has now <a href="http://questions.london.gov.uk/QuestionSearch/searchclient/questions/question_282124">confirmed</a> that he has allocated funding for at least 450 new homes on the Aylesbury at - guess what? affordable rent.</p>

<h2>Heygate - a Tory &amp; Labour blueprint</h2>

<p><a href="http://twitter.com/ElephantParkLDN/status/606461178991255552/photo/1"><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/brandonlewis_trafalgarplace.jpg' width='400' height='350' title='Housing Minister tours new Heygate'><span class='caption-text'>Housing Minister tours new Heygate</span></span></a>
We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/28/manifesto-for-destruction-of-council-estates/">blogged in February</a> about Labour Lord Adonis&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/8192">visit to the Elephant &amp; Castle</a> and his <a href="http://www.ippr.org/publications/city-villages-more-homes-better-communities">manifesto</a> for the destruction of the council estates. At the beginning of the month Housing Minister Brandon Lewis <a href="https://twitter.com/ElephantParkLDN/status/606512000261345280">visited phase one of the redeveloped Heygate</a> and made a <a href="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/e764af1c-0f6a-11e5-897e-00144feabdc0.html">similar call</a>, in what appears to be a race to the bottom in UK housing policy.</p>

<p>In his <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/brandon-lewis-speaks-at-the-london-real-estate-forum">speech</a> at the <a href="http://www.lref.co.uk/">London Real Estate Forum</a> on 11th June, Brandon Lewis vowed to <em>&ldquo;regenerate those inner city estates that are dominated by the high-rise blocks of the 1960s and 70s&rdquo;</em> and claimed that <em>&ldquo;completely rebuilding these estates will provide more homes and commercial space using the same amount of land.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>He referred to a report he <a href="http://www.savills.co.uk/_news/article/72418/175241-0/04/2014/savills-research--london-regeneration-research-proposal">commissioned</a> last year from Savills, which claims that <em>&ldquo;rediscovering just half of this former housing capacity would supply London’s expected housing needs for the next 17 years.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/revitalising.png" width="350" height="350">We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/08/southwark-fails-to-deliver/">blogged</a> last year about Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/download/3934/the_new_southwark_plan">draft new planning policy</a>, which praises the Heygate regeneration and proposes to roll out similar schemes across the borough.
We also <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">wrote</a> about the assessment Southwark had <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SNhat.pdf">commissioned</a> from Savills, to establish which of its council estates were no longer &lsquo;viable&rsquo;. Rumour has it that this assessment is now complete but the results have not been published. As soon as this &lsquo;disposals list&rsquo; is made public, we&rsquo;ll be looking to explain to tenants &amp; residents groups affected exactly what regeneration means.<br/>
</br></p>

<h2>Urban Parsley</h2>

<p>Meanwhile council leader Peter John was also being led by Lend Lease on a tour of <a href="http://trafalgarplace.com/">&lsquo;Trafalgar Place&rsquo;</a> (phase one of the redeveloped Heygate nearing completion). Cllr John was particularly excited about the carrots growing in the new &lsquo;community garden&rsquo;, which comes with a ready-grown vegetable patch.<br/>
<a href="https://twitter.com/peterjohn6/status/610408022645587968/photo/1"><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/communitycarrots.jpg' width='' height='' title='Council leader Peter John tweets about carrots on redeveloped Heygate'><span class='caption-text'>Council leader Peter John tweets about carrots on redeveloped Heygate</span></span></a><br/>
It was left to us to point out that the carrots are corporate carrots, not communal carrots, as the &lsquo;community garden&rsquo; is situated in a raised courtyard above the parking lobby with zero public access; and, for the record, just <a href="http://35percent.org/affordable-housing/">8 of the 235 new homes</a> in this first phase of the redeveloped Heygate are going to be social rented homes. There will be a handful &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; homes and a number of shared ownership flats (<a href="http://35percent.org/images/LQPriceList.pdf">if you earn an income of £57k</a>).<br/>
On a site that was <a href="http://35percent.org/heygate-regeneration-faq/">sold at a loss</a> to developers and home to an <a href="http://heygatewashome.org">established community</a> now <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2013/06/08/the-heygate-diaspora/">scattered to the wind</a>, the carrots are a perfect example of what has been <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/architecture-design-blog/2015/apr/16/the-great-garden-swindle-how-developers-are-hiding-behind-shrubbery">termed</a> <strong>&lsquo;urban parsley&rsquo;</strong>: <em>&lsquo;a green garnish used as a decoy to distract from what’s really going on&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<h2>Urban Practitioners</h2>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://action.labour.org.uk/page/-/site/img/people/headshots/helen%20hayes.jpg' width='' height='' title='New Southwark Labour MP Helen Hayes'><span class='caption-text'>New Southwark Labour MP Helen Hayes</span></span>One of our new Southwark MPs Helen Hayes appeared in an <a href="http://www.private-eye.co.uk/hp-sauce">article</a> in Private Eye last week. Helen took over from Tessa Jowell as MP for Dulwich and West Norwood earlier this year, but has been a Southwark councillor since 2010. The Eye took issue with her simultaneous role as boss of an architecture firm, which has not only been writing up council planning policy, but was also <a href="http://m.building.co.uk/lend-lease-wins-%C2%A315bn-regeneration-of-elephant-and-castle/3092038.article">part of the Lend Lease consortium</a> that had won the bid for the Elephant &amp; Castle regeneration and has <a href="http://www.architectsjournal.co.uk/news/allies-and-morrison-wins-go-ahead-for-first-private-homes-on-olympic-park/8656074.article">contracts</a> with Lend Lease elsewhere. Her firm has also been involved in a number of controversial developments in the borough, including the Ministry of Sound (<a href="http://35percent.org/eileen-house">Eileen House</a>) development and the <a href="http://www.alliesandmorrison.com/project/aylesbury-academy/">Aylesbury estate regeneration</a>.</p>

<h2>Urban Campaigners</h2>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='https://i-d-images.vice.com/images/articles/meta/2015/06/19/untitled-article-1434727223.jpg?crop=1xw:0.8450292397660819xh;0xw,0.005847953216374269xh&resize=1200:*&output-format=image/jpeg&output-quality=90' width='' height='' title='Marching for homes - former investment banker and council regeneration boss Fiona Colley - bottom right'><span class='caption-text'>Marching for homes - former investment banker and council regeneration boss Fiona Colley - bottom right</span></span>
Our very own <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=116">Cllr Fiona Colley</a> was spotted campaigning for more affordable homes and against austerity in <a href="https://i-d.vice.com/en_gb/article/why-did-the-daily-mail-paint-this-anti-austerity-campaigner-as-a-violent-extremist">this vice article</a>. After selling off the Heygate and Aylesbury, former investment banker Cllr Colley stepped down from her role as <strong>Cabinet member for Regeneration</strong> last year, to take up her new role as <strong>Cabinet member for Finance, Modernisation and Performance</strong>. We wonder whether she has had a change of heart, or - having snapped up two new-build flats in the Canada Water regeneration<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> - the homes she is marching for are of a different tenure to those her fellow marchers have in mind..</p>

<h2>Aylesbury CPO Public Inquiry</h2>

<p>A date has been set for the Aylesbury CPO Inquiry to resume. The Inquiry will reconvene on Tuesday October 13th back at the Den. It is scheduled to last for two days and will hear further arguments relating to Human Rights, which the council was unable to respond to during the last hearing. This time the objectors have instructed counsel and will be represented at the hearing by a barrister from <a href="http://landmarkchambers.co.uk">Landmark Chambers</a>.</p>

<p></br>
</br>
<strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>On 6th Jan 1999 Fiona Colley purchased flat 8, Yew House, 2 Woodlands Crescent SE16 6YH (Canada Water regeneration) off-plan for £159,000 and then sold it post-construction on 31st July 2003 for £271,000. On Sept 3rd 2003, she purchased flat 8, Rowan House, 3 Woodlands Crescent SE16 6YF (Canada Water regeneration) for £390,000 and then sold it in May 20th 2011 for £610,000. <a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury CPO Inquiry - Extra Time]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/16/aylesbury-cpo-inquiry-extra-time/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-16T13:54:39+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/16/aylesbury-cpo-inquiry-extra-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://www.eastlondonlines.co.uk/ell_wp/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/alanfootballclub.jpg" width="300" height="200">The Aylesury CPO Inquiry resumed back at the Den on Tuesday, but by the end of day the Inspector had decided extra time was needed. She accepted the objectors&#8217; argument that there were still legal questions to be answered, among others about the absence of a successful ballot result in favour of demolition. She also agreed that objectors needed more time to get legal assistance and that it will probably be autumn before the the inquiry resumes.  We understand that the leaseholders have since instructed Landmark Chambers to act on their behalf.</p>

<p>Tuesday&rsquo;s hearing returned to the issue of the Bermondsey Spa regeneration and the switch of tenures from social rent to affordable rent. Objectors had raised questions about this at the first hearing and in their <a href="http://35percent.org/images/Objectors_OpeningSubmissions_andAppendices.pdf">opening submission</a>, but were told that Southwark and Notting Hill Housing needed time to look into the details before answering questions.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/theexchange.jpg' width='' height='' title='Notting Hill's Bermondsey Spa regeneration'><span class='caption-text'>Notting Hill&rsquo;s Bermondsey Spa regeneration</span></span></p>

<p>On being questioned again, this time representatives from the council and Notting Hill both said they could not comment because the matter was in the hands of their respective legal departments.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, Southwark did table two &lsquo;explanatory notes&rsquo; agreed with Notting Hill about the Bermondsey Spa regeneration and four other developments, which did shed some further light on the matter. The <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/CPO_ExplanatoryNote27April2015.pdf">first</a> of these shows that wholesale changes to the tenure mix had been made post approval on all four developments and that while there was an overall increase in affordable housing of 260 units, there was a net loss in <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/ObjectorsReplyToExplantoryNote1.pdf">social rented housing of 15 homes</a>. Also in each case a broadly policy-compliant scheme was changed after planning approval to become wildly non-compliant.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/ExplanatoryNote1.png' width='' height='' title='The Council's first 'explanatory note' tabled on day 4 of the Inquiry'><span class='caption-text'>The Council&rsquo;s first &lsquo;explanatory note&rsquo; tabled on day 4 of the Inquiry</span></span></p>

<p>The <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/CPO_ExplanatoryNote12May2015.pdf">second note</a> was a strictly legal description of how in each case these changes could be justified. It does not address any of the issues about policy compliance, the correct mix of social and intermediate housing, or why the planning committee is left entirely in ignorance of the significant tenure changes being made post approval.</p>

<p>In the second note Southwark also confirmed that the definition of affordable rent used in the legal agreements <em>&ldquo;can be interpreted flexibly enough to allow them to be delivered as social rented units&rdquo;</em>. However, Notting Hill doesn&rsquo;t agree - as the note says: <em>&ldquo;It is not yet clear whether the parties agree on the correct interpretation.&rdquo;</em> Southwark has therefore <em>&ldquo;sought advice from the council&rsquo;s legal department&rdquo;</em> and Notting Hill is also <em>&ldquo;seeking advice in relation to the wording of the agreement&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/ExplanatoryNote2.png' width='' height='' title='The Council's second 'explanatory note' tabled on day 5 of the Inquiry'><span class='caption-text'>The Council&rsquo;s second &lsquo;explanatory note&rsquo; tabled on day 5 of the Inquiry</span></span></p>

<p>The problem for Notting Hill and Southwark Council is that they have been found out. By using the same legal definition for both affordable rent and social rent, they can claim to be delivering social rented housing when in actual fact they are delivering affordable rent. The question now is who is going to shoulder the blame and whether or not the affordable rented units at Bermondsey Spa (and maybe elsewhere?) will be converted to social rent.</p>

<p>If these differences cannot be resolved amicably Southwark has the option of enforcing its own interpretation, in which case Notting Hill could respond via the courts. Notting Hill Housing is Southwark&rsquo;s development partner on the Aylesbury and its largest development partner in the borough. So the Council needs to lay down the law and make sure that Notting Hill delivers the social rented homes that the borough so desperately needs, not some bogus &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; or &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; by the back door.</p>

<p><strong>Postscript Update 22/5/15</strong>
Southwark News has picked up on our tenure switch story and published an <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/southwark-council-probes-44-missing-social-homes/">article</a> with quotes from Cllr Williams, claiming that the council is <em>&ldquo;looking into the rent levels proposed at Bermondsey Spa&rdquo;</em> and that <em>&ldquo;appropriate action&rdquo;</em> will be taken. The article also confirms that Notting Hill has built a total of 1,442 homes in Southwark and that it has another 5,489 in the pipeline.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury CPO Inquiry - Into the Lion's Den]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/02/aylesbury-estate-compulsory-purchase-order-public-inquiry/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-02T09:10:32+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/02/aylesbury-estate-compulsory-purchase-order-public-inquiry</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/CDsUkrnW0AEP5X-.jpg" width="400" height="300">The Public Inquiry into the Aylesbury Compulsory Purchase Order was adjourned on Friday (until 12th May), after four days of sharp argument between Southwark Council and objectors to the order. This is the third CPO Southwark has sought in relation to the Aylesbury regeneration and we can expect many more as it seeks to get rid of leaseholders who do not accept its derisory compensation offers.</p>

<p>The Inquiry was conducted by government Inspector Leslie Coffey and was held in Arry&rsquo;s Bar at Millwall Football ground. The Inquiry had been moved to the Den to be better able to control feared protests from angry estate residents.</p>

<h2>Them and Us</h2>

<p>Southwark Council&rsquo;s large team of officers were led by barrister <a href="http://www.chambersandpartners.com/uk-bar/person/224510/melissa-murphy">Melissa Murphy</a>, whose recent work includes acting for Basildon council in the eviction of the Dale Farm gypsy and traveller site.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.peoplesrepublicofsouthwark.co.uk/images/stories/news/2804201502.jpg" width="410" height="300">Objectors included representatives from the <a href="https://halag.wordpress.com/">Aylesbury Leaseholders Action Group</a>, the 35% Campaign and former local Tory Councillor Toby Eckersley.
Over the first two days council regeneration officers detailed the background and benefits of new development with much reference to the key planning document, the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200211/area_action_plans/1327/aylesbury_area_action_plan">Aylesbury Area Action Plan</a> (AAAP) of 2009, according to which the regeneration will provide a <em>&lsquo;mixed community&rsquo;</em> comprising about 3,500 homes of great design standards with new green spaces.</p>

<h2>Social rent or not social rent?</h2>

<p>Also present was Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s Head of Regeneration, Rosemary Houseman. Ms Houseman was closely questioned by Objectors about the funding arrangements for the scheme. Under cross examination Ms Housman reluctantly admitted that the 1670 &lsquo;target rented&rsquo; Aylesbury homes that Notting Hill had received funding for under the <a href="https://www.london.gov.uk/priorities/housing-land/increasing-housing-supply/mayor-housing-covenant-2015-2018">Mayor&rsquo;s 2015-18 MHC programme</a>, were referred to in the funding allocation as affordable rent - not social rent.</p>

<h2>Non answers</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/manorplace_sr.png" width="300" height="500">Notting Hill Housing and Southwark Council were also cross examined by objectors about the <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing/">Bermondsey Spa S106 fiasco</a>, where Notting Hill had promised social rented housing but delivered affordable rent instead. Objectors raised further concerns about tenure switching at other Notting Hill developments including <a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk">Manor Place depot</a>, where <a href="http://www.manorplacedepot.co.uk/Manor-Place-Exhibition-Banners.pdf">pre-planning consultation documents</a> described <em>&ldquo;9 Social Rent Family Homes&rdquo;</em>, which subsequently disappeared into <em>&ldquo;Affordable Rent&rdquo;</em> homes when the planning application was submitted.</p>

<p>No clear answers to these questions were forthcoming - council and Notting Hill witnesses repeatedly argued that they didn&rsquo;t have the details of the schemes before them and thus couldn&rsquo;t comment. Eventually an explanatory note was promised and this arrived at 2pm of what was to be the final day of the Inquiry. These points will be taken up when the Inquiry resumes next week and we will be addressing this in our next blog.</p>

<h2>The cost</h2>

<p>Southwark Council did <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Email14April2015_KReed.pdf">confirm</a> that it had spent a staggering £46.8m on the Aylesbury regeneration scheme to date. This comprised total capital account costs of £32.1m (demolition &amp; acquisiton) and revenue account costs amounting to £14.7m (Management &amp; Administration, Master-planning, Communications, PFI, Development Partner Procurement, Feasibility Studies etc).</p>

<p>Southwark Council also <a href="http://35percent.org/images/PMcGreal_Email28April2015.pdf">confirmed</a> that some of its officers valuing leaseholders&#8217; homes were not fully qualified or RICS registered. Leaseholders had <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/ALAG_RICS.pdf">complained to RICS</a> about officers conducting the valuations, but because neither the officers in question or Southwark Council were RICS registered, they were unable to pursue the matter.</p>

<h2>&lsquo;Sham&rsquo; consultations and legal queries</h2>

<p>On the objectors&#8217; side Toby Eckersley called the consultation for the AAAP a &lsquo;sham&rsquo;. He supported his claim by reference to the evidence base supporting the council&rsquo;s decision making process. He took the Inquiry to paragraph 3.1.4 of the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/2938/consultation_report_main_report-appendix_6"><em>&ldquo;Consultation report for the Aylesbury Area Action Plan&rdquo;</em></a>, which shows that Southwark received just 33 written representations in response to its consultation on the question of demolition or refurbishment, of which only 5 supported demolition while 9 supported refurbishment (the estate is home to over 7,500 people).</p>

<p>Toby also raised several interesting legal points around whether Southwark had actually fulfilled all the procedural conditions needed to go ahead with the regeneration. He argued that several provisions of the Housing Act 1985 could be open to the interpretation that a ballot is required for a scheme to demolish an estate, especially when the scheme provides for secure tenants to be moved to a new tenancy on the site with a registered provider (i.e. stock transfer). He referred the Inquiry to the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/8289/1293538.pdf">Statutory Guidance on schedule 3A</a> and also to section 105 of the Act, which expressly mentions demolition as a housing management matter which, in principle, should be consulted on. The council responded that a ballot with <strong>YES</strong> vote wasn&rsquo;t necessary because its deal with Notting Hill wasn&rsquo;t a stock transfer; i.e. they were booting residents out before handing the buildings over to Notting Hill to demolish. The Inspector granted an adjournment that would allow objectors time to consider and reply to Southwark&rsquo;s response.</p>

<h2>Ms Murphy&rsquo;s law</h2>

<p>Objectors had several expert witnesses to support their case; <a href="https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=BJCAM61">Dr Ben Campkin</a> of the UCL Bartlett School of Architecture argued that the unjustified negative image of the estate is the thread which underlies ideas about its demolition and regeneration. He gave a presentation based on his book <a href="https://www.bartlett.ucl.ac.uk/architecture/events/remaking-london-event">&lsquo;Remaking London&rsquo;</a> and was subsequently subjected to a fierce cross-examination by Ms Murphy. She took Dr Campkin to task for not being familiar with the Aylesbury Area Action Plan, one of the many large documents within the Inquiry&rsquo;s four-volume core bundle. Amongst other points she also referred to a previous Inspector&rsquo;s <em>&lsquo;educated judgement&rsquo;</em> that the Aylesbury estate was <em>&ldquo;visually unattractive&rdquo;</em>, which drew laughter from the (largely uneducated) public present .</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Conisbee_Nov2004Figures.png"><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/Conisbee_Nov2004Figures.png" width="400" height="300"></a>Dr <a href="http://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=CACRA07">Kate Crawford</a> from the UCL Faculty for Engineering Science gave evidence <em>&lsquo;as an expert citizen&rsquo;</em> on the pros and cons of demoliton vs refurbishment, for which she had authored a <a href="http://www.engineering.ucl.ac.uk/engineering-exchange/files/2014/10/Report-Refurbishment-Demolition-Social-Housing.pdf">report</a> by the <a href="http://www.engineering.ucl.ac.uk/">UCL Engineering Exchange</a>.</p>

<p>Dr Crawford pointed out that there was no legible version of the cost benefit analysis comparing the benefits of demolition against refurbishment, which had been keenly sought by objectiors. She also pointed out that the issue of embodied energy had not been addressed. Ms Murphy had little time for any of this and again referred her to all the documents that Dr Crawford might not have read.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.peoplesrepublicofsouthwark.co.uk/images/stories/0205201502.jpg" width="400" height="300">Also appearing in support of the objectors were <a href="https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=JREND85">Professor Jane Rendell</a> from UCL Bartlett, who in her <a href="http://35percent.org/images/SummaryProfRendell.pdf">expert witness statement</a> pointed to seven reasons why the CPO was not in the public benefit and <a href="http://www2.le.ac.uk/departments/geography/people/professor-loretta-lees-1">Professor Loretta Lees</a>, an <em>&lsquo;international expert on gentrification and the policies and practices associated with it&rsquo;</em>. Professor Lees presented her research to the Inquiry which included extracts from interviews conducted on the estate and an analysis of the extent to which residents were being displaced from the area. Her displacement maps projected during the presentation, were a sobering reminder of the <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2013/06/08/the-heygate-diaspora/">Heygate diaspora</a> and provided a clear indication as to who this regeneration is (or isn&rsquo;t) benefitting.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/lorettalees_aylesburydisplacement.png"></p>

<h2>The residents speak</h2>

<p>On the fourth day a dose of reality was introduced into proceedings when residents gave personal testimony about the human impact and cost of the regeneration.</p>

<p>Les Kerrigan was a leaseholder and resident of 27 years standing and he spoke up for the refurbishment option. His family and friends were all in the area and he complained of the treatment he had received from Southwark&rsquo;s surveyors (a recurring theme) and their &lsquo;derisory&rsquo; offers of compensation.</p>

<p>Mrs Agnes Kabuto had been leaseholder for 25 years and spoke of Southwark&rsquo;s broken promises, including the promise that residents could return to the rebuilt Aylesbury.  Her grandchild attended the local school and her wheelchair-bound mother was becoming ill with anxiety about what would happen to them.  She could not afford any of the rehousing options Notting Hill had offered her and would have a problem getting a mortgage because of her age. She said she felt like <em>&lsquo;a small fish in a sea of sharks&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Ms Judi Boss complained of the confusion Southwark had caused leaseholders and spoke of the support leaseholders had given each other.  She said <em>&lsquo;I feel like I signed my human rights away when I signed my lease&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<p>A statement was read out on behalf of Mr Mehmet Suzman, aged 80, and his wife, Mrs Suzman, aged 76, because they were only able to attend the first day of the hearing. It said that they had no idea they could be bought-out without comparable compensation. They had had shop on the Walworth Rd and had lived in the area 40 years; their family and friends lived all around them; they asked where were they to go if Southwark took their home away from them? Who would give them a mortgage?</p>

<p>The Inquiry resumes back at the Den on 12th May.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury Applications Approved]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/26/aylesbury-applications-approved/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-26T20:25:05+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/26/aylesbury-applications-approved</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/CDTZqH_WYAAUca2.jpg" width="300" height="200">Southwark council battoned down the hatches at their Tooley Street headquarters last Thursday, in preparation for the controversial Aylesbury planning application committee hearing.
In the event, Aylesbury tenants and leaseholders were bitterly disappointed when the six hour meeting approved the <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">applications</a>.
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://peoplesrepublicofsouthwark.co.uk/images/2304201504.jpg" width="300" height="200">Unsurprisingly there was much emotion and some anger at the packed Committee meeting. Objectors were led by tenants group &lsquo;Aylesbury Tenants &amp; Leaseholders First&rsquo; <a href="http://aylesburytenantsfirst.org.uk/">ATLF</a>, accompanied by a representative from the 35% campaign.</p>

<p>ATLF spoke forcefully against the applications. They objected to the loss of social rented housing, the failure to respect the estate ballot that overwhelmingly voted against stock transfer and redevelopment by a housing association and the pitiful compensation and displacement of leaseholders.</p>

<p>35% campaigners took up the issue of the slippery social rented housing definitions and cited the <a href="http://35percent.org/images/AylesburyPlanningApplications_ref15AP3843-44.pdf">sleight of hand</a> used by Notting Hill Housing in their <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing/">Bermondsey Spa regeneration</a> and <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/18/aylesbury-planning-application-hearing/">Elmington estate regeneration</a>, switching social rent for affordable rent.</p>

<p>When Councillors challenged John Hughes - NHHT&rsquo;s Development Director about why NHHT had switched rent tenures at these schemes he replied: <strong> <em>&ldquo;The rents that we are charging at Grange Walk (Bermondsey Spa) and Edmund Street (Elmington estate) are wholly compliant with the planning permissions we received.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<iframe width="350" height="197" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Xqme8oXrCp0?rel=0" align="center" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>This is technically correct (affordable rent is ultimately what ended up in the planning legal agreements) but avoids the question of why the schemes were submitted and approved by committee as social rent. This question Hughes deferred to officers, suggesting they would be better placed to answer it, but thanks to the tight chairing of the meeting this was never followed up.</p>

<p>The only people who stepped forward to speak in support of the application were the Labour ward councillors for the estate.</p>

<p>While the decision to approve the application means that leaseholders now face the loss of their homes and at least 778 social rented homes are lost, a small victory was achieved: Southwark and Notting Hill agreed during the Committee to a tighter definition of social rented housing in the legal S106 agreement. So while this may provide some safeguard, true social rents are not yet guaranteed.</p>

<p>The 35% Campaign challenged Notting Hill&rsquo;s use of the term &lsquo;target rent&rsquo;. In response Notting Hill Housing <a href="http://35percent.org/images/MasterplanClarificationLetter7April.pdf">said</a> <em>&ldquo;social rent means target rent&rdquo;</em>. To which we can only ask <em>&ldquo;why not say social rent then?&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/votinginfavour.png" width="400" height="300">Notting Hill&rsquo;s funding for the Aylesbury development is <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/InsideHousingBoris.pdf">linked to providing affordable rent</a> not social rent. On the other hand Southwark has pledged that social rent is exactly what local people will get out of the Aylesbury redevelopment. Cooking up this new term <em>&lsquo;target rent&rsquo;</em> squares the circle, but at the expense of higher rents for local people.</p>

<p>The 35% campaign will be giving evidence at this week&rsquo;s Public Inquiry into the Aylesbury redevelopment, where we will be giving witness evidence and seeking a fuller explanation of Notting Hill&rsquo;s slippery definitions. The four-day Inquiry is open to the public and will be held at the <a href="http://www.millwallfc.co.uk/tickets/how0-to-get-here/">Millwall Football Club Conference Centre</a> from Tues 28th to Fri 1st (10am-5pm). For an idea of what will be debated at the Inquiry, <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Objectors_OpeningSubmissions_andAppendices.pdf">this copy</a> of the Objectors&#8217; Opening Submission sets out their arguments very clearly.</p>

<h2>Spineless Southwark</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11135/north-south_southwark_spine_cycle_route"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SouthwarkSpine.png" width="300" height="480"></a>While the 35% campaign learnt a wonderful bit of planning jargon on Thursday evening - &ldquo;bikeability&rdquo; - a great opportunity to strengthen the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1812/southwark_council_launches_new_cycling_strategy">&lsquo;Southwark Spine&rsquo;</a> cycling strategy was lost. This recently announced cycle route from the north to the south of the borough runs directly through the middle of the Aylesbury. The aspiration is that <em>&ldquo;the route will be segregated in areas of heavy traffic or large vehicles&rdquo;</em>. But this is now not going to happen on the Aylesbury, despite the fact that an additional bus route will be added to the three already which run down Thurlow street. Instead we will be getting <em>&ldquo;traffic calming measures&rdquo;</em> because Notting Hill doesn&rsquo;t want to encourage <em>&ldquo;fast commuter cycling&rdquo;</em> through its quiet residential development.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury Redevelopment - Decision Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/18/aylesbury-planning-application-hearing/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/18/aylesbury-planning-application-hearing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Aylesburyoutline2.jpg" width="400" height="300"> The planning applications for the redevelopment of the Aylesbury estate are to be considered by Southwark council&rsquo;s planning commitee on <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/ieListDocuments.aspx?CId=119&amp;MId=4808&amp;Ver=4">Thursday evening</a>. Officers recommend that approval be granted - their report on the outline masterplan application can be found <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!Vbu5QpckfYCnJrulzlWyuQ%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">here</a>.</p>

<p>We blogged <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing/">previously</a> about Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s development at the Bermondsey Spa regeneration, where social rented housing agreed at planning committee became affordable rent when - by sleight of hand - social rent was defined in the legal agreement as affordable rent.</p>

<p>In an email response to an enquiry about its Bermondsey Spa development from a local ward councillor, a Notting Hill spokesperson confirmed <strong> <em>&ldquo;we don&rsquo;t have any social rented properties here&rdquo;</em> </strong> and explained that the 44 &lsquo;social rented&rsquo; units are currently let at affordable rents, ranging from 42% of market rent for 3 beds to 63% of market rent for 1 beds (average across all unit types = 58% of market rents).</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!J5kImYW5llmj0BA4PEvWpw%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/elmingtons106.png" width="430" height="310"></a>We have now discovered that the Bermondsey Spa tenure definition switch was no isolated incident: another Notting Hill Housing redevelopment - the Elmington estate regeneration (now rebranded <a href="http://www.camberwellfields.com/">&lsquo;Camberwell Fields&rsquo;</a>) has a definition of social rented housing in its <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!J5kImYW5llmj0BA4PEvWpw%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">S106 agreement</a> enabling the very same tenure switch.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/camberwell-fields-logo.png" width="300" height="200">&lsquo;Camberwell Fields&rsquo; is not due to be completed until later in the year, so we don&rsquo;t know exactly the percentage of market rent the supposed &lsquo;social rented&rsquo; units will be let at yet.<br/>
</br></p>

<p>Concern about the same thing happening on the Aylesbury has been amplified by Notting Hill&rsquo;s use of the term &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; in its planning application; this has raised great suspicion amongst local people. On the very eve of the planning hearing, Notting Hill were obliged to send <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/MasterplanClarificationLetter7April.pdf">letters</a> to all objectors &lsquo;clarifying&rsquo; amongst other things that the term &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; means social rent. Southwark&rsquo;s planning officers agree with this:<br/>
<img class="center" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/CCoxHXoWYAAyHtv.png"></p>

<p>However, Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s <a href="http://35percent.org/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.pdf">Development Partnership Agreement</a> for the Aylesbury has no such definiton; &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; is defined with a vague reference to a &lsquo;target&rsquo; and &lsquo;formula&rsquo; set by government, without any reference to the term social rent or the National Rent Regime regulatory framework which governs it.<br/>
<a href="http://35percent.org/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Aylesbury_targetrent.png"></a></p>

<p>Past planning committees have had the wool pulled over their eyes by Notting Hill Housing. If the same thing happens again on Thursday then we can add the loss of roughly 1300 social rented units promised by Notting Hill on the Aylesbury, to the 44 units lost at Bermondsey Spa and the 41 units set to be lost on its Elmington estate regeneration.</p>

<p>The Aylesbury applications are due to be heard on Thursday evening. In the meantime, we have written a <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyPlanningApplications_ref15AP3843-44.pdf">letter</a> to Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="https://twitter.com/interpolitan_1">Head of Planning</a> and the following planning committee councillors who will be deciding the application, urging them to reject the application until the precise legal definition of the social housing tenure proposed has been published for public consultation. If they stand for social housing which really is social housing or believe in a fair and transparent planning process then they will support and act upon our request.</p>

<ul>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=899">Nick Dolezal</a> -    Chair (Labour)</li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=50000619">Maisie Anderson</a>  (Labour) <a href="https://twitter.com/MaisieA">@MaisieA</a></li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=50000696">Sarah King</a>  (Labour) <a href="https://twitter.com/sezking78">@sezking78</a></li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=50000664">Hamish McCallum</a> (Lib Dem) <a href="https://twitter.com/hamishmccallum">@hamishmccallum</a></li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=909">Darren Merrill</a> (Labour) <a href="https://twitter.com/MerrillDarren">@MerrillDarren</a></li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=334">Michael Mitchell</a> (Conservative)</li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=50000717">Jamille Mohammed</a> (Labour)</li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=161">Adele Morris</a>  (Lib Dem) <a href="https://twitter.com/AdeleCathedrals">@AdeleCathedrals</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifesto for the Destruction of Council Estates]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/28/manifesto-for-destruction-of-council-estates/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-28T13:22:05+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/28/manifesto-for-destruction-of-council-estates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/adonis.png" width="300" height="200">The prestigious <strong>Institute of Public Policy Research (IPPR)</strong> has published a <a href="http://www.ippr.org/publications/city-villages-more-homes-better-communities">policy paper</a> that proposes the wholesale demolition of London&rsquo;s council estates, in the name of regeneration and to allow for the creation of so-called &lsquo;City Villages&rsquo;.</p>

<p>The paper is the brainchild of New Labour peer <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Adonis,_Baron_Adonis">Lord Adonis</a> and includes a chapter by Southwark council leader Peter John.</p>

<p>Adonis was a Greek god who was the epitomy of masculine beauty; our Lord Adonis is a more mundane character: a Blairite zealot who <a href="http://labourlist.org/2014/09/could-we-see-a-jowelladonis-ticket-for-london-mayor/">fancies himself as London&rsquo;s Deputy Mayor</a>. He has gathered together a group of like-minded cronies including London borough council leaders and <a href="http://www.grosvenorestate.com/">property developers</a> to pen a policy proposal entitled <strong>&ldquo;City Villages: More homes, better communities&rdquo;</strong>.</p>

<p>The idea is simple: London needs lots of new homes; they could all be built on brownfield sites; council estates are on brownfield sites - so let&rsquo;s demolish council estates. The land is worth a lot of money, so friendly property developers can be enlisted to help. Demolishing council estates would also get rid of that awful <strong> <em>&ldquo;mono-tenure&rdquo;</em> </strong>housing that breeds crime and anti-social behaviour.</p>

<p>His Lordship draws on various provocative examples to make his case, including the Heygate estate. Southwark council leader Peter John writes a chapter on this great success story, which our readers will know from <a href="http://35percent.org/affordable-housing/">previous posts</a> destroyed 1200 council homes, replacing them with 79 social rented units, plus 200 unaffordable &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; units, <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2013/06/08/the-heygate-diaspora/">ripping off leaseholders</a> along the way - or, in Councillor John&rsquo;s words creating <strong> <em>&ldquo;a genuine mix of private owned, private rented, shared ownership and social rented homes for people of all incomes.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/pjgrin.png" width="400" height="300">Councillor John further redefines the word success when he praises the Strata Tower&rsquo;s <strong> <em>&ldquo;distinctive three wind turbines&rdquo;</em> </strong>, <a href="http://35percent.org/strata-tower">which</a> do not turn, do not work and do not generate any electricity - a fitting symbol of the Elephant &amp; Castle regeneration after all.</p>

<p>Lord Adonis laments the fact that only a <strong> <em>&ldquo;tiny fraction&rdquo;</em> </strong> of London&rsquo;s estates are currently being redeveloped and cites amongst these the massive <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/davehillblog/2015/mar/26/andrew-adonis-and-estate-regeneration-some-pros-and-cons">Earls Court redevelopment</a>, which will require the <a href="https://westkengibbsgreen.wordpress.com/">demolition of the West Ken &amp; Gibbs estate</a> and of course our very own <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">Aylesbury redevelopment</a>.</p>

<p>Both his Lordship and Councillor John acknowledge that this can all be a bit controversial, in that <strong> <em>&ldquo;redevelopment of estates is sometimes assumed to mean that existing tenants and residents will be displaced by wealthier incomers&rdquo;</em> </strong>, but according to Lord Adonis <strong> <em>&ldquo;this need not, nor should it be the case&rdquo;</em> </strong>, since redevelopment should offer ample opportunity for residents to remain in new homes once completed.</p>

<p>We beg to differ; over the past 10 years estate regenerations have <a href="https://www.london.gov.uk/media/assembly-press-releases/2015/02/8000-social-homes-lost-in-a-decade">lost us 8,000 social rented units</a>, while increasing free-market housing ten-fold and doubling the overall housing density. The lessons that we&rsquo;ve learned are that anyone who stands in the way of a regeneration - whether council tenant or leaseholder - is going to lose their home and will unlikely be able to afford any of the new homes.</p>

<p>We are not the only ones to take issue with Lord Adonis&rsquo;s policy proposals; Duncan Bowie, member of the EC of London Labour Housing Group and former advisor to Ken Livingstone has published a <a href="https://redbrickblog.wordpress.com/2015/03/31/city-villages-the-wrong-solution-to-londons-housing-crisis/">detailed critique</a> of Adonis&rsquo;s proposals, which he describes as <em>&lsquo;grossly out of touch&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<h2>Aylesbury planning application - get your tickets now!</h2>

<p>The date of the planning committee meeting for the Aylesbury redevelopment applications has been set back from the 14th April, possibly to the 21st April. The council has said it is expecting &lsquo;much interest&rsquo; and it&rsquo;s likely that the meeting will be ticketed, which requires anyone wishing to attend to register with the council beforehand. Health and safety concerns are clearly uppermost in Southwark council&rsquo;s mind and will no doubt mean that numbers will also be limited.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/chilterngroup.png" width="400" height="300">However, the date for the Compulsory Purchase Order Public Inquiry is fixed (28th April - 1st May at <a href="https://www.etcvenues.co.uk/venues/prospero-house">Prospero House</a>) and this will not be changed. The <a href="http://halag.wordpress.com">Aylesbury Leaseholders Action Group</a> has published its Statement of Case ahead of the Inquiry. Their objections explain how replacement housing will be unaffordable to existing residents and explore the lack of transparency about the proposed tenure mix. You can read through their Statement of Case on their campaign website <a href="https://halag.wordpress.com/2015/03/27/cpo-public-inquiry-help-required/">here</a>.</p>

<h2>P.S. - IPPR makes a couple of good suggestions</h2>

<p>To return to the IPPR policy paper - it does make one or two constructive suggestions, such as the recommendation that <strong> <em>&ldquo;At a minimum, tenants should be balloted on regeneration schemes&rdquo;</em> </strong>. Cllr John couldn&rsquo;t have read this bit, because of course the Aylesbury residents <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2001/dec/27/1">gave a resounding &lsquo;NO&rsquo;</a> to regeneration when they were balloted in 2001.</p>

<p>Another recommendation <strong> <em>&ldquo;Transparency about the future tenure mix is essential from the outset&rdquo;</em> </strong> is also absent from the Aylesbury redevelopment; as we saw in our last two blog posts, Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s definition of social rented tenure is as clear as mud and it has also been <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2015/mar/29/tenants-face-70m-rent-rise-as-social-housing-converted-to-affordable-homes">reported</a> to be converting its existing social tenancies at an alarming rate.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stand Up for More Social Housing (at 80% Market Rent)]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-18T09:29:17+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/homesforbritain.jpg' width='250' height='500' title='Notting Hill Director Kate Davies'><span class='caption-text'>Notting Hill Director Kate Davies</span></span><strong> <em>&ldquo;Let&rsquo;s all of us stand up for more social housing&rdquo;</em> </strong> was the <a href="https://twitter.com/NottingHillHG/status/577771553842167808">call to arms</a> during the <a href="http://www.24dash.com/news/housing/2015-03-18-The-Homes-for-Britain-bus-relay-reaches-Westminister">&lsquo;impassioned speech&rsquo;</a> from Notting Hill Housing Trust&rsquo;s Director Kate Davies at yesterday&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2015/mar/17/london-housing-rally-protesters-gather-at-homes-for-britain-event">&lsquo;Homes for Britain&rsquo;</a> rally. The rally was part of an ongoing campaign organised by the <a href="http://www.housing.org.uk/">National Housing Federation</a>, of which NHHT is a founding member.</p>

<p>We have blogged previously about NHHT&rsquo;s dodgy definition of social housing and its <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/customers/permanent-rented-housing/information-for-permanent-rented-housing-tenants/affordable-rent-update">blanket policy</a> of converting all its existing social rented properties to <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/housing-network/2014/feb/03/affordable-housing-meaning-rent-social-housing">affordable rent</a> when tenancies expire.</p>

<p>So we have taken a closer look at the kind of &lsquo;social&rsquo; housing Notting Hill&rsquo;s Director wants us all to stand up for more of.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/theexchange.jpg' width='' height='' title=''The Exchange' - Notting Hill's 205 unit development at the Bermondsey Spa regeneration scheme (site 5C)'><span class='caption-text'>&lsquo;The Exchange&rsquo; - Notting Hill&rsquo;s 205 unit development at the Bermondsey Spa regeneration scheme (site 5C)</span></span>
This is <a href="http://www.the-exchange-london.com/">&lsquo;The Exchange&rsquo;</a> in Bermondsey, Notting Hill&rsquo;s latest completed development in Southwark and part of the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200180/bermondsey_spa/1144/bermondsey_spa_masterplan">Bermondsey Spa regeneration scheme</a>.
All but three private and two shared-ownership units in this 205-home development have been sold and of those that remain the private flats are <a href="http://www.the-exchange-london.com/availability?tenure=TH">priced</a> at over £1m and the shared-ownership flats <a href="http://www.the-exchange-london.com/availability/so">require</a> a minimum salary of £73,986 to qualify.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/BermondseySpaDemolition.jpg' width='350' height='300' title='Demolition of 54 council homes on the site'><span class='caption-text'>Demolition of 54 council homes on the site</span></span>The development should also have had 44 social rented units, to replace the 54 council homes demolished to make way for <strong>&lsquo;The Exchange&rsquo;</strong>.</p>

<p>44 social rented units were duly proposed in Notting Hill&rsquo;s <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?casereference=10/AP/3010&amp;system=DC">planning application</a> for the site and that&rsquo;s what was confirmed in the <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7B%7B%7B!7lhb2IoB57lo6iUf2g/V0A==!%7D%7D%7D">planning officer&rsquo;s report</a>. Paragraphs 27 &amp; 29 of the GLA <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/GLABermondseySpaReport.pdf">planning report</a> also confirmed that the development proposed 44 social rented homes. However, after approval was given Southwark Council and Notting Hill signed-off the <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7B%7B%7B!v0IQJeAkBHGLkpIJJYfrTA==!%7D%7D%7D">s106 legal agreement</a> with something completely different - 44 &lsquo;affordable rented&rsquo; units (ie. up to 80% market rents) <strong>not</strong> 44 social rented units.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/BermondseySpaS106.png' width='' height='' title='Officers report states 44 Social Rented homes but S106 Agreement says Affordable Rented units'><span class='caption-text'>Officers report states 44 Social Rented homes but S106 Agreement says Affordable Rented units</span></span></p>

<p>The change in wording is subtle but the consequences aren&rsquo;t; according to <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">Southwark&rsquo;s own figures</a>, a 1-bed social rented flat in Bermondsey(SE16) costs an average £97 per week, compared to £273 per week for &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; at 80% market rent.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s hard not to conclude that the public has been deceived over this development: it was led to believe that it was getting social rents at all stages up to planning approval, then a switch was effected when the legal documents were drawn up after approval was granted.</p>

<p>We showed in our last blog how this sleight-of-hand is becoming commonplace in Southwark&rsquo;s planning process.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.png' width='400' height='200' title='Extract from Aylesbury estate Development Agreement'><span class='caption-text'>Extract from Aylesbury estate Development Agreement</span></span>We have also shown in <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">previous blog posts</a> how Notting Hill is using the terms &lsquo;social&rsquo;, &lsquo;target&rsquo; and &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; rent interchangably in its forthcoming application for the Aylesbury estate redevelopment and <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/10/affordable-rent-is-not-social/">blogged</a> about the worrying fact that affordable rents of up to 80% are included in the Notting Hill development agreement for the Aylesbury.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburySelection.jpg' width='' height='' title='Notting Hill's Director & Southwark council leader celebrate demolition of Aylesbury redevelopment's phase 2'><span class='caption-text'>Notting Hill&rsquo;s Director &amp; Southwark council leader celebrate demolition of Aylesbury redevelopment&rsquo;s phase 2</span></span>
So, we have to ask the question - will the Aylesbury go the same way as the Bermondsey Spa regeneration with affordable rent slipped in quietly through the back door?</p>

<p>One way of finding out would be to for details of Notting Hill&rsquo;s funding allocation for the Aylesbury redevelopment. It has currently secured a total of £92m in funding from the Mayor&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.london.gov.uk/priorities/housing-land/increasing-housing-supply/affordable-homes-programme">Affordable Homes Programme</a> and is by far the largest single recipient of funding from it. London Assembly member Darren Johnson recently tabled a formal <a href="http://questions.london.gov.uk/QuestionSearch/searchclient/questions/question_281359">question</a> to the Mayor about the tenure mix linked to Notting Hill&rsquo;s £92m allocation. We will be watching out for the Mayor&rsquo;s response.</p>

<p>We need to let the council know that the game is up and that we are not going to accept this disingenuous racket. The Aylesbury planning application is due to be heard by committee on 14th April and we will be making our voices heard. We invite you to support us by objecting to the planning application online using our <a href="http://commentform.herokuapp.com">automated objection form</a>.</p>

<h2>Postscript update (3rd April 2015)</h2>

<p>The people at <a href="http://southwarknotes.wordpress.com">Southwark Notes</a> couldn&rsquo;t quite believe that Notting Hill had passed off affordable rent as social rent at its Bermondsey Spa site, so they attempted to seek confirmation via twitter:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/NottingHillHG">@NottingHillHG</a> Hiya NHHT. Is it true that 44 units of social housing at your Exchange site will be &#39;affordable rent&#39;? <a href="http://t.co/gUvnsYQjZX">http://t.co/gUvnsYQjZX</a></p>&mdash; Southwark Notes (@SouthwarkNotes) <a href="https://twitter.com/SouthwarkNotes/status/578173781019111424">March 18, 2015</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>Notting Hill unashamedly confirmed that Bermondsey Spa&rsquo;s 44 &lsquo;social rented&rsquo; units were indeed let at affordable rather than social rents, but that these generally averaged just 58% of market rent:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-cards="hidden" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/SouthwarkNotes">@SouthwarkNotes</a> Yes, affordable rent (average 58% of market rent) due to Gov changes to rent setting in 2011. See <a href="http://t.co/2tThW5DZGZ">http://t.co/2tThW5DZGZ</a></p>&mdash; Notting Hill Housing (@NottingHillHG) <a href="https://twitter.com/NottingHillHG/status/583639651702943744">April 2, 2015</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>Notting Hill&rsquo;s twitter reply also blamed its change of tenure on <strong> <em>&ldquo;Government changes to rent setting&rdquo;</em> </strong> and provided a <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/customers/permanent-rented-housing/money/how-we-set-your-rent-and-charges/rent-increases">link to its website</a> for further details. Below is an extract from that website link, where Notting Hill explains what affordable rent is and confirms that <strong> <em>&ldquo;Approximately 10% of all our &lsquo;social rented housing&rsquo; properties are rented at affordable rents&rdquo;.</em> </strong><br/>
<img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/NHHTAffordableRent.png" width="550" height="500"></p>

<p>We note that Notting Hill has written the term <strong>&lsquo;social rented housing&rsquo;</strong> in inverted commas. It seems that - thanks to Notting Hill Housing Trust - this might be the way <strong>&lsquo;social rented housing&rsquo;</strong> needs to be written from now on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Affordable Rent Is Not Social Rent]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/10/affordable-rent-is-not-social/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-10T20:37:50+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/10/affordable-rent-is-not-social</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/279910_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/wolvertons106SR2.png" width="400" height="400"></a>We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">blogged previously</a> about the last phase of the Aylesbury redevelopment, where we saw plans waved through as social rent, only to discover afterwards that the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/279910_1.pdf">s106 legal agreement</a> defined social rent as encompassing the <a href="http://cfg.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/affordable-rent">HCA&rsquo;s definition of affordable rent</a> (80% market rent).
</br>
</br></p>

<p><a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk/Manor-Place-Exhibition-Banners.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Manorplace_socialrent2.png" width="300" height="320"></a>Notting Hill Housing Group, which is developing all subsequent phases of the Aylesbury estate, has taken a different approach: instead of substituting affordable rent for social rent via the back door, it is openly defining affordable rent as a subcategory of social rent.
Those familiar with housing policy will know that social rents are not determined by Housing Associations; they are determined by the National Rent Regime regulatory framework - and that they are not set in relation to market rents; they are set in relation to average household incomes.</p>

<p>This hasn&rsquo;t deterred Notting Hill Housing; its <a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk/Manor-Place-Exhibition-Banners.pdf">consultation document</a> for another Walworth scheme, the <a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk">Manor Place development</a> (a former Council <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/10070/recycling/1364/reuse_and_recycling_centre">refuse depot</a>) shows it will be setting rents for its new social rented homes at <em>&ldquo;up to 50% of local market rents&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/RentsRising.jpg" width="300" height="200">50% of local market rents may sound like a good deal to some, but in an area where rents have increased by 17% in the last 3 years<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> to an average £300 per week for a 1-bed flat<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, 50% of market rents is roughly double existing council rents. The crucial difference is also that market rents rise well beyond wages in property hotspots like Southwark; an important consideration in a borough where the average household income of a council tenant is £9,100 per year<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> and definitely not rising at the same rate as local market rents.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/affordablerentstudy.png" width="350" height="300"></a>Southwark council has undertaken <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/download/2914/affordable_rent_in_southwark_2011">a study</a> of the affordability of affordable rent in the borough, so it is entirely aware that these ridiculous &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; rents are unaffordable to most of its residents. Indeed, it has said as much in <a href="http://35percent.org/images/fionacolleyresponsetolondonplan.pdf">representations to the Mayor</a> rejecting the new tenure policy. <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">This spreadheet</a> from the council&rsquo;s study shows the minimum household income needed for one of Notting Hill&rsquo;s new 50% market rent &lsquo;social rented&rsquo; homes is £39,860 per year - well beyond the £21,000 mean average household income in Walworth.</p>

<p>We don&rsquo;t yet know what percentage of market rent the replacement &lsquo;social&rsquo; housing on the new Aylesbury estate will be, but we do know that the <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.pdf">Agreement</a> signed for the sale of the estate allows notting hill to set the new affordable rents at up to 80% market rent:</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.png"></a></p>

<p>Some might see all this as an inevitable consequence of the market and beyond the control of public authorities, but this would ignore the fact that the Aylesbury and Manor Place depot are on council-owned land, being bought in turn by a publicly-funded Housing Association. Southwark and Notting Hill should be fulfilling their duty to build truly affordable and truly social rented homes on this land, not playing games with dodgy &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; housing definitions.
</br></p>

<h2>More from the Notting Hill Mob</h2>

<p>Notting Hill are also involved in the Council&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/823/regeneration_projects/1798/elmington_regeneration/4">Elmingtion estate regeneration</a> in Camberwell, where the council has just <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s48494/Report%20CPO%20for%20Elmington%20Estate.pdf">issued a Compulsory Purchase Order</a> on 144 homes in phase 3 of the scheme. Phases 1 &amp; 2, where Notting Hill has already <a href="http://directobjective.blogspot.co.uk/2011/12/elmington-estate-revisited.html">demolished 373 council homes</a>, are nearing completion and the new &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; homes are currently being marketed in the development rebranded <a href="http://www.camberwellfields.com/">&lsquo;Camberwell Fields&rsquo;</a>.
<a href="http://www.camberwellfields.com/"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/camberwell-fields-logo.png"></a></p>

<p>Paragraph 12 of this <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s30291/Report%20Disposal%20of%20the%20Councils%20freehold%20interest%20in%20Elmington%20estate%20sites%20C%20D%20E%20and%20G%20Camberw.pdf">Council report</a> confirms that all replacement 1 &amp; 2 bed social housing in the redevelopment will be set at 65% market rent. According to <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">Southwark&rsquo;s figures</a> this will amount to £194 per week: double the existing council rents. Tenants who have been &lsquo;decanted&rsquo; from the estate and wish to exercise their right to return, will therefore need to be able to afford a 100% rent hike.</p>

<p>But the main component of the new &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; housing comprises shared ownership units. Notting Hill has just released the <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/CamberwellFields.pdf">price list</a> for these, and the cheapest will be £380k for a 1-bed flat. For this you will need to buy a minimum 40% share, have a minimum household income of £51,824 and will pay a total of £1,438 per month in rent, mortgage and service charge payments. The average income of Camberwell households is £24,400pa, so they are obviously out of luck.</p>

<h2>Not Notting Hill (but not better neither)..</h2>

<p><a href="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/properties/lq-trafalgar-place/?preview=true"><img class="left" src="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/LQ-@-Trafalfar-Place-Brochure.jpg" width="250" height="300"></a>Last week, L&amp;Q <a href="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/properties/lq-trafalgar-place/?preview=true">launched</a> its shared ownership homes on the redeveloped Heygate estate. The launch coincided with the latest phase of marketing at a <a href="http://www.thestandard.com.hk/news_detail.asp?art_id=154851&amp;con_type=3">sales event in Hong Kong</a>. According to L&amp;Q&rsquo;s <a href="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/LQ-@-Trafalgar-Place-Pricelist-12-bed-launch-2.pdf">price list</a>, the cheapest of the Heygate&rsquo;s new &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; shared ownership homes will set you back £126k for a 30% stake in a 1-bed flat, for which you will need to buy a minimum 30% share, requiring a household income of at least £57,500k per year. A 25% share in a 2-bed duplex will set you back £185,625, but with a minimum household income requirement of £64,500 it won&rsquo;t be long before you will be able to staircase up to full ownership of the flat, priced at a mere £742,500. It seems our council leader is finally delivering on his housing <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7585">pledge</a> to help poor Southwark residents on <em>&ldquo;£60-£80,000 a year – but who have absolutely no hope of buying&rdquo;</em>.   <br/>
</br></p>

<h2>Southwark seeks help</h2>

<p><a href="http://southwark.communitymaps.org.uk/#/project/15?center=51.4653:-0.0707:12"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/interactivemap.png" width="250" height="250"></a>While council estates tumble across the borough Southwark Council has launched an <a href="http://southwark.communitymaps.org.uk/#/welcome">interactive map</a>, inviting people to suggest where it should build its pledged 11,000 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes. Vacant land is limited so it will be a difficult task; back in December the Council even <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/12/06/11000-new-private-and-social-council-homes-on-target/">suggested</a> exploring the purchase of land on the open market from developers. Given its <a href="http://35percent.org/heygate-regeneration-faq/">track record</a> in negotiating with developers, a better alternative would be to build the new council homes on the vast estates that the Council is &lsquo;regenerating&rsquo; (Heygate, Aylesbury, Wooddene &amp; Elmington etc). Even now it’s not too late and surely preferable to selling these sites off to developers and corporated-minded Housing Associations, who provide nothing but a few unaffordable affordable homes in return?</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Source: <a href="http://data.london.gov.uk/dataset/average-private-rents-borough/resource/73b9fb07-b5bb-4a53-88b7-c17269879a08">Greater London Authority - Dataset 2014</a><a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See data for SE17 in Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">Dec 2014 Affordable Rent Study dataset</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See sheet 8, row 9 of the Council&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">Dec 2014 Affordable Rent Study update</a>.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Greenwich Developers Ordered to Show Their Sums]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/02/04/developers-ordered-to-show-their-sums/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-04T15:19:21+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/02/04/developers-ordered-to-show-their-sums</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://gsa-studios.com/images/uploads/projects/1168x650_greenwich.jpg" width="300" height="200">We reported last year how a residents group in Greenwich had followed our lead and requested the viability assessments justifying decisions to reduce affordable housing in the £5bn Greenwich Peninsula redevelopment. Similar to our request for the Heygate figures, Greenwich residents had won the support of the Information Commissioner but were then taken to appeal by the Council and developer Knight Dragon. We put them in touch with our legal friends at Leigh Day &amp; Monckton Chambers and expert witness <a href="http://www.northampton.ac.uk/directories/people/bob-colenutt">Dr Colenutt</a> who helped the campaigners take on the Council &amp; developer&rsquo;s barristers at an Information Tribunal hearing in October last year.</p>

<p>After a two month wait, the Tribunal issued its <a href="http://bit.ly/1zS9Qc0">decision notice</a> earlier this week. The decision was conclusive and damning; it rejected the Council&rsquo;s arguments and pointed out that councillors on Greenwich&rsquo;s planning committee had no more information about the viability figures than did the general public. Hong Kong developer Knight Frank&rsquo;s arguments about commercial confidentiality were also given short shrift by the Judge <strong> <em>&ldquo;This is a case where a company, robust enough to take on the development of a huge site over a period of 20 years.. immediately asks to be relieved of a planning obligation freely negotiated by its predecessor. It justifies this change on the basis of a downturn in house prices it knew about at the time of purchase, using a valuation model that looks at current values only and does not allow for change in the many factors that may affect a valuation over time. It seems to us that in those circumstances the public interest in openness about the figures is very strong.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>In contrast to the Heygate decision where developer Lend Lease was allowed to withhold its financial model in appendix 22 of the assessment, the Greenwich decision took a much tougher line: <strong> <em>&lsquo;once it is accepted that the EIR regulations apply, it is necessary to apply them in their full rigour.  There is no room for an “EIR lite” approach&rsquo;</em> </strong> (para. 24) <br/>
There are more details about the Greenwich decision on the <a href="http://853blog.com/2015/02/03/greenwich-peninsula-social-cleansing-council-loses-battle-to-keep-developer-document-secret/">853 blog</a>.</p>

<h2>Viability for dummies</h2>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/viabilityfordummies.pdf"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/viabilityfordummies.png" width="300" height="400"></a>In terms of EIR case law, there was still some doubt following the Heygate decision about exactly what developers are allowed to withhold, especially in light of the ongoing legal battle over the interpretation of the Heygate decision notice. The Greenwich decision appears to have addressed that ambiguity and provided a clear steer as to what exactly is subject to disclosure - everything.</p>

<p>This should now clear the path for other community groups to obtain viability information and participate more meaningfully in planning issues.</p>

<p>In an attempt to help them do so, we have drafted a <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/viabilityfordummies.pdf">&lsquo;dummies&rsquo; guide</a> to viability, part 1 of which explains how to obtain viability information using EIR requests.</p>

<h2>Heygate Tribunal battle continues</h2>

<p>The ongoing battle over the interpretation of the Tribunal&rsquo;s May 2014 <a href="http://www.informationtribunal.gov.uk/DBFiles/Decision/i1279/London%20Borough%20of%20Southwark%20EA.2013.0162%20%2809.05.14%29.pdf">decision notice</a> continues. The decision allowed Lend Lease to withhold its financial development model projections on retail and office floorspace. The notice ordered the parties to get together and agree on dividing up the information for disclosure along those lines. It acknowledged that there may be &lsquo;grey areas&rsquo; and stated that if parties are unable to reach agreement then it will reconvene to settle the argument.
After many months of stalling and heel dragging by Southwark and Lend Lease, the Tribunal reconvened partially in October and was due to reconvene for a full hearing on 11th Dec last year. But Lend Lease&rsquo;s Commercial Director was unable to attend so the hearing was postponed. The hearing was finally able to take place on 21st January when parties made their arguments on how the information should be divided up according to the Tribunal&rsquo;s May 2014 decision.</p>

<p>During the hearing Lend Lease&rsquo;s counsel argued that protecting its financial model in appendix 22, also extended to protecting the inputs and outputs to the model found elsewhere in the report and its appendices. Mr Glasspool&rsquo;s counsel pointed out that the inputs and outputs did not form &lsquo;part of the model&rsquo; and would not expose the model&rsquo;s underlying formulas that Lend Lease had so vehemently argued were its &lsquo;trade secret&rsquo;.</p>

<p>The Tribunal is expected to issue a decision notice detailing exactly which information can be withheld some time in the next few weeks.</p>

<h2>Southwark joins 35% campaign</h2>

<p>Southwark Council issued a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1903/southwark_council_slams_plans_to_reduce_affordable_housing_contributions">press statement</a> earlier this week entitled <strong> <em>&ldquo;Southwark Council slams plans to reduce affordable housing contributions.&rdquo;</em> </strong> The statement says it <strong> <em>&ldquo;has hit out at government plans to allow developers to reduce affordable housing contributions&rdquo;</em> </strong>. It is referring to the governments new <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2015/feb/01/property-developers-affordable-housing-councils-empty-building">&lsquo;vacant building credit&rsquo;</a>, which is said to cut back even further the amount of affordable housing delivered through planning gain.</p>

<p>Much as we applaud Southwark&rsquo;s sentiment, we point out that it first needs to sort out its problem of allowing developers to get away with avoiding affordable housing by viability assessments. Two such examples are these developments currently under construction at the Elephant, both of which are being built on land sold to developers by the Council. Thanks to Southwark&rsquo;s failure to question the viability assessments submitted at planning, neither of these will provide any affordable housing and the payments in-lieu are a fraction of what they should have been according to Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://affordable.heroku.com/images/affordablehousingspg.pdf">in-lieu tariff</a>.     <br/>
<img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/tribecaonetheelephant.jpg"></p>

<p>You can read more detailed info about the Tribeca Square development <a href="http://35percent.org/tribeca-square/">here</a> and One The Elephant <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/01/11/flogging-the-elephant/">here.</a></p>

<h2>Aylesbury Occupied</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/B8_4AbdIAAAb-ir.jpg" width="300" height="600"> Housing activists have occupied empty homes on the Aylesbury estate. The activists took up occupation directly following last weekend&rsquo;s <a href="http://marchforhomes.org">March for Homes</a> and are protesting at the failure to address London&rsquo;s growing housing crisis.</p>

<p>In an <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/development/protestors-occupy-estate-earmarked-for-15bn-regeneration/7008068.article">interview</a> with Inside Housing, Councillor Williams, Southwark&rsquo;s Cabinet member for Regeneration claimed that the protesters <strong> <em>&ldquo;are risking the delivery of the very homes they claim to be campaigning for.&rdquo;</em> </strong> He went on to explain that <strong> <em>&ldquo;The scheme will be 50% affordable, with 75% of these rented and 25% for shared ownership.&rdquo;</em> </strong> We are unsurprised to note the semantic subtlety of Cllr Williams&#8217; omitting to use either the word <strong>&lsquo;social&rsquo;</strong> or <strong>&lsquo;affordable&rsquo;</strong> in conjunction with the word <strong>&lsquo;rented&rsquo;</strong>.</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyTLF.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyTLF.png" width="300" height="400"></a>Cllr Williams also claims that the protestors don&rsquo;t represent the Aylesbury residents, but <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyTLF.pdf">this flyer</a> suggests that at least <a href="http://aylesburytenantsfirst.org.uk/">one tenants group</a> on the estate disagrees.</p>

<p>The Aylesbury occupiers have set up a website for their campaign <a href="http://fightfortheaylesbury.wordpress.com">http://fightfortheaylesbury.wordpress.com</a> and Twitter account: @OccupyAylesbury
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>Concrete Heartland</h2>

<p>Concrete Heartland, a film about the Heygate regeneration by Steven Ball and Rastko Novaković has now been released online. Following a number of screenings last year, it has now been uploaded for popular consumption and can be viewed online at <a href="http://concreteheartland.info">http://concreteheartland.info</a><br/>
Assembled from 12 years of archive materials, the film charts the struggles of the local community to keep their homes, stay living in the area and maintain communal benefits in the face of the advance of this now notorious &lsquo;urban redevelopment programme&rsquo;.</p>

<h2>West Hendon estate</h2>

<p>BBC&rsquo;s The One Show featured a piece on the West Hendon estate on Monday. Due to the notorius viability arguments, residents there are being forced out of the area after developers Barratt argued that it was no longer possible to rehouse them in the new development. The story sounds all too familiar to us down here in Southwark.
</center></p>

<iframe width="350" height="197" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5OXc814Q9ps" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p></center></p>

<h2>Affordable housing tenants excluded from communal gardens</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/media/brochure/b2678/files/assets/common/page-substrates/page0015.jpg" width="300" height="200">Southwark&rsquo;s planning committee <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/8077">has agreed</a> to a variation in planning conditions for the <a href="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/new-homes/london/tower-bridge/one-tower-bridge">One Tower Bridge development</a>, to prevent affordable housing tenants being able to use the communal garden available to private residents. Simon Bevan, Southwark&rsquo;s director of planning, told the planning committee that the exclusion of social tenants from the garden was <strong> <em>&ldquo;not seen as any significant restriction on how they enjoy their property&rdquo;.</em> </strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
