<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[35% Campaign]]></title>
  <link href="http://35percent.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://35percent.org/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-21T11:29:14+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://35percent.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[EAN]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Barratt Conquers Southwark]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/09/14/barratt-conquers-southwark/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-14T18:01:50+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/09/14/barratt-conquers-southwark</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Barratt Homes, Britains third-largest housebuilder, has just <a href="http://www.cityam.com/223932/building-bonanza-barratt-profits-jump-45-cent">posted</a> a 45% rise in profits to £565.5m during the last financial year.</p>

<p>Barratt&rsquo;s success is due in part to its pipeline of major developments in Southwark, which include <a href="http://www.barratthomes.co.uk/new-homes/greater-london/h469201-maple-quays/"><strong>Maple Quays</strong></a> (668 homes in phase 1 of the <a href="http://35percent.org/canada-water/">Canada Water regeneration</a>); <a href="http://www.barratthomes.co.uk/new-homes/greater-london/track-record---article-pages/the-galleria/"><strong>The Galleria</strong></a> development in Peckham; <a href="http://www.barratthomes.co.uk/new-homes/greater-london/h309201-redwood-park/"><strong>Redwood Park</strong></a> (212 homes on former council land at Surrey Quays) and the 60-acre, 3,500-home Aylesbury estate redevelompent for which Barratt is Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/our-developments/aylesbury-estate-southwark">development partner</a>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='https://betterblackfriars.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/erlang-house.jpg' width='' height='' title='Barratt's Blackfriars Circus development featuring 'The Conquest Apartments''><span class='caption-text'>Barratt&rsquo;s Blackfriars Circus development featuring &lsquo;The Conquest Apartments&rsquo;</span></span></p>

<p>Barratt has also recently started work on its <a href="http://www.barratthomes.co.uk/new-homes/greater-london/H625601-Blackfriars-circus/"><strong>&lsquo;Blackfriars Circus&rsquo;</strong></a> development, comprising 336 new homes in 5 buildings ranging up to 27 storeys in height, overlooking the South Bank University campus near Elephant &amp; Castle. According to <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/8441">SE1 website</a> the tallest of these will be known as <strong>&lsquo;The Conquest Apartments&rsquo;</strong>. This is an appropriate name for a development that was able to dupe Southwark council into waiving the tenure requirements of its 35% affordable housing Policy. These would have secured a minimum 70 social rented homes in the development, but Barratt submitted a viability assessment claiming it would only be viable to provide 8 social rented homes and 48 affordable rent homes. The <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!5wmNTTJlhAE1P%2fSH390aXg%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">officer&rsquo;s report</a> explains that the council had the viability assessment appraised by the &lsquo;Borough Valuer&rsquo; and that <strong> <em>&ldquo;Whilst a number of inputs into the valuation have been agreed (including commercial values, ground rents, and professional fees) an agreement has not been reached on two fundamental matters: methodology of calculating the benchmark value of the site; and residential sale values. As such, the applicant and the Borough Valuer have not reached an agreed position about how much affordable housing can be delivered on site.&rdquo;</em> </strong> (para. 109)</p>

<p>Nevertheless the planning application was waved through and demolition works started on the site earlier this year. However, it is now being <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/8441">reported</a> that the council is planning to buy these 8 social and 48 affordable rented homes from Barratt, in order to turn them into social rented council homes at a cost of £10m.</p>

<p>The absurdity of buying homes from developers to convert to social rent when they should have been social rent anyway, is plain for all to see.
However, it also appears that Southwark is paying well over the market price: the £10m price tag for 56 affordable housing units seems an awful lot compared to the <a href="http://35percent.org/images/LR_LANDQ_TrafalgarPlace.pdf">£3.1m paid</a> by L&amp;Q for 54 affordable homes it brought from Heygate developer Lend Lease at <a href="http://trafalgarplace.com">Trafalgar Place</a>.</p>

<h2>Maple Quays</h2>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='https://pbs.twimg.com/media/CKr8DTiWUAAJn7n.jpg' width='300' height='200' title=''><span class='caption-text'></span></span>In 2013, Barratt completed its <a href="http://www.barratthomes.co.uk/new-homes/greater-london/h469201-maple-quays/"><strong>Maple Quays</strong></a> development at Canada Water. This first phase of the <a href="http://35percent.org/canada-water/">Canada Water regeneration</a> comprised 9 buildings ranging up to 26 storeys, providing 668 residential units of which 123 were supposed to be social rent - according to the council&rsquo;s <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!vAhB%2bWXWLqfrJmcf89aX8A%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">planning report</a> for the planning application
:</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!vAhB%2bWXWLqfrJmcf89aX8A%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/CanadaWaterSiteA_OR.png' width='' height='' title='Officer report for Site A planning permission (ref:09/AP/1870)'><span class='caption-text'>Officer report for Site A planning permission (ref:09/AP/1870)</span></span></a></p>

<p>However, when the <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!x3RgHHSbSY10notKcDq0rQ%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">section 106 legal agreement</a> was drawn up, there was no mention of social rented housing - only <strong>&lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo;</strong> (i.e. 80% market rent):</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!x3RgHHSbSY10notKcDq0rQ%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/CanadaWaterS106.png' width='' height='' title='S106 Legal agreement for Site A'><span class='caption-text'>S106 Legal agreement for Site A</span></span></a></p>

<h2>Chambers Wharf</h2>

<p>It is starting to look this these tenure switches have become routine practice for new developments in Southwark. The arrangement suits both developers and the council, who can <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/100-affordable-homes-open-on-brownfield-site/">claim the credit</a> for delivering new social rented housing, which is in actual fact affordable rent.<br/>
We recently discovered such a tenure switch at <strong>Chambers Wharf</strong>, Berkeley Homes&#8217; latest development on Southwark&rsquo;s riverside. In May this year, Councillor Williams <a href="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/press-releases/2015/southwark-development-sets-new-standard-for-affordable-housing-in-london">proclaimed</a> the completion of <strong> <em>&ldquo;106 social rented apartments and 14 social rented family homes,&rdquo;</em> </strong> which he claimed was proof that the council is <strong> <em>&ldquo;tackling the housing crisis head on and are doing all we can to build the quality affordable homes our residents so desperately need&rdquo;</em> </strong>.<br/>
But what Councillor Williams&#8217; press statement didn&rsquo;t say was that the 89 of the social rented homes had been converted to affordable rents of 65% market rent by <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/ieDecisionDetails.aspx?Id=3617">mutual agreement</a> with the council, following a &lsquo;viability review&rsquo; of the scheme in 2013.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/chamberswharf.jpg' width='' height='' title='Chambers Wharf - before and after'><span class='caption-text'>Chambers Wharf - before and after</span></span></p>

<h2>Will the Aylesbury follow suit?</h2>

<p>Questions are being asked whether the replacement <strong>social rented</strong> housing on London&rsquo;s largest council estate redevelopment scheme will meet the same fate, i.e. end up being delivered as <strong>affordable rent</strong>?</p>

<p>Three weeks ago the council published its <a href="http://35percent.org/images/AylesburyS106.pdf">Section 106 agreement</a> with Notting Hill Housing for the Aylesbury redevelopment, which covers both the <strong>First Development Site</strong> (<strong>FDS</strong> - phase one) and the <strong>Outline Development Site</strong> (the rest of the scheme). We have had a thorough read of the agreement and have got some serious concerns about the wording, which we think could open the door to interpretation as <strong>affordable rent</strong> on the Outline Site.</p>

<p>Our main concern is that the agreement&rsquo;s affordable housing schedule prescribes <strong>&lsquo;social rented&rsquo;</strong> housing for the <strong>First Development Site</strong> (<strong>FDS</strong>), but the wording for the <strong>Outline Site</strong> has omitted the word <strong>&lsquo;rented&rsquo;</strong> and says just <strong>&lsquo;social&rsquo;</strong> housing. Given the fact that there is no definition elsewhere in the agreement for the term ‘Social’, we are worried that any future legal dispute over the interpretation of this term may fall back on the statutory definition, which includes affordable rent under the broad definition of ‘social’ housing in <a href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2008/17/section/68">section 68 of the Housing and Regeneration Act 2008</a>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/aylesburyAHschedule.png' width='' height='' title='Schedule 8 of the S106 Agreement'><span class='caption-text'>Schedule 8 of the S106 Agreement</span></span></p>

<p>Of additional concern is that various references can be found in the agreement in relation to social rented housing on the <strong>FDS</strong>, but there are no specific references to social rented housing in relation to the <strong>Outline Site</strong>:</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/AylesburyS106_pg42.png' width='' height='' title='Schedule 3 of the S106 Agreement'><span class='caption-text'>Schedule 3 of the S106 Agreement</span></span></p>

<p>We have written a <a href="http://35percent.org/images/AylesburyS106_CllrWilliams.pdf">letter</a> to Councillor Williams setting out our concerns in detail and requesting that the S106 agreement be amended.</p>

<p>If the council and Notting Hill are <strong>genuinely</strong> committed to the provision of <strong>social rented</strong> rather than <strong>affordable rented</strong> housing on the Aylesbury, then we see no reason why they wouldn&rsquo;t agree to these amendments.</p>

<p><meta name="twitter:card" content="summary_large_image">
<meta name="twitter:site" content="@35Percent_EAN">
<meta name="twitter:title" content="Aylesbury redevelopment agreement leaves door open to affordable rent">
<meta name="twitter:description" content="The Aylesbury redevelopment section 106 agreement has been worded such that the door has been left open to interpretation as affordable rent rather than social rent.">
<meta name="twitter:image" content="http://35percent.org/images/aylesburyAHschedule.png"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kipling Estate's Literary Connections]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/25/kipling-and-the-quill/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-25T20:15:05+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/25/kipling-and-the-quill</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week the Guardian picked up on our <a href="http://35percent.org/neo-bankside">analysis</a> of the Neo Bankside affordable housing fiasco and ran an <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/architecture-design-blog/2015/jul/21/neo-bankside-how-richard-rogers-new-non-dom-accom-cut-out-the-poor">article</a> highlighting Southwark&rsquo;s growing problem of accepting payments in-lieu of affordable housing.</p>

<p>On Thursday the Guardian ran a <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/davehillblog/2015/jul/23/resident-led-southwark-social-housing-scheme-shows-london-the-way">different story</a> about an in-fill project to provide new council homes on a Southwark council estate, which it said <strong> <em>&ldquo;shows London the way&rdquo;</em> </strong> in solving the housing crisis.</p>

<p>As part of its <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200537/11000_new_council_homes">programme to build 11,000 new council homes</a>, Southwark council is trumpeting the construction of 30 new council homes on the Kipling estate, managed by its TMO <a href="http://www.leathermarketjmb.org.uk/category/new-homes/"><strong>&lsquo;Leathermarket CBS&rsquo;</strong></a>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/kiplingestate.png' width='' height='' title='Proposed site for new council homes on the TMO-managed Kipling estate'><span class='caption-text'>Proposed site for new council homes on the TMO-managed Kipling estate</span></span></p>

<p>But what the Guardian article or press release didn&rsquo;t say, is that the project is being funded by the developer of a new residential tower at London Bridge, who has agreed to fund it in exchange for not having to provide any affordable housing on-site in its development.</p>

<p>Developer <a href="http://investream.com"><strong>&lsquo;Investream&rsquo;</strong></a>- acting under the auspices of a shell company <strong>&lsquo;Bilford Ltd&rsquo;</strong> (<a href="http://35percent.org/images/LR_Bilford.pdf">registered</a> in Jersey) - has submitted a <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk:8190/online-applications/applicationDetails.do?activeTab=summary&amp;keyVal=_STHWR_DCAPR_9558037">planning application</a> for the demolition of <strong>Capital House</strong> (a 10 storey building leased by KCL as part of its <a href="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/innovation/research/support/grants/contact/guys.aspx">Guy&rsquo;s campus</a>) and the construction of <strong>&lsquo;The Quill&rsquo;</strong> - a 21 and 31 storey building connected via walkways and decorated with a quill-shaped spire, which the <a href="http://www.spparcstudio.com/Home.aspx">architect</a> claims  <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!lv%2bf4WD7hw9vUL41nLaBAA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><em>&ldquo;will draw on the literary connections of Southwark.&rdquo;</em></a> (para. 4.132)</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/quill2.png' width='' height='' title='CGI mockup of proposed development 'The Quill' near London Bridge'><span class='caption-text'>CGI mockup of proposed development &lsquo;The Quill&rsquo; near London Bridge</span></span></p>

<p><strong>The Quill</strong> was orginally <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7918">granted</a> planning consent in 2011, but to provide student accommodation which was exempt from affordable housing requirements. This <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk:8190/online-applications/applicationDetails.do?activeTab=summary&amp;keyVal=_STHWR_DCAPR_9558037">new application</a> seeks to convert the accommodation to private residential use, providing 119 new homes. Southwark&rsquo;s 35% policy would normally require at least 41 of these to be provided as affordable housing units on-site, of which 13 would need to be shared ownership and 28 social rented. Instead of meeting these on-site requirements, <strong>Bilford</strong> has applied to fund the construction of around 30 social rented homes off-site on the Kipling estate.</p>

<p>In November 2014 Bilford submitted a detailed <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!a%2fXn%2fIRgCqJtDcLW0mQiuA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">Affordable Housing Statement</a> with its planning application, setting out its funding offer to Leathermarket and has submitted a confidential viability assessment justifying why affordable housing on-site would not be viable.</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!a%2fXn%2fIRgCqJtDcLW0mQiuA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/quillahstatement.png' width='' height='' title='Extract from The Quill planning application's affordable housing statement'><span class='caption-text'>Extract from The Quill planning application&rsquo;s affordable housing statement</span></span></a></p>

<p>Things have apparently now changed since this original agreement between <strong>Bilford</strong> and Leathermarket. <strong>Bilford</strong> will now be making the in-lieu payment to the council&rsquo;s s106 fund instead of directly to Leathermarket. The council will in turn fund the Kipling estate project from its pooled S106 funds. This triangular accounting provides a layer of separation between the two schemes and enables Southwark to trumpet the Kipling project as part of its ambitious programme to build 11,000 new council homes.</p>

<p>New social rented homes are good, but accepting them in-lieu of ones that should be provided on-site in new developments goes directly against the council&rsquo;s policy of creating mixed communities, which it has used so vociferously in justifying the demoliton of its &lsquo;mono-tenure&rsquo; Heygate &amp; Aylesbury estates.</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!vH%2be%2bKK7uZu6GcJ8p3lqbQ%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/carvil_bilford.png' width='300' height='500' title='Kim Humphries acting on behalf of Bilford'><span class='caption-text'>Kim Humphries acting on behalf of Bilford</span></span></a>Representing and <a href="http://carvil-ventures.co.uk/node/68">advising</a> <strong>Bilford</strong> is former deputy council leader, turned development consultant Kim Humphries. Kim founded <a href="http://carvil-ventures.co.uk/about-us"><strong>&lsquo;Carvil Ventures&rsquo;</strong></a> after losing his seat in 2010 and has been helping developers obtain planning permission ever since. Among his <a href="http://carvil-ventures.co.uk/clients-partners">clients</a> are <strong>Delancey</strong>, developers of the <a href="http://carvil-ventures.co.uk/elephant-castle-shopping-centre">Elephant &amp; Castle shopping centre</a> and <a href="http://carvil-ventures.co.uk/node/36">185 Park Street</a>; <strong>Neobrand&rsquo;s</strong> <a href="http://carvil-ventures.co.uk/node/69">87 Newington Causeway development</a> and <strong>British Land&rsquo;s</strong> <a href="http://carvil-ventures.co.uk/node/30">Canada Water</a> scheme.</p>

<p>Kim also prepared Bilford&rsquo;s <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!pMcMh5jSJoLhoPr4hZ2nzw%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">Statement of Community Involvement</a> - a necessary planning document showing that the developer has consulted with the local community. Kim claims to have obtained <strong> <em>&ldquo;extensive feedback&rdquo;</em> </strong> from his public consultation, in which he claims <strong> <em>&ldquo;considerable support was expressed for Bilford&rsquo;s redevelopment plans with 60% supporting the proposals.&rdquo;</em> </strong> But page 15 of the <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!pMcMh5jSJoLhoPr4hZ2nzw%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">Statement</a>, shows that his claim of 60% support is based on a survey of just 15 people..<br/>
</br></p>

<h2>The future of &ldquo;high investment needs estates&rdquo;</h2>

<p>Last week we <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/18/all-is-to-be-revealed/">blogged</a> about the results of Savills&#8217; <strong> <em>&ldquo;Asset Performance Evaluation,&rdquo;</em> </strong> which gave rankings to each of the borough&rsquo;s council estates based on asset value and social achievement indicators. The estates were then labelled as either assets which would continue to receive <strong> <em>&ldquo;regular investment&rdquo;</em> </strong> or _ <strong>&ldquo;high investment needs estates,&rdquo;_ </strong> which would be considered for _ <strong>&ldquo;redevelopment or regeneration&rdquo;_ </strong>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/Richard-Livingstone.jpg' width='300' height='450' title='Cllr Richard Livingstone - Member for Housing'><span class='caption-text'>Cllr Richard Livingstone - Member for Housing</span></span>When Southwark News ran a <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/your-home-is-worth-less-than-nothing-council-report-evaluates-southwark-properties/">story</a> on the Savills evaluation last week, Cllr Richard Livingstone fought back insisting that it had been misunderstood and reassured council tenants that it was <strong> <em>&ldquo;only ever an exercise to see how the council could invest its funds in an informed way, to improve everyone’s living conditions.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>He claimed that it was simply <strong> <em>“an indication of where higher levels of investment are needed in the buildings alone, to make sure they are up to the standards of quality our residents deserve.&ldquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>He goes on to explain that <strong> <em>&ldquo;The report makes it very clear that there is no need for Southwark to consider any further large scale redevelopment schemes like the Heygate or the Aylesbury and that any redevelopment would only be considered as a ‘last resort.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>However, a closer look at Cllr Livingstone&rsquo;s <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s55565/Report%20Future%20Estate%20Regeneration.pdf">report</a> which accompanied the Savills evaluation, paints a very different picture of its purpose and intent:</p>

<p><a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s55565/Report%20Future%20Estate%20Regeneration.pdf"><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/CabinetReport.png' width='350' height='550' title='Cllr Livingstone's report to Cabinet'><span class='caption-text'>Cllr Livingstone&rsquo;s report to Cabinet</span></span></a>The report speaks of <strong> <em>&ldquo;high investment need estates&rdquo;</em> </strong> where there is <strong> <em>&ldquo;a legacy of poorly designed and built housing,&rdquo;</em> </strong> coupled with <strong> <em>&ldquo;opportunities  to  increase  the  amount  of  council  housing  through wider estate regeneration.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>It goes on to highlight <strong> <em>&ldquo;the  need  to  make  difficult  choices&rdquo;</em> </strong> accompanied by <strong> <em>&ldquo;the  prospect  of  leveraging  in  private  sector investment,&rdquo;</em> </strong> but with the reassurance that <strong> <em>&ldquo;the number of new council homes delivered as a result of the schemes will exceed the numbers demolished.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>The report concludes by saying that residents in those estates affected will only be consulted once officers have decided their homes should be demolished: <strong> <em>&ldquo;Prior to proceeding to engagement with residents, a cross-council panel  of relevant officers will have met to establish the feasibility of sites.&rdquo;</em> </strong> (para. 18)</p>

<p>We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/07/23/mystery-objector-1301/">blogged</a> in July last year about a council report which referred to a zone <strong> <em>&ldquo;within which the majority of housing estates identified for Estate renewal are located”</em> </strong> and in <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">December</a> last year about the commissioning of the asset performance evaluation. Two weeks ago the council leader <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s55105/Appendix%202%20-%20Members%20Questions%20with%20supplemental%20questions.pdf">claimed</a> to <strong> <em>&#8220;have identified approximately 500 sites&rdquo;</em> </strong> for its programme to build 11,000 homes (see Q4).</p>

<p>The council should stop beating about the bush with its estate renewal plans. The fate of the Heygate, Aylesbury, Wood Dene and Elmington estates were all sealed when they became labelled as <strong> <em>&ldquo;high investment needs estates.&rdquo;</em> </strong> The council needs to come clean about exactly what plans it has for the earmarked estates and start involving residents in its decision making now.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/06/staying-put-cover.jpg?w=208&h=300' width='' height='' title='The 'Staying Put' Handbook'><span class='caption-text'>The &lsquo;Staying Put&rsquo; Handbook</span></span>Southwark News has published a <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/your-home-is-worth-less-than-nothing-council-report-evaluates-southwark-properties/">list</a> of all the <strong> <em>&ldquo;high investment need estates&rdquo;</em> </strong> earmarked by the Savills evaluation. Residents on these estates would do well to start reading the <a href="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/06/staying-put-web-version-low.pdf"><strong>&lsquo;Staying Put Handbook&rsquo;</strong></a> - a guide for communities facing demolition and displacement.<br/>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Councillor John Promises to Reveal All]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/18/all-is-to-be-revealed/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-18T11:19:19+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/18/all-is-to-be-revealed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/pjflasher.jpg" width="200" height="400">Viability assessments, the secret documents that developers use to reduce the amount of affordable housing they build, will now have to be made public, according to <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/my-conscience-is-clear-council-leader-peter-john-comes-out-fighting-as-heygate-deal-scrutinised/">this interview</a> that council leader Peter John gave in the Southwark News last week.</p>

<p>Councillor John also said that we could be getting more affordable housing on Lend Lease&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.elephantpark.co.uk/"><strong>Elephant Park</strong></a> development (formerly the Heygate estate).</p>

<p>On viability assessments Cllr John is swimming with the tide. Islington council has just revealed its detailed and well thought-out <a href="http://www.islington.gov.uk/services/planning/planningpol/pol_supplement/Pages/Development-Viability-Discussion-Paper-and-Questionnaire.aspx">proposal</a> for making viability assessments transparent and ensuring developers deliver the maximum amount of affordable housing. At a <a href="https://www.thebureauinvestigates.com/2015/07/07/bureau-to-hold-debate-on-affordable-housing-and-viability-assessments-at-the-commons/">House of Commons meeting</a> last Tuesday, Islington called upon all London boroughs to join them in a pan-London response to the scandal of lost affordable housing. Greenwich council has also said that all viability assessments it receives will be made fully public and Hackney council is looking at much stronger transparency measures. Most surprising of all, Mayor Boris Johnson conceded at a <a href="http://35percent.org/images/GLA_Transcript_ViabilityMQ150715.pdf">Planning Committee meeting</a> on thursday, that viability assessments are part of a <em>&lsquo;dark art&rsquo;</em> and that something needs to be done because <em>&lsquo;developers are getting away with it&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Southwark should take the <a href="http://www.islington.gov.uk/services/planning/planningpol/pol_supplement/Pages/Development-Viability-Discussion-Paper-and-Questionnaire.aspx">Islington Supplementary Planning Document</a> as its benchmark and produce a draft right now for consultation alongside the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/856/planning_policy/3315/the_new_southwark_plan">new Southwark Plan</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/my-conscience-is-clear-council-leader-peter-john-comes-out-fighting-as-heygate-deal-scrutinised/"><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/pjsn.jpg" width="400" height="300"></a>During the interview, Cllr John also defended Southwark council&rsquo;s notorious deal with Lend Lease that slashed <a href="http://35percent.org/affordable-housing/">affordable housing on the new Heygate</a>, reducing the number of social rented units to just 74. He said that we could still get more than was agreed in future detailed planning applications. If this is a sincere promise, the very first thing we need is a new viability assessment. The one just revealed has been shown to favour Lend Lease&rsquo;s profits above all else and was heavily criticised by the District Valuer, whose recommendations Southwark ignored. It is a document which has no credibility and must not be allowed to govern the delivery of affordable housing on Elephant Park over the next ten years.</p>

<h2>Stop Press: We are all on the List</h2>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/page_17.jpg"><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/harrietharman_peniselevator.jpg' width='300' height='500' title='Article in Southwark News - 16th July'><span class='caption-text'>Article in Southwark News - 16th July</span></span></a>Southwark council is due to discuss progress on its plans to build 11,000 council homes on <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/ieListDocuments.aspx?CId=302&amp;MId=5138&amp;Ver=4">Tuesday evening</a> and will be considering a <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s55626/Appendix%204%20Savills%20Evaluation.pdf">report</a> by global property consultant <strong>Savills</strong>. This measures the performance of all Southwark&rsquo;s 406 council estates or <em>&lsquo;asset groups&rsquo;</em> as Savills calls them. Savills does not use Peter John&rsquo;s <a href="http://35percent.org/images/page_17.jpg">&lsquo;penile drugs injection&rsquo;</a> test as a measure of a community&rsquo;s success, but its pseudo-scientific approach is not much better. It lumps together stock condition and maintenance costs with socio-economic measurements such as income levels and educational attainment, to give each council estate a rating.</p>

<p>These two sets of measurements are described as Net Present Value (NPV - crudely: the cost of upkeep against rental income) and <em>&lsquo;Sustainability&rsquo;</em>, which it defines as the <em>&lsquo;social and economic performance of the neighbourhood&rsquo;</em>. The social and economic indicators include, amongst other things how poor people are, how healthy they are, how many are jobless, how many claim benefits and how much crime and anti-social behaviour there is. Sustainability is measured entirely in socio-economic terms; it includes no environmental factors.</p>

<p>All estates then fall into one of four categories: those with <strong>&lsquo;strong NPV&rsquo;</strong> (Net Present Value) and <strong>&lsquo;strong sustainabilty&rsquo;</strong>; those with <strong>&lsquo;weak NPV&rsquo;</strong> and <strong>&lsquo;strong sustainability&rsquo;</strong>; those with <strong>&lsquo;strong NPV&rsquo;</strong> and <strong>&lsquo;weak sustainabilty&rsquo;</strong>; and those with <strong>&lsquo;weak NPV&rsquo;</strong> and <strong>&lsquo;weak sustainability&rsquo;</strong>. A future course of action is prescribed for each:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Rating </th>
<th> Course of Action  </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Above Average NPV &amp; Above Average Sustainability </td>
<td>    Regular Investment </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Below Average NPV &amp; Above Average Sustainability </td>
<td>    Small scale redevelopment or regeneration </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Above Average NPV &amp; Below Average Sustainability </td>
<td>    Asset investment/community initiatives </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Below Average NPV &amp; Below Average Sustainability </td>
<td>    &ldquo;Widest range of options&rdquo; </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p></br>
Those estates that are <strong>above average NPV</strong> and <strong>above average sustainability</strong> can expect <em>&lsquo;regular investment&rsquo;</em>. Those that have <strong>below average NPV</strong> and <strong>strong social sustainability</strong> are prescribed <em>&lsquo;small scale redevelopment/regeneration&rsquo;</em> measures. Those which have <strong>above average NPV</strong> but <strong>weak social sustainability</strong> will require <em>&lsquo;community initiatives alongside asset investment&rsquo;</em>. Finally those which show both <strong>below average NPV</strong> and <strong>weak social sustainability</strong> will be dealt with on the <em>&lsquo;widest range of options possible&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/southwark_estates.png' width='' height='' title='Map showing location of Southwark council estates'><span class='caption-text'>Map showing location of Southwark council estates</span></span>
</br>
</br>
Nobody can argue with investment in council estates and social housing, but the examples of Heygate and Aylesbury give us good reason to worry and Savills&#8217; involvement is not reassuring. They were authors of a <a href="http://www.savills.co.uk/_news/article/72418/175241-0/04/2014/savills-research--london-regeneration-research-proposal">report</a> last year that led to <a href="http://www.standard.co.uk/news/politics/eric-pickles-tear-down-estates-to-boost-poor-innercity-homes-9277330.html">headlines</a> like <em>&ldquo;Eric Pickles: Tear down estates to boost poor inner-city homes&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p>We also note that Cllr Peter John is <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/28/manifesto-for-destruction-of-council-estates/">of a mind</a> that the Heygate and Aylesbury regenerations are a success and holds them up as an example for others to follow.</p>

<p>We should not accept the Savills report as any basis for estate renewal in Southwark. The whole report is set up to lead to conclusions that favour redevelopment and the displacement of local communities.  Refurbishment is not mentioned when it should be the benchmark against which the cost and social impact of any redevelopment should be compared. The Cabinet should thank Savills for its report at its meeting on Tuesday, pay them, sack them and send them on their way. It should instead look to the <a href="http://www.engineering.ucl.ac.uk/engineering-exchange/demolition-refurbishment-social-housing/">work</a> of University College London, which has conducted extensive research on the merits of council estate refurbishment versus demolition.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Completing the Masterplan - Shopping Centre Traders to Be Booted Out]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/12/shopping-centre-and-lcc-redevelopment-proposals/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-12T11:46:55+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/12/shopping-centre-and-lcc-redevelopment-proposals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/LCCAerial.jpg"><img src="http://35percent.org/images/LCCAerial.jpg"></a>
Just as the dust settles on the rubble of the Heygate estate, consultation begins on the demise of another large part of the Elephant &amp; Castle&rsquo;s local community.</p>

<p>Shopping centre owner and property developer Delancey, has publicised proposals for a <a href="http://elephantandcastletowncentre.co.uk/">&lsquo;new town centre&rsquo;</a> and its working assumption is that the shopping centre will be demolished and current traders will just up-sticks and &lsquo;move on&rsquo;.</p>

<p>An <a href="http://elephantandcastletowncentre.co.uk/exhibition.htm">exhibition</a> of the proposals, dubbed <strong>&lsquo;Completing the Masterplan&rsquo;</strong> was held last week. It displayed proposals for a mixed-use development of retail, 1000 new homes and a new campus for the London College of Communication. LCC would move from its present campus, allowing that land to be incorporated as part of the redevelopment scheme.</p>

<p>The proposals will obviously entail the demolition of the entire shopping centre including the <a href="http://coronettheatre.co.uk/home/save-the-coronet/">Coronet theatre</a>, but the exhibition does not dwell on this. In our view, demolition is not a foregone conclusion; at the time Delancey bought the shopping centre, refurbishment was the preferred option and it may look a bit tatty but for a lot of people it still has great social value.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.social-life.co/media/cache/7c/d8/7cd88351c83035bea1af1a55ffe6d81a.jpg"></p>

<p>The exhibition also failed to say what will happen to the current shopkeepers and stallholders, who depend on the centre for their living and provide a valuable service to the local community.</p>

<p>Nor did the exhibition say how much affordable housing there will be. The 1000 new homes will be entirely private rented sector, with maximum 3 year tenancies and none will be for sale, but this does not exempt Delancey from the policy requirement to provide 35% affordable housing, half of which must be social rented.<br/>
<a href="http://35percent.org/images/newhomesforlondoners.png"><img src="http://35percent.org/images/newhomesforlondoners.png"></a></p>

<p>We took up the <a href="http://35percent.org/images/delanceyinvite.pdf">invite</a> and went along to the exhibition to speak to Delancey&rsquo;s representatives, who provided answers to some of our questions; yes, there will be affordable housing but how much hasn&rsquo;t yet been decided; and no, there will be no provision for current shopkeepers, their leases are coming to an end and they will have to move on.</p>

<p>Delancey suggested that some traders may be able to pick up space in its <a href="http://35percent.org/tribeca-square">Tribeca Square</a> development next door, where there should be a small number of retail units, some at reduced rents and earmarked for displaced shopping centre retailers (see section below for more details on this).</p>

<p>This is Delancey&rsquo;s second public consultation event for its shopping centre redevelopment and despite being a statutory part of the planning process, there are three big, basic questions that Delancey has not addressed:</p>

<ol>
<li>Where are the current traders going to go?</li>
<li>How much affordable housing will there be?</li>
<li>What justifies the demolition of the shopping centre?</li>
</ol>


<p>Without public discussion of these questions there can be no meaningful consultation. Southwark council should send Delancey back to the drawing board and tell it to come up with some answers - then real consultation can begin.</p>

<h2>Our Council Leader&rsquo;s view..</h2>

<p>Council leader Peter John gave his opinions on the latest regeneration plans on BBC Radio London 94.9FM last week, where he was ably challenged by former Labour Councillor Piers Corbyn on the merits of Delancey&rsquo;s plans. Councillor John said that he had not yet seen the proposals, but thought that raising the issue of affordable housing was <em>&ldquo;premature&rdquo;</em>. He ducked the interviewer&rsquo;s question of what Southwark would do if the planning application does not come with the required 35% affordable housing; the correct answer would have been <em>&lsquo;we will reject the application&rsquo;</em>, instead he rather feebly said that he would <em>&lsquo;ask for an explanation&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/214183721&amp;color=ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false"></iframe>


<p></br></p>

<p>35% affordable housing still only gets us 175 social rented units in this scheme, a fraction of what we <a href="http://35percent.org/affordable-housing">lost on the Heygate</a>, with a further 175 shared ownership. This is the minimum Southwark&rsquo;s policy requires and it must not accept any viability assessment nonsense from Delancey. We don&rsquo;t want to see it pleading poverty once again, as on its neighbouring <a href="http://35percent.org/tribeca-square">Tribeca Square</a> development where there is no affordable housing of any kind.</p>

<h2>Delancey - a morality tale</h2>

<p>A measure of Delancey&rsquo;s sincerity in suggesting new premises for shopping centre traders at Tribeca Square, can be gauged by the following story:</p>

<p>Back in 2008, when Delancey obtained planning approval for its <a href="http://35percent.org/tribeca-square">Tribeca Square</a> site, it signed a <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!kx6tQZNPCJomdoeiotHphA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">legal agreement</a> with Southwark to provide a number of retail units for traders displaced from the shopping centre, some of which would be affordable<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. This was also one of its justifications for not providing any affordable housing<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.</p>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/tribeca_affordablebusinessunits.png"><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/tribeca_affordablebusinessunits.png' width='' height='' title='Schedule 4B of the Tribeca Square S106 legal agreement'><span class='caption-text'>Schedule 4B of the Tribeca Square S106 legal agreement</span></span></a></p>

<p>By July 2013, former owners of the shopping centre <strong>St Modwen</strong> had shelved demolition plans <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/5215">in favour of refurbishment</a>, so Delancey <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?casereference=13/AP/2302&amp;system=DC">went back</a> to the council and had the legal agreement changed to take these units away from the displaced traders and give them to Sainsburys instead. This was Delancey&rsquo;s <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!1764S3MSO%2biBJUp3XuUgYQ%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">explanation</a>: <em>&ldquo;the s106 agreement was signed at a time when it was expected that the E&amp;C shopping centre would be redeveloped, but we understand that this is no longer the case and question the requirement to offer these retail units to tenants of the centre in any event due to the change in circumstance.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>In November 2013 Delancey bought the shopping centre from <strong>St Modwen</strong> and subsequently <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7258">announced</a> its intention to demolish and redevelop the site. It has not returned to Southwark council and said the units are now needed more than ever by the shopping centre&rsquo;s small shopkeepers, can it please change the agreement again?</p>

<p>Delancey have shown themselves to be slippery customers and they are <a href="http://www.thisismoney.co.uk/money/news/article-1583098/Soros-offers-a-helping-hand-to-Ritblat-junior.html">backed</a> up by big money, including one of the world&rsquo;s richest men, George Soros. They are in this to make even more money, and Southwark council must defend local peoples&#8217; interest much better than it has done so far.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/sainsburys.png' width='' height='' title='The supermarket frontage which should have been small retail units reserved for shopping centre traders'><span class='caption-text'>The supermarket frontage which should have been small retail units reserved for shopping centre traders</span></span><br/>
</br>
</br></p>

<p><strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See pg. 22-25 (Schedule 1 provision 5) of the <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!kx6tQZNPCJomdoeiotHphA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">legal agreement</a> entitled &lsquo;Affordable Business Space&rsquo;.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See paragraph 104 of the planning case officer&rsquo;s <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!vh9yc2npGzJ28c%2fJbhd%2fLA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">report.</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crap Journalism, Crap Deal]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/04/crap-journalism/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-04T08:17:23+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/07/04/crap-journalism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/ViabilityAssessment.png" width="200" height="300">We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/06/25/heygate-viability-assessment-finally-revealed/">blogged</a> last week about the Guardian&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2015/jun/25/london-developers-viability-planning-affordable-social-housing-regeneration-oliver-wainwright">damning article</a>, which revealed how Southwark had rolled over to Lend Lease&rsquo;s demands to reduce affordable housing using highly questionable viability evidence.</p>

<p>Council leader Peter John claimed that the Guardian revelations were <em>&ldquo;wrong&rdquo;</em> and accused it of <em>&ldquo;crap journalism&rdquo;</em>. But after being challenged, neither Councillor John nor any other council member has come forward to set the record straight and say exactly what was inaccurate.</p>

<p>Former Southwark Regeneration chief Councillor Fiona Colley <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/development/council-to-refuse-demands-about-heygate-estate/6528392.article">had her say</a> about the viability assessment a while ago:
</br></p>

<blockquote><p>‘There is nothing I would like more than to publish this document and show the world what a fantastic deal we negotiated for the people of Elephant & Castle. However, we entered into those negotations with Lend Lease on a confidential basis, and I am not willing to break that agreement because a handful of people wrongly think the document contains something sinister.’</p></blockquote>


<p>Now that we can all see <a href="http://35percent.org/collated-viability-assessments/">the document</a>, we all know the deal wasn&rsquo;t fantastic - to paraphrase Peter John, it was crap.</p>

<h2>One Labour head rises above the parapet</h2>

<p>Newly elected Southwark MP Neil Coyle has responded more constructively to the viability revelations. On Monday he asked the Housing Minister Brandon Lewis a <a href="http://www.parliament.uk/business/publications/written-questions-answers-statements/written-question/Commons/2015-06-29/4517/">parliamentary question</a>:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.parliament.uk/business/publications/written-questions-answers-statements/written-question/Commons/2015-06-29/4517/"><img class="center" src="http://35percent.org/images/pq.png"></a></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/NeilCoyle.jpg" width="250" height="200">It&rsquo;s good that Neil&rsquo;s first parliamentary question has taken up this crucial issue and we don&rsquo;t suppose he is surprised by the Housing Minister&rsquo;s non-answer. But we must point out that the viability loophole can be closed by a local authority itself, with a simple change in planning policy. Greenwich council recently announced that it would be <a href="http://www.royalgreenwich.gov.uk/news/article/479/have_your_say_on_landmark_new_council_planning_policy">changing its policy</a> to make all viability assessments public and Islington council has been consulting on similar <a href="http://www.islington.gov.uk/services/planning/planningpol/pol_supplement/Pages/Development-Viability-Discussion-Paper-and-Questionnaire.aspx">policy changes</a>. We hope that Neil&rsquo;s parliamentary question is an indication that Southwark is about to follow Greenwich and Islington&rsquo;s lead; including viability transparency in the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/856/planning_policy/3315/the_new_southwark_plan">draft New Southwark Plan</a> would be a good start.</p>

<p>Neil also made his <a href="http://www.parliamentlive.tv/Event/Index/67063140-a0b0-46b2-abd2-a09b8b3e2cdb">first speech</a> in the House of Commons, during which he <a href="http://www.theyworkforyou.com/debates/?id=2015-07-01a.1521.1&amp;#g1546.0">praised</a> the new park being provided by the Heygate redevelopment. We and many other people in the area want to see this as a truly public park adopted by the council, not the privately owned, <a href="http://35percent.org/sustainable-development/">privately managed model</a> that was approved at planning committee.
</br>
</br></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/facebook.png" width="400" height="350">In a conversation sparked by the Guardian article on Facebook, Neil Coyle also points out that the &lsquo;Heygate saga&rsquo; began under a Lib Dem administration. We feel bound to point out that Neil was <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgListDeclarationsOfInterest.aspx?RPID=0&amp;TAG=0&amp;UID=897&amp;MID=0&amp;AT=&amp;DR=13%2F05%2F2010-24%2F05%2F2011&amp;ACT=Later">Deputy Cabinet member for Estate Regeneration</a> and ward councillor at the Elephant when his administration <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/4712">signed</a> the Heygate deal with Lend Lease.<br/>
</br>
<span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/imageuploads/1280161383_62.49.27.213.jpg' width='300' height='200' title='Council leader Peter John signing deal with Lend Lease (2010)'><span class='caption-text'>Council leader Peter John signing deal with Lend Lease (2010)</span></span><br/>
</br>
The truth is that all major parties have whole-heartedly and uncritically supported the regeneration, so they can share the blame for the Heygate shambles evenly amongst themselves. The task now is to make sure that future developments such as the shopping centre scheme, don&rsquo;t end up the same way.</p>

<p>Over to you Neil..</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Heygate Viability Assessment Finally Revealed]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/06/25/heygate-viability-assessment-finally-revealed/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-25T21:47:03+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/06/25/heygate-viability-assessment-finally-revealed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Tribunalfolderssmall.jpg" width="400" height="300">
After three years of appeals by Southwark Council and its development partner Lend Lease, Adrian Glasspool has finally received the <a href="http://35percent.org/collated-viability-assessments/">viability assessment</a> for the Heygate outline masterplan in response to his <a href="https://www.whatdotheyknow.com/request/viability_assessment_for_plannin?unfold=1">May 2012 FOI/EIR request</a>. Southwark had initially rejected the request and appealed after his subsequent complaint was <a href="http://ico.org.uk/~/media/documents/decisionnotices/2013/fer_0461281.ashx">upheld</a> by the Information Commissioner. A long battle through the Tribunal system then culminated in a 6 day <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/02/11/heygate-tribunal-hearing-extended/">hearing</a> in February last year, followed by a <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/FirstTierDecisionHeygate.pdf">decision notice</a> directing Southwark to release the assessment minus some of its financial modelling figures<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Following a further dispute about exactly which figures could be withheld, the Tribunal resumed and issued a <a href="http://www.informationtribunal.gov.uk/DBFiles/Decision/i1505/London%20Borough%20of%20Southwark%20EA.2013.0162%20%2810.3.15%29%202nd%20Decision.pdf">final decision</a> in March this year. The viability assessment was then received in April and after examination by sympathetic industry experts we can now disclose our findings. The Heygate tribunal case has since triggered decisions to disclose viability information for other large regeneration schemes including <a href="http://ico.org.uk/~/media/documents/decisionnotices/2013/fer_0491596.ashx">Earls Court regeneration</a> and <a href="http://ico.org.uk/~/media/documents/decisionnotices/2014/fer_0524770.pdf">Greenwich Peninsula</a>.</p>

<p>As well as a copy of the disclosed viability assessment, the 35% campaign has also obtained via FOI a (heavily redacted) <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/DVSreport_HeygateOutline.pdf">copy</a> of the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/district-valuer-services-dvs/about">District Valuer Service</a>(DVS) appraisal of the viability assessment, commissioned by Southwark council.</p>

<h2>First impressions</h2>

<h3>This is a profitability assessment- not a viability assessment</h3>

<p>Lend Lease commissioned Savills to produce the viability assessment and the first thing that becomes clear from the disclosed information is that <strong>unviable doesn&rsquo;t mean unprofitable.</strong> Savills tested to see how the development could provide an &lsquo;acceptable&rsquo; level of developer&rsquo;s return for Lend Lease (i.e. profit margin) - and set the level of affordable housing accordingly.</p>

<h3>25% is deemed the acceptable level of profit</h3>

<p>Savills settled on 25% as the acceptable level of profit and the minimum needed to test the viability of the scheme - i.e. the &lsquo;viability benchmark&rsquo;.</p>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/HeygateViabilityAssessment_MainReport.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/viabilitybenchmark.png"></a></p>

<p>But no explanation is given as to why 25% profit was used as the viability benchmark, rather than the 20% Lend Lease had agreed contractually with Southwark in its Partnership Agreement<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> (Southwark is a development partner in this scheme); all that Savills says is this:</p>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/HeygateViabilityAssessment_MainReport.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/savillsdr.png"></a></p>

<p>In his report on the viability assessment, the District Valuer was clearly not impressed with this explanation. <a href="http://35percent.org/images/DVSreport_HeygateOutline.pdf"><em>&ldquo;I do not adopt the profit benchmark that Savills have adopted..&rdquo;</em></a>(page 30, para. 2)</p>

<p>He goes on to say:</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/DVSreport_HeygateOutline.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/DVSacceptablereturn.png"></a></p>

<p>Nonetheless, Southwark ignored his advice and accepted the 25% figure (equivalent to approx £300m<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>) as the viability benchmark in calculating the affordable housing offer. It&rsquo;s important to note that as well as the viability assessment, <em>&ldquo;the Council keeps DVS&rsquo;s report confidential also&rdquo;</em><sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>; it is not shown to planning committee councillors and there is nothing obliging the council&rsquo;s planning officers to implement, or act upon any of the District Valuer&rsquo;s recommendations.</p>

<p>The 25% required profit figure in the viability assessment serves to inflate the projected development costs and allow the consequent reduction of affordable housing. In the event, the number of social rented units was reduced from the 432<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> required by policy <a href="http://35percent.org/affordable-housing">to just 74</a>, and the total number of <a href="http://www.thelondoneconomic.com/2015/03/17/trafalgar-place-a-damning-indictment-of-affordable-housing-in-london/">&lsquo;affordable&rsquo;</a> homes from 35% to 25% (a reduction in itself of £90m worth of affordable housing<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>).</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!cvj%2buF2v8VRqQhUGaBSuKw%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/UpdatedAHStatement.png' width='' height='' title='Lend Lease's final proposed tenure mix for the Heygate masterplan site'><span class='caption-text'>Lend Lease&rsquo;s final proposed tenure mix for the Heygate masterplan site</span></span></a></p>

<p>During the Tribunal hearing, council officers acknowledged that they did not actually see the viability assessment themselves, but depended entirely upon the District Valuer. However, the District Valuer said that the 25% profit margin was too high and well above the 15% average. So with this in mind and, in the knowledge that the Partnership Agreement had stipulated a lower figure (20%), why did Southwark continue to allow the 25% to be used as the viability benchmark?</p>

<h3>Residential sales prices were grossly underestimated</h3>

<p>An important element of the viability assessment is the anticipated sales prices of the new homes. If this is underestimated it reduces the projected profitability of the development and the amount of money available for affordable housing. The viability assessment estimated that Lend Lease&rsquo;s new flats would sell for an average of £600 per sqft<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" rel="footnote">7</a></sup>.</p>

<p>The District Valuer flagged this up and expressed concern that Lend Lease&rsquo;s sales projections were <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Southwark-Simon-Bevan.pdf"><em>&ldquo;too conservative&rdquo;</em></a>(para. 81). He explained that <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/DVSreport_HeygateOutline.pdf"><em>&ldquo;much of the local sales evidence is not comparable to what is proposed&rdquo;</em> and <em>&ldquo;does not give an idea of what may be achieved following redevelopment.&rdquo;</em></a>(page 40)</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/88_LangdaleClose_SE17.JPG' width='400' height='300' title='88 Langdale Close on the Pelier estate'><span class='caption-text'>88 Langdale Close on the Pelier estate</span></span>The local &lsquo;comparable&rsquo; sales evidence provided in <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Appendix12.pdf">appendix 12</a> of the viability assessment, shows just how poor the supporting evidence is. Property number 24 on the comparables list is this 2-bed ex-council flat on the council&rsquo;s Pelier estate straddling the Walworth/Camberwell borders; a long way from the 35-storey, concierge-serviced luxury towers Lend Lease is building up at the Elephant.</p>

<p>A quick trip to Lend Lease&rsquo;s marketing showroom at the Elephant shows that its <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/WestGrovePrices.pdf">price list</a> for <a href="http://www.elephantpark.co.uk/news-and-editorial/news/west-grove-film-premiere">&lsquo;West Grove&rsquo;</a> (the latest phase to go on sale) is advertising flats for sale at an average of £1,012 per sqft - i.e. £400 per sqft more than Lend Lease&rsquo;s viability assessment estimate.</p>

<h3>Why no review mechanism?</h3>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/LLWestGrove.PNG"><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/LLWestGrove.PNG" width="400" height="300"></a>As a result of his concerns about the pessimistic sales projections, the District Valuer recommended that a &lsquo;review mechanism&rsquo; be made a condition of planning consent. He recognised that even a small increase in the sales values given could have a <a href="http://35percent.org/images/DVSreport_HeygateOutline.pdf"><em>&ldquo;significant impact on the profitability and this underlines the need to have a review mechanism.&rdquo;</em></a>(page 39, para. h).</p>

<p>Southwark however, did not think a review mechanism was worth their while; the case officer&rsquo;s <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!hgyBVuEH%2b8BxXry2bGRAtA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">report</a> for the masterplan application said:</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!hgyBVuEH%2b8BxXry2bGRAtA%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><em>&ldquo;Given that the development is phased and extends over a prolonged period, it would normally be expected that the viability situation should be reviewed, so that in the event of an economic upturn an increased level of affordable housing could be secured. It should however be noted that the indicative viable level of 9.4%, indicates that a very significant economic upturn would be required in order to bring the viability to a level of affordable housing above the 25% proposed in this application. Hence it is unlikely (in light of the current viability gap) that a review would secure any increase in the quantum of affordable housing that could be supported by the scheme.&rdquo;</em></a>  (paras. 153-154)</p>

<p>Southwark council acknowledges that it did not have the expertise nor the experience to appraise the viability assessment. Southwark&rsquo;s Director of Planning said in <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Southwark-Simon-Bevan.pdf">evidence</a> given at the Tribunal that <em>&ldquo;None of the council&rsquo;s planning officers has the expertise to analyse a viability assessment. The council&rsquo;s planning officers refer all viability assessments, without exception, either to the District Valuer Service, or to the council&rsquo;s internal Property Valuation team.&rdquo;</em>(para 41).</p>

<p>This is why it had to send the viability assessment to the District Valuer Service. It had so little confidence in its own ability to understand the assessment that it did not even open the viability assessment&rsquo;s critical financial model:</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Southwark-Simon-Bevan.pdf"><em>&ldquo;The [financial] model could not be opened as the file was incompatible with the Council&rsquo;s computer systems.&rdquo;</em></a>(para. 73)</p>

<p>Nonetheless, despite being so dependent on the District Valuer, Southwark ignored his criticism of the profit level and ignored his recommendation that there should be a review mechanism. As a result Southwark has lost 358 social rented homes, while Lend Lease stands to make whacking profits.</p>

<h2>&lsquo;Something Sinister&rsquo; or &lsquo;crap journalism&rsquo;?</h2>

<p>Southwark has spent 3 years and a significant amount of taxpayer&rsquo;s money on lawyers, arguing that local people don’t have the right to see documents that their elected councillors had based important planning decisions on.</p>

<p>Southwark&rsquo;s regeneration boss justified the council&rsquo;s position by <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/development/council-to-refuse-demands-about-heygate-estate/6528392.article">claiming</a> that it had <em>&ldquo;There is nothing I would like more than to publish this document and show the world what a fantastic deal we negotiated for the people of Elephant &amp; Castle. However, we entered into negotiations with Lend Lease on a confidential basis, and I am not willing to break that agreement because a handful of people wrongly think the document contains something sinister.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>We have published the <a href="http://35percent.org/collated-viability-assessments/">disclosed viability assessment</a> on our website, and will be further exploring the information it contains in a series of blog posts to follow. In the meantime Southwark has got some serious questions to answer. As a result of the findings in a similar Tribunal case in Greenwich Peninsula, <a href="https://www.thebureauinvestigates.com/2015/05/26/dismay-doesnt-do-it-justice-how-a-secret-system-was-used-to-axe-hundreds-of-affordable-homes-on-britains-most-iconic-construction-site/">media pressure</a> forced Greenwich Council to change its policy and make all viability assessments public by default. Southwark on the other hand has shown no such humility; in response to the <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2015/jun/25/london-developers-viability-planning-affordable-social-housing-regeneration-oliver-wainwright">Guardian&rsquo;s exclusive story</a> on our findings, council leader Peter John claimed that the article was <em>&ldquo;wrong&rdquo;</em> and accused the Guardian of <em>&ldquo;crap journalism&rdquo;</em>. Guardian journalist Olly Wainwright then responded by inviting Councillor John to <em>&ldquo;get in touch if you think there are mistakes&rdquo;</em>, to which he replied <em>&ldquo;Corrected your articles previously - can&rsquo;t do it every time.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/ollywainwright/status/614174166045052928"><img src="http://35percent.org/images/PJ_HeygateViabilityResponse.png"></a></p>

<p>We have been campaigning for several years now around the Elephant &amp; Castle regeneration, much of which has involved trying to initiate some kind of reasoned debate around planning decisions affecting local people. We have made a point of ensuring that our criticisms are grounded in fact and supported by evidence (even when information has not been made readily available). To date these criticisms have been largely ignored by Southwark council. However, this time the claims are relatively serious and supported by detailed information in the disclosed viability assessment that Councillor John has spent 3 years fighting to conceal. Rather than claiming the assertions are simply <em>&ldquo;wrong&rdquo;</em> or <em>&ldquo;crap journalism&rdquo;</em>, we invite Councillor John to make a more dignified response. Beyond correcting what he believes is inaccurate, we invite him to answer two very simple questions:</p>

<ul>
<li>Why did the Council fail to follow the District Valuer&rsquo;s recommendation of imposing a viability review mechanism, linked to the delivery of the phased development over its eleven year construction period?</li>
<li>Why did the Council allow Lend Lease&rsquo;s viability assessment to assume a profit margin benchmark 5% higher than had been agreed contractually? (the 5% representing approximately £50m that could have been spent on affordable housing).</li>
</ul>


<p>The comments section at the bottom of this blog post is enabled and ready to use. Over to you Councillor John?..</p>

<p></br>
<strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>The Tribunal ruled that Lend Lease could withold its financial model in appendix 22 of the viability assessment and commercial information relating to Lend Lease&rsquo;s negotiations with other businesses - see paras 55 &amp; 56 of the <a href="http://heygatewashome.org/img/FirstTierDecisionHeygate.pdf">decision notice</a> respectively.  <a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See page 83 of the leaked <a href="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf">Regeneration Agreement</a>  <a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See column &lsquo;Scheme Profit&rsquo; on lower section of page 36 of the <a href="http://35percent.org/images/DVSreport_HeygateOutline.pdf">District Valuer&rsquo;s report</a>.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>See paragraph 49 of the Director of Planning&rsquo;s <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Southwark-Simon-Bevan.pdf">Tribunal evidence.</a><a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>Southwark&rsquo;s policy requires 35% affordable housing, 50% of which must be social rented (i.e. 17.5% of the total number of new Heygate homes (2,469) = 432).<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>Total number of habitable rooms in the Heygate masterplan application was 9052. The viability assessment justified the 10% reduction in affordable housing - 10% of 9052 is 905 habitable rooms; <a href="http://35percent.org/images/affordablehousingspg.pdf">Southwark&rsquo;s tariff</a> for in-lieu affordable housing payments at the Elephant is £100,000 per habitable room; £100,000 X 905 = £90.5m.  <a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:7">
<p>See paragraph 9.1.1.4 of the <a href="http://35percent.org/images/HeygateViabilityAssessment_MainReport.pdf">main viability assessment report</a> and <a href="http://35percent.org/images/Appendix12.pdf">Appendix 12</a>.<a href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[£63m Public Money to Build 274 Private Homes]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/06/19/housing-minister-visits-new-heygate/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/06/19/housing-minister-visits-new-heygate</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://i11.tinypic.com/49iebk5.jpg' width='300' height='500' title='CGI of London 360 Tower'><span class='caption-text'>CGI of London 360 Tower</span></span> Tory Housing Minister Brandon Lewis has <a href="http://www.egi.co.uk/news/lewis-announces-252m-prs-boost/">announced</a> the third round of successful bidders in the government&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/1000-new-homes-for-private-rent-in-london">Build to Rent fund</a>.</p>

<p>&lsquo;Build to rent&rsquo; or PRS (Private Rented Sector) funding is the Conservative government&rsquo;s answer to the housing crisis, with which it subsidises the building of homes for private rent, but without imposing constraints on how much those rents will be. Last year we <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/07/19/community-infrastructure-levy/">reported</a> that Delancey had let slip that its new PRS homes at the Elephant were expected to fetch on average £375pw for 1-bed and £500pw for a 2-bed.</p>

<p>One of the successful bidders this time round was the Richard Rogers designed, 44-storey <a href="http://35percent.org/london-360-tower">London 360 Tower</a>, which <a href="http://www.london.gov.uk/moderngov/documents/s45702/06%20Programmes%20delegated%20to%20HCA.rtf">received £45m</a> funding for 274 new PRS homes on the site of the former London Park Hotel at Newington Butts. We <a href="http://35percent.org/london-360-tower/">blogged previously</a> about the &lsquo;dreadful irony&rsquo; of this site being bought (under threat of compulsory purchase) by the government&rsquo;s regeneration agency with £18m of public money, specifically for the purpose of building affordable housing. Now we are seeing an additional £45m being poured into this development which won&rsquo;t contain a single affordable or social rented home.</p>

<p>In summary, £63m of public funds is being spent to acquire and develop a 44-storey tower comprising what is openly <a href="http://residential.jll.co.uk/en-gb/property-search/property-details.aspx?t=c&amp;id=JLLATC41432">described</a> by the scheme&rsquo;s promoters as <strong>&ldquo;274 private homes&rdquo;</strong>. That&rsquo;s a cost of £230k per home when the money could clearly be better spent elsewhere; as we have <a href="http://35percent.org/aylesbury-estate/">shown</a>, council homes on the Aylesbury estate could be brought up to Decent Homes Standard for a sum of just £20k per dwelling.</p>

<p>Most housing associations have snubbed the &lsquo;build to rent&rsquo; funding on the grounds that it doesn&rsquo;t create housing affordable for those in need. As usual, Notting Hill Housing saw pound signs and was one of the first to apply. So far it has been <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/build-to-rent-round-1-allocations/build-to-rent-round-1-signed-contracts">allocated</a> £17m in the first round of funding to build 181 PRS homes in London. We don&rsquo;t know how many of these will be on the new Aylesbury, but we do now know that despite its insistence that there would be no &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; homes on the redeveloped estate, the Mayor has now <a href="http://questions.london.gov.uk/QuestionSearch/searchclient/questions/question_282124">confirmed</a> that he has allocated funding for at least 450 new homes on the Aylesbury at - guess what? affordable rent.</p>

<h2>Heygate - a Tory &amp; Labour blueprint</h2>

<p><a href="http://twitter.com/ElephantParkLDN/status/606461178991255552/photo/1"><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/brandonlewis_trafalgarplace.jpg' width='400' height='350' title='Housing Minister tours new Heygate'><span class='caption-text'>Housing Minister tours new Heygate</span></span></a>
We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/28/manifesto-for-destruction-of-council-estates/">blogged in February</a> about Labour Lord Adonis&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/8192">visit to the Elephant &amp; Castle</a> and his <a href="http://www.ippr.org/publications/city-villages-more-homes-better-communities">manifesto</a> for the destruction of the council estates. At the beginning of the month Housing Minister Brandon Lewis <a href="https://twitter.com/ElephantParkLDN/status/606512000261345280">visited phase one of the redeveloped Heygate</a> and made a <a href="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/e764af1c-0f6a-11e5-897e-00144feabdc0.html">similar call</a>, in what appears to be a race to the bottom in UK housing policy.</p>

<p>In his <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/brandon-lewis-speaks-at-the-london-real-estate-forum">speech</a> at the <a href="http://www.lref.co.uk/">London Real Estate Forum</a> on 11th June, Brandon Lewis vowed to <em>&ldquo;regenerate those inner city estates that are dominated by the high-rise blocks of the 1960s and 70s&rdquo;</em> and claimed that <em>&ldquo;completely rebuilding these estates will provide more homes and commercial space using the same amount of land.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>He referred to a report he <a href="http://www.savills.co.uk/_news/article/72418/175241-0/04/2014/savills-research--london-regeneration-research-proposal">commissioned</a> last year from Savills, which claims that <em>&ldquo;rediscovering just half of this former housing capacity would supply London’s expected housing needs for the next 17 years.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/revitalising.png" width="350" height="350">We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/08/southwark-fails-to-deliver/">blogged</a> last year about Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/download/3934/the_new_southwark_plan">draft new planning policy</a>, which praises the Heygate regeneration and proposes to roll out similar schemes across the borough.
We also <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">wrote</a> about the assessment Southwark had <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SNhat.pdf">commissioned</a> from Savills, to establish which of its council estates were no longer &lsquo;viable&rsquo;. Rumour has it that this assessment is now complete but the results have not been published. As soon as this &lsquo;disposals list&rsquo; is made public, we&rsquo;ll be looking to explain to tenants &amp; residents groups affected exactly what regeneration means.<br/>
</br></p>

<h2>Urban Parsley</h2>

<p>Meanwhile council leader Peter John was also being led by Lend Lease on a tour of <a href="http://trafalgarplace.com/">&lsquo;Trafalgar Place&rsquo;</a> (phase one of the redeveloped Heygate nearing completion). Cllr John was particularly excited about the carrots growing in the new &lsquo;community garden&rsquo;, which comes with a ready-grown vegetable patch.<br/>
<a href="https://twitter.com/peterjohn6/status/610408022645587968/photo/1"><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://35percent.org/images/communitycarrots.jpg' width='' height='' title='Council leader Peter John tweets about carrots on redeveloped Heygate'><span class='caption-text'>Council leader Peter John tweets about carrots on redeveloped Heygate</span></span></a><br/>
It was left to us to point out that the carrots are corporate carrots, not communal carrots, as the &lsquo;community garden&rsquo; is situated in a raised courtyard above the parking lobby with zero public access; and, for the record, just <a href="http://35percent.org/affordable-housing/">8 of the 235 new homes</a> in this first phase of the redeveloped Heygate are going to be social rented homes. There will be a handful &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; homes and a number of shared ownership flats (<a href="http://35percent.org/images/LQPriceList.pdf">if you earn an income of £57k</a>).<br/>
On a site that was <a href="http://35percent.org/heygate-regeneration-faq/">sold at a loss</a> to developers and home to an <a href="http://heygatewashome.org">established community</a> now <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2013/06/08/the-heygate-diaspora/">scattered to the wind</a>, the carrots are a perfect example of what has been <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/architecture-design-blog/2015/apr/16/the-great-garden-swindle-how-developers-are-hiding-behind-shrubbery">termed</a> <strong>&lsquo;urban parsley&rsquo;</strong>: <em>&lsquo;a green garnish used as a decoy to distract from what’s really going on&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<h2>Urban Practitioners</h2>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='http://action.labour.org.uk/page/-/site/img/people/headshots/helen%20hayes.jpg' width='' height='' title='New Southwark Labour MP Helen Hayes'><span class='caption-text'>New Southwark Labour MP Helen Hayes</span></span>One of our new Southwark MPs Helen Hayes appeared in an <a href="http://www.private-eye.co.uk/hp-sauce">article</a> in Private Eye last week. Helen took over from Tessa Jowell as MP for Dulwich and West Norwood earlier this year, but has been a Southwark councillor since 2010. The Eye took issue with her simultaneous role as boss of an architecture firm, which has not only been writing up council planning policy, but was also <a href="http://m.building.co.uk/lend-lease-wins-%C2%A315bn-regeneration-of-elephant-and-castle/3092038.article">part of the Lend Lease consortium</a> that had won the bid for the Elephant &amp; Castle regeneration and has <a href="http://www.architectsjournal.co.uk/news/allies-and-morrison-wins-go-ahead-for-first-private-homes-on-olympic-park/8656074.article">contracts</a> with Lend Lease elsewhere. Her firm has also been involved in a number of controversial developments in the borough, including the Ministry of Sound (<a href="http://35percent.org/eileen-house">Eileen House</a>) development and the <a href="http://www.alliesandmorrison.com/project/aylesbury-academy/">Aylesbury estate regeneration</a>.</p>

<h2>Urban Campaigners</h2>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='https://i-d-images.vice.com/images/articles/meta/2015/06/19/untitled-article-1434727223.jpg?crop=1xw:0.8450292397660819xh;0xw,0.005847953216374269xh&resize=1200:*&output-format=image/jpeg&output-quality=90' width='' height='' title='Marching for homes - former investment banker and council regeneration boss Fiona Colley - bottom right'><span class='caption-text'>Marching for homes - former investment banker and council regeneration boss Fiona Colley - bottom right</span></span>
Our very own <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=116">Cllr Fiona Colley</a> was spotted campaigning for more affordable homes and against austerity in <a href="https://i-d.vice.com/en_gb/article/why-did-the-daily-mail-paint-this-anti-austerity-campaigner-as-a-violent-extremist">this vice article</a>. After selling off the Heygate and Aylesbury, former investment banker Cllr Colley stepped down from her role as <strong>Cabinet member for Regeneration</strong> last year, to take up her new role as <strong>Cabinet member for Finance, Modernisation and Performance</strong>. We wonder whether she has had a change of heart, or - having snapped up two new-build flats in the Canada Water regeneration<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> - the homes she is marching for are of a different tenure to those her fellow marchers have in mind..</p>

<h2>Aylesbury CPO Public Inquiry</h2>

<p>A date has been set for the Aylesbury CPO Inquiry to resume. The Inquiry will reconvene on Tuesday October 13th back at the Den. It is scheduled to last for two days and will hear further arguments relating to Human Rights, which the council was unable to respond to during the last hearing. This time the objectors have instructed counsel and will be represented at the hearing by a barrister from <a href="http://landmarkchambers.co.uk">Landmark Chambers</a>.</p>

<p></br>
</br>
<strong>Footnotes:</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>On 6th Jan 1999 Fiona Colley purchased flat 8, Yew House, 2 Woodlands Crescent SE16 6YH (Canada Water regeneration) off-plan for £159,000 and then sold it post-construction on 31st July 2003 for £271,000. On Sept 3rd 2003, she purchased flat 8, Rowan House, 3 Woodlands Crescent SE16 6YF (Canada Water regeneration) for £390,000 and then sold it in May 20th 2011 for £610,000. <a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury CPO Inquiry - Extra Time]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/16/aylesbury-cpo-inquiry-extra-time/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-16T13:54:39+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/16/aylesbury-cpo-inquiry-extra-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://www.eastlondonlines.co.uk/ell_wp/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/alanfootballclub.jpg" width="300" height="200">The Aylesury CPO Inquiry resumed back at the Den on Tuesday, but by the end of day the Inspector had decided extra time was needed. She accepted the objectors&#8217; argument that there were still legal questions to be answered, among others about the absence of a successful ballot result in favour of demolition. She also agreed that objectors needed more time to get legal assistance and that it will probably be autumn before the the inquiry resumes.  We understand that the leaseholders have since instructed Landmark Chambers to act on their behalf.</p>

<p>Tuesday&rsquo;s hearing returned to the issue of the Bermondsey Spa regeneration and the switch of tenures from social rent to affordable rent. Objectors had raised questions about this at the first hearing and in their <a href="http://35percent.org/images/Objectors_OpeningSubmissions_andAppendices.pdf">opening submission</a>, but were told that Southwark and Notting Hill Housing needed time to look into the details before answering questions.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/theexchange.jpg' width='' height='' title='Notting Hill's Bermondsey Spa regeneration'><span class='caption-text'>Notting Hill&rsquo;s Bermondsey Spa regeneration</span></span></p>

<p>On being questioned again, this time representatives from the council and Notting Hill both said they could not comment because the matter was in the hands of their respective legal departments.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, Southwark did table two &lsquo;explanatory notes&rsquo; agreed with Notting Hill about the Bermondsey Spa regeneration and four other developments, which did shed some further light on the matter. The <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/CPO_ExplanatoryNote27April2015.pdf">first</a> of these shows that wholesale changes to the tenure mix had been made post approval on all four developments and that while there was an overall increase in affordable housing of 260 units, there was a net loss in <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/ObjectorsReplyToExplantoryNote1.pdf">social rented housing of 15 homes</a>. Also in each case a broadly policy-compliant scheme was changed after planning approval to become wildly non-compliant.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/ExplanatoryNote1.png' width='' height='' title='The Council's first 'explanatory note' tabled on day 4 of the Inquiry'><span class='caption-text'>The Council&rsquo;s first &lsquo;explanatory note&rsquo; tabled on day 4 of the Inquiry</span></span></p>

<p>The <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/CPO_ExplanatoryNote12May2015.pdf">second note</a> was a strictly legal description of how in each case these changes could be justified. It does not address any of the issues about policy compliance, the correct mix of social and intermediate housing, or why the planning committee is left entirely in ignorance of the significant tenure changes being made post approval.</p>

<p>In the second note Southwark also confirmed that the definition of affordable rent used in the legal agreements <em>&ldquo;can be interpreted flexibly enough to allow them to be delivered as social rented units&rdquo;</em>. However, Notting Hill doesn&rsquo;t agree - as the note says: <em>&ldquo;It is not yet clear whether the parties agree on the correct interpretation.&rdquo;</em> Southwark has therefore <em>&ldquo;sought advice from the council&rsquo;s legal department&rdquo;</em> and Notting Hill is also <em>&ldquo;seeking advice in relation to the wording of the agreement&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/ExplanatoryNote2.png' width='' height='' title='The Council's second 'explanatory note' tabled on day 5 of the Inquiry'><span class='caption-text'>The Council&rsquo;s second &lsquo;explanatory note&rsquo; tabled on day 5 of the Inquiry</span></span></p>

<p>The problem for Notting Hill and Southwark Council is that they have been found out. By using the same legal definition for both affordable rent and social rent, they can claim to be delivering social rented housing when in actual fact they are delivering affordable rent. The question now is who is going to shoulder the blame and whether or not the affordable rented units at Bermondsey Spa (and maybe elsewhere?) will be converted to social rent.</p>

<p>If these differences cannot be resolved amicably Southwark has the option of enforcing its own interpretation, in which case Notting Hill could respond via the courts. Notting Hill Housing is Southwark&rsquo;s development partner on the Aylesbury and its largest development partner in the borough. So the Council needs to lay down the law and make sure that Notting Hill delivers the social rented homes that the borough so desperately needs, not some bogus &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; or &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; by the back door.</p>

<p><strong>Postscript Update 22/5/15</strong>
Southwark News has picked up on our tenure switch story and published an <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/news/southwark-council-probes-44-missing-social-homes/">article</a> with quotes from Cllr Williams, claiming that the council is <em>&ldquo;looking into the rent levels proposed at Bermondsey Spa&rdquo;</em> and that <em>&ldquo;appropriate action&rdquo;</em> will be taken. The article also confirms that Notting Hill has built a total of 1,442 homes in Southwark and that it has another 5,489 in the pipeline.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury CPO Inquiry - Into the Lion's Den]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/02/aylesbury-estate-compulsory-purchase-order-public-inquiry/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-02T09:10:32+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/05/02/aylesbury-estate-compulsory-purchase-order-public-inquiry</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/CDsUkrnW0AEP5X-.jpg" width="400" height="300">The Public Inquiry into the Aylesbury Compulsory Purchase Order was adjourned on Friday (until 12th May), after four days of sharp argument between Southwark Council and objectors to the order. This is the third CPO Southwark has sought in relation to the Aylesbury regeneration and we can expect many more as it seeks to get rid of leaseholders who do not accept its derisory compensation offers.</p>

<p>The Inquiry was conducted by government Inspector Leslie Coffey and was held in Arry&rsquo;s Bar at Millwall Football ground. The Inquiry had been moved to the Den to be better able to control feared protests from angry estate residents.</p>

<h2>Them and Us</h2>

<p>Southwark Council&rsquo;s large team of officers were led by barrister <a href="http://www.chambersandpartners.com/uk-bar/person/224510/melissa-murphy">Melissa Murphy</a>, whose recent work includes acting for Basildon council in the eviction of the Dale Farm gypsy and traveller site.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.peoplesrepublicofsouthwark.co.uk/images/stories/news/2804201502.jpg" width="410" height="300">Objectors included representatives from the <a href="https://halag.wordpress.com/">Aylesbury Leaseholders Action Group</a>, the 35% Campaign and former local Tory Councillor Toby Eckersley.
Over the first two days council regeneration officers detailed the background and benefits of new development with much reference to the key planning document, the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200211/area_action_plans/1327/aylesbury_area_action_plan">Aylesbury Area Action Plan</a> (AAAP) of 2009, according to which the regeneration will provide a <em>&lsquo;mixed community&rsquo;</em> comprising about 3,500 homes of great design standards with new green spaces.</p>

<h2>Social rent or not social rent?</h2>

<p>Also present was Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s Head of Regeneration, Rosemary Houseman. Ms Houseman was closely questioned by Objectors about the funding arrangements for the scheme. Under cross examination Ms Housman reluctantly admitted that the 1670 &lsquo;target rented&rsquo; Aylesbury homes that Notting Hill had received funding for under the <a href="https://www.london.gov.uk/priorities/housing-land/increasing-housing-supply/mayor-housing-covenant-2015-2018">Mayor&rsquo;s 2015-18 MHC programme</a>, were referred to in the funding allocation as affordable rent - not social rent.</p>

<h2>Non answers</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/manorplace_sr.png" width="300" height="500">Notting Hill Housing and Southwark Council were also cross examined by objectors about the <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing/">Bermondsey Spa S106 fiasco</a>, where Notting Hill had promised social rented housing but delivered affordable rent instead. Objectors raised further concerns about tenure switching at other Notting Hill developments including <a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk">Manor Place depot</a>, where <a href="http://www.manorplacedepot.co.uk/Manor-Place-Exhibition-Banners.pdf">pre-planning consultation documents</a> described <em>&ldquo;9 Social Rent Family Homes&rdquo;</em>, which subsequently disappeared into <em>&ldquo;Affordable Rent&rdquo;</em> homes when the planning application was submitted.</p>

<p>No clear answers to these questions were forthcoming - council and Notting Hill witnesses repeatedly argued that they didn&rsquo;t have the details of the schemes before them and thus couldn&rsquo;t comment. Eventually an explanatory note was promised and this arrived at 2pm of what was to be the final day of the Inquiry. These points will be taken up when the Inquiry resumes next week and we will be addressing this in our next blog.</p>

<h2>The cost</h2>

<p>Southwark Council did <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Email14April2015_KReed.pdf">confirm</a> that it had spent a staggering £46.8m on the Aylesbury regeneration scheme to date. This comprised total capital account costs of £32.1m (demolition &amp; acquisiton) and revenue account costs amounting to £14.7m (Management &amp; Administration, Master-planning, Communications, PFI, Development Partner Procurement, Feasibility Studies etc).</p>

<p>Southwark Council also <a href="http://35percent.org/images/PMcGreal_Email28April2015.pdf">confirmed</a> that some of its officers valuing leaseholders&#8217; homes were not fully qualified or RICS registered. Leaseholders had <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/ALAG_RICS.pdf">complained to RICS</a> about officers conducting the valuations, but because neither the officers in question or Southwark Council were RICS registered, they were unable to pursue the matter.</p>

<h2>&lsquo;Sham&rsquo; consultations and legal queries</h2>

<p>On the objectors&#8217; side Toby Eckersley called the consultation for the AAAP a &lsquo;sham&rsquo;. He supported his claim by reference to the evidence base supporting the council&rsquo;s decision making process. He took the Inquiry to paragraph 3.1.4 of the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/2938/consultation_report_main_report-appendix_6"><em>&ldquo;Consultation report for the Aylesbury Area Action Plan&rdquo;</em></a>, which shows that Southwark received just 33 written representations in response to its consultation on the question of demolition or refurbishment, of which only 5 supported demolition while 9 supported refurbishment (the estate is home to over 7,500 people).</p>

<p>Toby also raised several interesting legal points around whether Southwark had actually fulfilled all the procedural conditions needed to go ahead with the regeneration. He argued that several provisions of the Housing Act 1985 could be open to the interpretation that a ballot is required for a scheme to demolish an estate, especially when the scheme provides for secure tenants to be moved to a new tenancy on the site with a registered provider (i.e. stock transfer). He referred the Inquiry to the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/8289/1293538.pdf">Statutory Guidance on schedule 3A</a> and also to section 105 of the Act, which expressly mentions demolition as a housing management matter which, in principle, should be consulted on. The council responded that a ballot with <strong>YES</strong> vote wasn&rsquo;t necessary because its deal with Notting Hill wasn&rsquo;t a stock transfer; i.e. they were booting residents out before handing the buildings over to Notting Hill to demolish. The Inspector granted an adjournment that would allow objectors time to consider and reply to Southwark&rsquo;s response.</p>

<h2>Ms Murphy&rsquo;s law</h2>

<p>Objectors had several expert witnesses to support their case; <a href="https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=BJCAM61">Dr Ben Campkin</a> of the UCL Bartlett School of Architecture argued that the unjustified negative image of the estate is the thread which underlies ideas about its demolition and regeneration. He gave a presentation based on his book <a href="https://www.bartlett.ucl.ac.uk/architecture/events/remaking-london-event">&lsquo;Remaking London&rsquo;</a> and was subsequently subjected to a fierce cross-examination by Ms Murphy. She took Dr Campkin to task for not being familiar with the Aylesbury Area Action Plan, one of the many large documents within the Inquiry&rsquo;s four-volume core bundle. Amongst other points she also referred to a previous Inspector&rsquo;s <em>&lsquo;educated judgement&rsquo;</em> that the Aylesbury estate was <em>&ldquo;visually unattractive&rdquo;</em>, which drew laughter from the (largely uneducated) public present .</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Conisbee_Nov2004Figures.png"><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/Conisbee_Nov2004Figures.png" width="400" height="300"></a>Dr <a href="http://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=CACRA07">Kate Crawford</a> from the UCL Faculty for Engineering Science gave evidence <em>&lsquo;as an expert citizen&rsquo;</em> on the pros and cons of demoliton vs refurbishment, for which she had authored a <a href="http://www.engineering.ucl.ac.uk/engineering-exchange/files/2014/10/Report-Refurbishment-Demolition-Social-Housing.pdf">report</a> by the <a href="http://www.engineering.ucl.ac.uk/">UCL Engineering Exchange</a>.</p>

<p>Dr Crawford pointed out that there was no legible version of the cost benefit analysis comparing the benefits of demolition against refurbishment, which had been keenly sought by objectiors. She also pointed out that the issue of embodied energy had not been addressed. Ms Murphy had little time for any of this and again referred her to all the documents that Dr Crawford might not have read.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.peoplesrepublicofsouthwark.co.uk/images/stories/0205201502.jpg" width="400" height="300">Also appearing in support of the objectors were <a href="https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=JREND85">Professor Jane Rendell</a> from UCL Bartlett, who in her <a href="http://35percent.org/images/SummaryProfRendell.pdf">expert witness statement</a> pointed to seven reasons why the CPO was not in the public benefit and <a href="http://www2.le.ac.uk/departments/geography/people/professor-loretta-lees-1">Professor Loretta Lees</a>, an <em>&lsquo;international expert on gentrification and the policies and practices associated with it&rsquo;</em>. Professor Lees presented her research to the Inquiry which included extracts from interviews conducted on the estate and an analysis of the extent to which residents were being displaced from the area. Her displacement maps projected during the presentation, were a sobering reminder of the <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2013/06/08/the-heygate-diaspora/">Heygate diaspora</a> and provided a clear indication as to who this regeneration is (or isn&rsquo;t) benefitting.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/lorettalees_aylesburydisplacement.png"></p>

<h2>The residents speak</h2>

<p>On the fourth day a dose of reality was introduced into proceedings when residents gave personal testimony about the human impact and cost of the regeneration.</p>

<p>Les Kerrigan was a leaseholder and resident of 27 years standing and he spoke up for the refurbishment option. His family and friends were all in the area and he complained of the treatment he had received from Southwark&rsquo;s surveyors (a recurring theme) and their &lsquo;derisory&rsquo; offers of compensation.</p>

<p>Mrs Agnes Kabuto had been leaseholder for 25 years and spoke of Southwark&rsquo;s broken promises, including the promise that residents could return to the rebuilt Aylesbury.  Her grandchild attended the local school and her wheelchair-bound mother was becoming ill with anxiety about what would happen to them.  She could not afford any of the rehousing options Notting Hill had offered her and would have a problem getting a mortgage because of her age. She said she felt like <em>&lsquo;a small fish in a sea of sharks&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Ms Judi Boss complained of the confusion Southwark had caused leaseholders and spoke of the support leaseholders had given each other.  She said <em>&lsquo;I feel like I signed my human rights away when I signed my lease&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<p>A statement was read out on behalf of Mr Mehmet Suzman, aged 80, and his wife, Mrs Suzman, aged 76, because they were only able to attend the first day of the hearing. It said that they had no idea they could be bought-out without comparable compensation. They had had shop on the Walworth Rd and had lived in the area 40 years; their family and friends lived all around them; they asked where were they to go if Southwark took their home away from them? Who would give them a mortgage?</p>

<p>The Inquiry resumes back at the Den on 12th May.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury Applications Approved]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/26/aylesbury-applications-approved/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-26T20:25:05+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/26/aylesbury-applications-approved</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/CDTZqH_WYAAUca2.jpg" width="300" height="200">Southwark council battoned down the hatches at their Tooley Street headquarters last Thursday, in preparation for the controversial Aylesbury planning application committee hearing.
In the event, Aylesbury tenants and leaseholders were bitterly disappointed when the six hour meeting approved the <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">applications</a>.
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://peoplesrepublicofsouthwark.co.uk/images/2304201504.jpg" width="300" height="200">Unsurprisingly there was much emotion and some anger at the packed Committee meeting. Objectors were led by tenants group &lsquo;Aylesbury Tenants &amp; Leaseholders First&rsquo; <a href="http://aylesburytenantsfirst.org.uk/">ATLF</a>, accompanied by a representative from the 35% campaign.</p>

<p>ATLF spoke forcefully against the applications. They objected to the loss of social rented housing, the failure to respect the estate ballot that overwhelmingly voted against stock transfer and redevelopment by a housing association and the pitiful compensation and displacement of leaseholders.</p>

<p>35% campaigners took up the issue of the slippery social rented housing definitions and cited the <a href="http://35percent.org/images/AylesburyPlanningApplications_ref15AP3843-44.pdf">sleight of hand</a> used by Notting Hill Housing in their <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing/">Bermondsey Spa regeneration</a> and <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/18/aylesbury-planning-application-hearing/">Elmington estate regeneration</a>, switching social rent for affordable rent.</p>

<p>When Councillors challenged John Hughes - NHHT&rsquo;s Development Director about why NHHT had switched rent tenures at these schemes he replied: <strong> <em>&ldquo;The rents that we are charging at Grange Walk (Bermondsey Spa) and Edmund Street (Elmington estate) are wholly compliant with the planning permissions we received.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<iframe width="350" height="197" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Xqme8oXrCp0?rel=0" align="center" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>This is technically correct (affordable rent is ultimately what ended up in the planning legal agreements) but avoids the question of why the schemes were submitted and approved by committee as social rent. This question Hughes deferred to officers, suggesting they would be better placed to answer it, but thanks to the tight chairing of the meeting this was never followed up.</p>

<p>The only people who stepped forward to speak in support of the application were the Labour ward councillors for the estate.</p>

<p>While the decision to approve the application means that leaseholders now face the loss of their homes and at least 778 social rented homes are lost, a small victory was achieved: Southwark and Notting Hill agreed during the Committee to a tighter definition of social rented housing in the legal S106 agreement. So while this may provide some safeguard, true social rents are not yet guaranteed.</p>

<p>The 35% Campaign challenged Notting Hill&rsquo;s use of the term &lsquo;target rent&rsquo;. In response Notting Hill Housing <a href="http://35percent.org/images/MasterplanClarificationLetter7April.pdf">said</a> <em>&ldquo;social rent means target rent&rdquo;</em>. To which we can only ask <em>&ldquo;why not say social rent then?&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/votinginfavour.png" width="400" height="300">Notting Hill&rsquo;s funding for the Aylesbury development is <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/InsideHousingBoris.pdf">linked to providing affordable rent</a> not social rent. On the other hand Southwark has pledged that social rent is exactly what local people will get out of the Aylesbury redevelopment. Cooking up this new term <em>&lsquo;target rent&rsquo;</em> squares the circle, but at the expense of higher rents for local people.</p>

<p>The 35% campaign will be giving evidence at this week&rsquo;s Public Inquiry into the Aylesbury redevelopment, where we will be giving witness evidence and seeking a fuller explanation of Notting Hill&rsquo;s slippery definitions. The four-day Inquiry is open to the public and will be held at the <a href="http://www.millwallfc.co.uk/tickets/how0-to-get-here/">Millwall Football Club Conference Centre</a> from Tues 28th to Fri 1st (10am-5pm). For an idea of what will be debated at the Inquiry, <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Objectors_OpeningSubmissions_andAppendices.pdf">this copy</a> of the Objectors&#8217; Opening Submission sets out their arguments very clearly.</p>

<h2>Spineless Southwark</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11135/north-south_southwark_spine_cycle_route"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SouthwarkSpine.png" width="300" height="480"></a>While the 35% campaign learnt a wonderful bit of planning jargon on Thursday evening - &ldquo;bikeability&rdquo; - a great opportunity to strengthen the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1812/southwark_council_launches_new_cycling_strategy">&lsquo;Southwark Spine&rsquo;</a> cycling strategy was lost. This recently announced cycle route from the north to the south of the borough runs directly through the middle of the Aylesbury. The aspiration is that <em>&ldquo;the route will be segregated in areas of heavy traffic or large vehicles&rdquo;</em>. But this is now not going to happen on the Aylesbury, despite the fact that an additional bus route will be added to the three already which run down Thurlow street. Instead we will be getting <em>&ldquo;traffic calming measures&rdquo;</em> because Notting Hill doesn&rsquo;t want to encourage <em>&ldquo;fast commuter cycling&rdquo;</em> through its quiet residential development.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury Redevelopment - Decision Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/18/aylesbury-planning-application-hearing/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/04/18/aylesbury-planning-application-hearing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Aylesburyoutline2.jpg" width="400" height="300"> The planning applications for the redevelopment of the Aylesbury estate are to be considered by Southwark council&rsquo;s planning commitee on <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/ieListDocuments.aspx?CId=119&amp;MId=4808&amp;Ver=4">Thursday evening</a>. Officers recommend that approval be granted - their report on the outline masterplan application can be found <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!Vbu5QpckfYCnJrulzlWyuQ%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">here</a>.</p>

<p>We blogged <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing/">previously</a> about Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s development at the Bermondsey Spa regeneration, where social rented housing agreed at planning committee became affordable rent when - by sleight of hand - social rent was defined in the legal agreement as affordable rent.</p>

<p>In an email response to an enquiry about its Bermondsey Spa development from a local ward councillor, a Notting Hill spokesperson confirmed <strong> <em>&ldquo;we don&rsquo;t have any social rented properties here&rdquo;</em> </strong> and explained that the 44 &lsquo;social rented&rsquo; units are currently let at affordable rents, ranging from 42% of market rent for 3 beds to 63% of market rent for 1 beds (average across all unit types = 58% of market rents).</p>

<p><a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!J5kImYW5llmj0BA4PEvWpw%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d"><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/elmingtons106.png" width="430" height="310"></a>We have now discovered that the Bermondsey Spa tenure definition switch was no isolated incident: another Notting Hill Housing redevelopment - the Elmington estate regeneration (now rebranded <a href="http://www.camberwellfields.com/">&lsquo;Camberwell Fields&rsquo;</a>) has a definition of social rented housing in its <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7b%7b%7b!J5kImYW5llmj0BA4PEvWpw%3d%3d!%7d%7d%7d">S106 agreement</a> enabling the very same tenure switch.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/camberwell-fields-logo.png" width="300" height="200">&lsquo;Camberwell Fields&rsquo; is not due to be completed until later in the year, so we don&rsquo;t know exactly the percentage of market rent the supposed &lsquo;social rented&rsquo; units will be let at yet.<br/>
</br></p>

<p>Concern about the same thing happening on the Aylesbury has been amplified by Notting Hill&rsquo;s use of the term &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; in its planning application; this has raised great suspicion amongst local people. On the very eve of the planning hearing, Notting Hill were obliged to send <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/MasterplanClarificationLetter7April.pdf">letters</a> to all objectors &lsquo;clarifying&rsquo; amongst other things that the term &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; means social rent. Southwark&rsquo;s planning officers agree with this:<br/>
<img class="center" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/CCoxHXoWYAAyHtv.png"></p>

<p>However, Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s <a href="http://35percent.org/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.pdf">Development Partnership Agreement</a> for the Aylesbury has no such definiton; &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; is defined with a vague reference to a &lsquo;target&rsquo; and &lsquo;formula&rsquo; set by government, without any reference to the term social rent or the National Rent Regime regulatory framework which governs it.<br/>
<a href="http://35percent.org/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Aylesbury_targetrent.png"></a></p>

<p>Past planning committees have had the wool pulled over their eyes by Notting Hill Housing. If the same thing happens again on Thursday then we can add the loss of roughly 1300 social rented units promised by Notting Hill on the Aylesbury, to the 44 units lost at Bermondsey Spa and the 41 units set to be lost on its Elmington estate regeneration.</p>

<p>The Aylesbury applications are due to be heard on Thursday evening. In the meantime, we have written a <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyPlanningApplications_ref15AP3843-44.pdf">letter</a> to Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="https://twitter.com/interpolitan_1">Head of Planning</a> and the following planning committee councillors who will be deciding the application, urging them to reject the application until the precise legal definition of the social housing tenure proposed has been published for public consultation. If they stand for social housing which really is social housing or believe in a fair and transparent planning process then they will support and act upon our request.</p>

<ul>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=899">Nick Dolezal</a> -    Chair (Labour)</li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=50000619">Maisie Anderson</a>  (Labour) <a href="https://twitter.com/MaisieA">@MaisieA</a></li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=50000696">Sarah King</a>  (Labour) <a href="https://twitter.com/sezking78">@sezking78</a></li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=50000664">Hamish McCallum</a> (Lib Dem) <a href="https://twitter.com/hamishmccallum">@hamishmccallum</a></li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=909">Darren Merrill</a> (Labour) <a href="https://twitter.com/MerrillDarren">@MerrillDarren</a></li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=334">Michael Mitchell</a> (Conservative)</li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=50000717">Jamille Mohammed</a> (Labour)</li>
<li>Councillor <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/mgUserInfo.aspx?UID=161">Adele Morris</a>  (Lib Dem) <a href="https://twitter.com/AdeleCathedrals">@AdeleCathedrals</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manifesto for the Destruction of Council Estates]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/28/manifesto-for-destruction-of-council-estates/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-28T13:22:05+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/28/manifesto-for-destruction-of-council-estates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/adonis.png" width="300" height="200">The prestigious <strong>Institute of Public Policy Research (IPPR)</strong> has published a <a href="http://www.ippr.org/publications/city-villages-more-homes-better-communities">policy paper</a> that proposes the wholesale demolition of London&rsquo;s council estates, in the name of regeneration and to allow for the creation of so-called &lsquo;City Villages&rsquo;.</p>

<p>The paper is the brainchild of New Labour peer <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Adonis,_Baron_Adonis">Lord Adonis</a> and includes a chapter by Southwark council leader Peter John.</p>

<p>Adonis was a Greek god who was the epitomy of masculine beauty; our Lord Adonis is a more mundane character: a Blairite zealot who <a href="http://labourlist.org/2014/09/could-we-see-a-jowelladonis-ticket-for-london-mayor/">fancies himself as London&rsquo;s Deputy Mayor</a>. He has gathered together a group of like-minded cronies including London borough council leaders and <a href="http://www.grosvenorestate.com/">property developers</a> to pen a policy proposal entitled <strong>&ldquo;City Villages: More homes, better communities&rdquo;</strong>.</p>

<p>The idea is simple: London needs lots of new homes; they could all be built on brownfield sites; council estates are on brownfield sites - so let&rsquo;s demolish council estates. The land is worth a lot of money, so friendly property developers can be enlisted to help. Demolishing council estates would also get rid of that awful <strong> <em>&ldquo;mono-tenure&rdquo;</em> </strong>housing that breeds crime and anti-social behaviour.</p>

<p>His Lordship draws on various provocative examples to make his case, including the Heygate estate. Southwark council leader Peter John writes a chapter on this great success story, which our readers will know from <a href="http://35percent.org/affordable-housing/">previous posts</a> destroyed 1200 council homes, replacing them with 79 social rented units, plus 200 unaffordable &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; units, <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2013/06/08/the-heygate-diaspora/">ripping off leaseholders</a> along the way - or, in Councillor John&rsquo;s words creating <strong> <em>&ldquo;a genuine mix of private owned, private rented, shared ownership and social rented homes for people of all incomes.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/pjgrin.png" width="400" height="300">Councillor John further redefines the word success when he praises the Strata Tower&rsquo;s <strong> <em>&ldquo;distinctive three wind turbines&rdquo;</em> </strong>, <a href="http://35percent.org/strata-tower">which</a> do not turn, do not work and do not generate any electricity - a fitting symbol of the Elephant &amp; Castle regeneration after all.</p>

<p>Lord Adonis laments the fact that only a <strong> <em>&ldquo;tiny fraction&rdquo;</em> </strong> of London&rsquo;s estates are currently being redeveloped and cites amongst these the massive <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/davehillblog/2015/mar/26/andrew-adonis-and-estate-regeneration-some-pros-and-cons">Earls Court redevelopment</a>, which will require the <a href="https://westkengibbsgreen.wordpress.com/">demolition of the West Ken &amp; Gibbs estate</a> and of course our very own <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">Aylesbury redevelopment</a>.</p>

<p>Both his Lordship and Councillor John acknowledge that this can all be a bit controversial, in that <strong> <em>&ldquo;redevelopment of estates is sometimes assumed to mean that existing tenants and residents will be displaced by wealthier incomers&rdquo;</em> </strong>, but according to Lord Adonis <strong> <em>&ldquo;this need not, nor should it be the case&rdquo;</em> </strong>, since redevelopment should offer ample opportunity for residents to remain in new homes once completed.</p>

<p>We beg to differ; over the past 10 years estate regenerations have <a href="https://www.london.gov.uk/media/assembly-press-releases/2015/02/8000-social-homes-lost-in-a-decade">lost us 8,000 social rented units</a>, while increasing free-market housing ten-fold and doubling the overall housing density. The lessons that we&rsquo;ve learned are that anyone who stands in the way of a regeneration - whether council tenant or leaseholder - is going to lose their home and will unlikely be able to afford any of the new homes.</p>

<p>We are not the only ones to take issue with Lord Adonis&rsquo;s policy proposals; Duncan Bowie, member of the EC of London Labour Housing Group and former advisor to Ken Livingstone has published a <a href="https://redbrickblog.wordpress.com/2015/03/31/city-villages-the-wrong-solution-to-londons-housing-crisis/">detailed critique</a> of Adonis&rsquo;s proposals, which he describes as <em>&lsquo;grossly out of touch&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<h2>Aylesbury planning application - get your tickets now!</h2>

<p>The date of the planning committee meeting for the Aylesbury redevelopment applications has been set back from the 14th April, possibly to the 21st April. The council has said it is expecting &lsquo;much interest&rsquo; and it&rsquo;s likely that the meeting will be ticketed, which requires anyone wishing to attend to register with the council beforehand. Health and safety concerns are clearly uppermost in Southwark council&rsquo;s mind and will no doubt mean that numbers will also be limited.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/chilterngroup.png" width="400" height="300">However, the date for the Compulsory Purchase Order Public Inquiry is fixed (28th April - 1st May at <a href="https://www.etcvenues.co.uk/venues/prospero-house">Prospero House</a>) and this will not be changed. The <a href="http://halag.wordpress.com">Aylesbury Leaseholders Action Group</a> has published its Statement of Case ahead of the Inquiry. Their objections explain how replacement housing will be unaffordable to existing residents and explore the lack of transparency about the proposed tenure mix. You can read through their Statement of Case on their campaign website <a href="https://halag.wordpress.com/2015/03/27/cpo-public-inquiry-help-required/">here</a>.</p>

<h2>P.S. - IPPR makes a couple of good suggestions</h2>

<p>To return to the IPPR policy paper - it does make one or two constructive suggestions, such as the recommendation that <strong> <em>&ldquo;At a minimum, tenants should be balloted on regeneration schemes&rdquo;</em> </strong>. Cllr John couldn&rsquo;t have read this bit, because of course the Aylesbury residents <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2001/dec/27/1">gave a resounding &lsquo;NO&rsquo;</a> to regeneration when they were balloted in 2001.</p>

<p>Another recommendation <strong> <em>&ldquo;Transparency about the future tenure mix is essential from the outset&rdquo;</em> </strong> is also absent from the Aylesbury redevelopment; as we saw in our last two blog posts, Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s definition of social rented tenure is as clear as mud and it has also been <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2015/mar/29/tenants-face-70m-rent-rise-as-social-housing-converted-to-affordable-homes">reported</a> to be converting its existing social tenancies at an alarming rate.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stand Up for More Social Housing (at 80% Market Rent)]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-18T09:29:17+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/18/stand-up-for-more-social-housing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/homesforbritain.jpg' width='250' height='500' title='Notting Hill Director Kate Davies'><span class='caption-text'>Notting Hill Director Kate Davies</span></span><strong> <em>&ldquo;Let&rsquo;s all of us stand up for more social housing&rdquo;</em> </strong> was the <a href="https://twitter.com/NottingHillHG/status/577771553842167808">call to arms</a> during the <a href="http://www.24dash.com/news/housing/2015-03-18-The-Homes-for-Britain-bus-relay-reaches-Westminister">&lsquo;impassioned speech&rsquo;</a> from Notting Hill Housing Trust&rsquo;s Director Kate Davies at yesterday&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2015/mar/17/london-housing-rally-protesters-gather-at-homes-for-britain-event">&lsquo;Homes for Britain&rsquo;</a> rally. The rally was part of an ongoing campaign organised by the <a href="http://www.housing.org.uk/">National Housing Federation</a>, of which NHHT is a founding member.</p>

<p>We have blogged previously about NHHT&rsquo;s dodgy definition of social housing and its <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/customers/permanent-rented-housing/information-for-permanent-rented-housing-tenants/affordable-rent-update">blanket policy</a> of converting all its existing social rented properties to <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/housing-network/2014/feb/03/affordable-housing-meaning-rent-social-housing">affordable rent</a> when tenancies expire.</p>

<p>So we have taken a closer look at the kind of &lsquo;social&rsquo; housing Notting Hill&rsquo;s Director wants us all to stand up for more of.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/theexchange.jpg' width='' height='' title=''The Exchange' - Notting Hill's 205 unit development at the Bermondsey Spa regeneration scheme (site 5C)'><span class='caption-text'>&lsquo;The Exchange&rsquo; - Notting Hill&rsquo;s 205 unit development at the Bermondsey Spa regeneration scheme (site 5C)</span></span>
This is <a href="http://www.the-exchange-london.com/">&lsquo;The Exchange&rsquo;</a> in Bermondsey, Notting Hill&rsquo;s latest completed development in Southwark and part of the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200180/bermondsey_spa/1144/bermondsey_spa_masterplan">Bermondsey Spa regeneration scheme</a>.
All but three private and two shared-ownership units in this 205-home development have been sold and of those that remain the private flats are <a href="http://www.the-exchange-london.com/availability?tenure=TH">priced</a> at over £1m and the shared-ownership flats <a href="http://www.the-exchange-london.com/availability/so">require</a> a minimum salary of £73,986 to qualify.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://www.downwelldemo.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/01/P6060031.jpg' width='350' height='300' title='Demolition of 54 council homes on the site'><span class='caption-text'>Demolition of 54 council homes on the site</span></span>The development should also have had 44 social rented units, to replace the 54 council homes demolished to make way for <strong>&lsquo;The Exchange&rsquo;</strong>.</p>

<p>44 social rented units were duly proposed in Notting Hill&rsquo;s <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?casereference=10/AP/3010&amp;system=DC">planning application</a> for the site and that&rsquo;s what was confirmed in the <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7B%7B%7B!7lhb2IoB57lo6iUf2g/V0A==!%7D%7D%7D">planning officer&rsquo;s report</a>. Paragraphs 27 &amp; 29 of the GLA <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/GLABermondseySpaReport.pdf">planning report</a> also confirmed that the development proposed 44 social rented homes. However, after approval was given Southwark Council and Notting Hill signed-off the <a href="http://planbuild.southwark.gov.uk/documents/?GetDocument=%7B%7B%7B!v0IQJeAkBHGLkpIJJYfrTA==!%7D%7D%7D">s106 legal agreement</a> with something completely different - 44 &lsquo;affordable rented&rsquo; units (ie. up to 80% market rents) <strong>not</strong> 44 social rented units.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/BermondseySpaS106.png' width='' height='' title='Officers report states 44 Social Rented homes but S106 Agreement says Affordable Rented units'><span class='caption-text'>Officers report states 44 Social Rented homes but S106 Agreement says Affordable Rented units</span></span></p>

<p>The change in wording is subtle but the consequences aren&rsquo;t; according to <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">Southwark&rsquo;s own figures</a>, a 1-bed social rented flat in Bermondsey(SE16) costs an average £97 per week, compared to £273 per week for &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; at 80% market rent.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s hard not to conclude that the public has been deceived over this development: it was led to believe that it was getting social rents at all stages up to planning approval, then a switch was effected when the legal documents were drawn up after approval was granted.</p>

<p>We showed in our last blog how this sleight-of-hand is becoming commonplace in Southwark&rsquo;s planning process.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.png' width='400' height='200' title='Extract from Aylesbury estate Development Agreement'><span class='caption-text'>Extract from Aylesbury estate Development Agreement</span></span>We have also shown in <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">previous blog posts</a> how Notting Hill is using the terms &lsquo;social&rsquo;, &lsquo;target&rsquo; and &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; rent interchangably in its forthcoming application for the Aylesbury estate redevelopment and <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/10/affordable-rent-is-not-social/">blogged</a> about the worrying fact that affordable rents of up to 80% are included in the Notting Hill development agreement for the Aylesbury.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburySelection.jpg' width='' height='' title='Notting Hill's Director & Southwark council leader celebrate demolition of Aylesbury redevelopment's phase 2'><span class='caption-text'>Notting Hill&rsquo;s Director &amp; Southwark council leader celebrate demolition of Aylesbury redevelopment&rsquo;s phase 2</span></span>
So, we have to ask the question - will the Aylesbury go the same way as the Bermondsey Spa regeneration with affordable rent slipped in quietly through the back door?</p>

<p>One way of finding out would be to for details of Notting Hill&rsquo;s funding allocation for the Aylesbury redevelopment. It has currently secured a total of £92m in funding from the Mayor&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.london.gov.uk/priorities/housing-land/increasing-housing-supply/affordable-homes-programme">Affordable Homes Programme</a> and is by far the largest single recipient of funding from it. London Assembly member Darren Johnson recently tabled a formal <a href="http://questions.london.gov.uk/QuestionSearch/searchclient/questions/question_281359">question</a> to the Mayor about the tenure mix linked to Notting Hill&rsquo;s £92m allocation. We will be watching out for the Mayor&rsquo;s response.</p>

<p>We need to let the council know that the game is up and that we are not going to accept this disingenuous racket. The Aylesbury planning application is due to be heard by committee on 14th April and we will be making our voices heard. We invite you to support us by objecting to the planning application online using our <a href="http://commentform.herokuapp.com">automated objection form</a>.</p>

<h2>Postscript update (3rd April 2015)</h2>

<p>The people at <a href="http://southwarknotes.wordpress.com">Southwark Notes</a> couldn&rsquo;t quite believe that Notting Hill had passed off affordable rent as social rent at its Bermondsey Spa site, so they attempted to seek confirmation via twitter:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/NottingHillHG">@NottingHillHG</a> Hiya NHHT. Is it true that 44 units of social housing at your Exchange site will be &#39;affordable rent&#39;? <a href="http://t.co/gUvnsYQjZX">http://t.co/gUvnsYQjZX</a></p>&mdash; Southwark Notes (@SouthwarkNotes) <a href="https://twitter.com/SouthwarkNotes/status/578173781019111424">March 18, 2015</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>Notting Hill unashamedly confirmed that Bermondsey Spa&rsquo;s 44 &lsquo;social rented&rsquo; units were indeed let at affordable rather than social rents, but that these generally averaged just 58% of market rent:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-cards="hidden" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/SouthwarkNotes">@SouthwarkNotes</a> Yes, affordable rent (average 58% of market rent) due to Gov changes to rent setting in 2011. See <a href="http://t.co/2tThW5DZGZ">http://t.co/2tThW5DZGZ</a></p>&mdash; Notting Hill Housing (@NottingHillHG) <a href="https://twitter.com/NottingHillHG/status/583639651702943744">April 2, 2015</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>Notting Hill&rsquo;s twitter reply also blamed its change of tenure on <strong> <em>&ldquo;Government changes to rent setting&rdquo;</em> </strong> and provided a <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/customers/permanent-rented-housing/money/how-we-set-your-rent-and-charges/rent-increases">link to its website</a> for further details. Below is an extract from that website link, where Notting Hill explains what affordable rent is and confirms that <strong> <em>&ldquo;Approximately 10% of all our &lsquo;social rented housing&rsquo; properties are rented at affordable rents&rdquo;.</em> </strong><br/>
<img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/NHHTAffordableRent.png" width="550" height="500"></p>

<p>We note that Notting Hill has written the term <strong>&lsquo;social rented housing&rsquo;</strong> in inverted commas. It seems that - thanks to Notting Hill Housing Trust - this might be the way <strong>&lsquo;social rented housing&rsquo;</strong> needs to be written from now on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Affordable Rent Is Not Social Rent]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/10/affordable-rent-is-not-social/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-10T20:37:50+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/03/10/affordable-rent-is-not-social</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/279910_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/wolvertons106SR2.png" width="400" height="400"></a>We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">blogged previously</a> about the last phase of the Aylesbury redevelopment, where we saw plans waved through as social rent, only to discover afterwards that the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/279910_1.pdf">s106 legal agreement</a> defined social rent as encompassing the <a href="http://cfg.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/affordable-rent">HCA&rsquo;s definition of affordable rent</a> (80% market rent).
</br>
</br></p>

<p><a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk/Manor-Place-Exhibition-Banners.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Manorplace_socialrent2.png" width="300" height="320"></a>Notting Hill Housing Group, which is developing all subsequent phases of the Aylesbury estate, has taken a different approach: instead of substituting affordable rent for social rent via the back door, it is openly defining affordable rent as a subcategory of social rent.
Those familiar with housing policy will know that social rents are not determined by Housing Associations; they are determined by the National Rent Regime regulatory framework - and that they are not set in relation to market rents; they are set in relation to average household incomes.</p>

<p>This hasn&rsquo;t deterred Notting Hill Housing; its <a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk/Manor-Place-Exhibition-Banners.pdf">consultation document</a> for another Walworth scheme, the <a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk">Manor Place development</a> (a former Council <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/10070/recycling/1364/reuse_and_recycling_centre">refuse depot</a>) shows it will be setting rents for its new social rented homes at <em>&ldquo;up to 50% of local market rents&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/RentsRising.jpg" width="300" height="200">50% of local market rents may sound like a good deal to some, but in an area where rents have increased by 17% in the last 3 years<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> to an average £300 per week for a 1-bed flat<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, 50% of market rents is roughly double existing council rents. The crucial difference is also that market rents rise well beyond wages in property hotspots like Southwark; an important consideration in a borough where the average household income of a council tenant is £9,100 per year<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> and definitely not rising at the same rate as local market rents.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/affordablerentstudy.png" width="350" height="300"></a>Southwark council has undertaken <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/download/2914/affordable_rent_in_southwark_2011">a study</a> of the affordability of affordable rent in the borough, so it is entirely aware that these ridiculous &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; rents are unaffordable to most of its residents. Indeed, it has said as much in <a href="http://35percent.org/images/fionacolleyresponsetolondonplan.pdf">representations to the Mayor</a> rejecting the new tenure policy. <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">This spreadheet</a> from the council&rsquo;s study shows the minimum household income needed for one of Notting Hill&rsquo;s new 50% market rent &lsquo;social rented&rsquo; homes is £39,860 per year - well beyond the £21,000 mean average household income in Walworth.</p>

<p>We don&rsquo;t yet know what percentage of market rent the replacement &lsquo;social&rsquo; housing on the new Aylesbury estate will be, but we do know that the <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.pdf">Agreement</a> signed for the sale of the estate allows notting hill to set the new affordable rents at up to 80% market rent:</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LBS_NHHT_DPAgreement.png"></a></p>

<p>Some might see all this as an inevitable consequence of the market and beyond the control of public authorities, but this would ignore the fact that the Aylesbury and Manor Place depot are on council-owned land, being bought in turn by a publicly-funded Housing Association. Southwark and Notting Hill should be fulfilling their duty to build truly affordable and truly social rented homes on this land, not playing games with dodgy &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; housing definitions.
</br></p>

<h2>More from the Notting Hill Mob</h2>

<p>Notting Hill are also involved in the Council&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/823/regeneration_projects/1798/elmington_regeneration/4">Elmingtion estate regeneration</a> in Camberwell, where the council has just <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s48494/Report%20CPO%20for%20Elmington%20Estate.pdf">issued a Compulsory Purchase Order</a> on 144 homes in phase 3 of the scheme. Phases 1 &amp; 2, where Notting Hill has already <a href="http://directobjective.blogspot.co.uk/2011/12/elmington-estate-revisited.html">demolished 373 council homes</a>, are nearing completion and the new &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; homes are currently being marketed in the development rebranded <a href="http://www.camberwellfields.com/">&lsquo;Camberwell Fields&rsquo;</a>.
<a href="http://www.camberwellfields.com/"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/camberwell-fields-logo.png"></a></p>

<p>Paragraph 12 of this <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s30291/Report%20Disposal%20of%20the%20Councils%20freehold%20interest%20in%20Elmington%20estate%20sites%20C%20D%20E%20and%20G%20Camberw.pdf">Council report</a> confirms that all replacement 1 &amp; 2 bed social housing in the redevelopment will be set at 65% market rent. According to <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">Southwark&rsquo;s figures</a> this will amount to £194 per week: double the existing council rents. Tenants who have been &lsquo;decanted&rsquo; from the estate and wish to exercise their right to return, will therefore need to be able to afford a 100% rent hike.</p>

<p>But the main component of the new &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; housing comprises shared ownership units. Notting Hill has just released the <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/CamberwellFields.pdf">price list</a> for these, and the cheapest will be £380k for a 1-bed flat. For this you will need to buy a minimum 40% share, have a minimum household income of £51,824 and will pay a total of £1,438 per month in rent, mortgage and service charge payments. The average income of Camberwell households is £24,400pa, so they are obviously out of luck.</p>

<h2>Not Notting Hill (but not better neither)..</h2>

<p><a href="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/properties/lq-trafalgar-place/?preview=true"><img class="left" src="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/LQ-@-Trafalfar-Place-Brochure.jpg" width="250" height="300"></a>Last week, L&amp;Q <a href="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/properties/lq-trafalgar-place/?preview=true">launched</a> its shared ownership homes on the redeveloped Heygate estate. The launch coincided with the latest phase of marketing at a <a href="http://www.thestandard.com.hk/news_detail.asp?art_id=154851&amp;con_type=3">sales event in Hong Kong</a>. According to L&amp;Q&rsquo;s <a href="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/LQ-@-Trafalgar-Place-Pricelist-12-bed-launch-2.pdf">price list</a>, the cheapest of the Heygate&rsquo;s new &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; shared ownership homes will set you back £126k for a 30% stake in a 1-bed flat, for which you will need to buy a minimum 30% share, requiring a household income of at least £57,500k per year. A 25% share in a 2-bed duplex will set you back £185,625, but with a minimum household income requirement of £64,500 it won&rsquo;t be long before you will be able to staircase up to full ownership of the flat, priced at a mere £742,500. It seems our council leader is finally delivering on his housing <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7585">pledge</a> to help poor Southwark residents on <em>&ldquo;£60-£80,000 a year – but who have absolutely no hope of buying&rdquo;</em>.   <br/>
</br></p>

<h2>Southwark seeks help</h2>

<p><a href="http://southwark.communitymaps.org.uk/#/project/15?center=51.4653:-0.0707:12"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/interactivemap.png" width="250" height="250"></a>While council estates tumble across the borough Southwark Council has launched an <a href="http://southwark.communitymaps.org.uk/#/welcome">interactive map</a>, inviting people to suggest where it should build its pledged 11,000 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes. Vacant land is limited so it will be a difficult task; back in December the Council even <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/12/06/11000-new-private-and-social-council-homes-on-target/">suggested</a> exploring the purchase of land on the open market from developers. Given its <a href="http://35percent.org/heygate-regeneration-faq/">track record</a> in negotiating with developers, a better alternative would be to build the new council homes on the vast estates that the Council is &lsquo;regenerating&rsquo; (Heygate, Aylesbury, Wooddene &amp; Elmington etc). Even now it’s not too late and surely preferable to selling these sites off to developers and corporated-minded Housing Associations, who provide nothing but a few unaffordable affordable homes in return?</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Source: <a href="http://data.london.gov.uk/dataset/average-private-rents-borough/resource/73b9fb07-b5bb-4a53-88b7-c17269879a08">Greater London Authority - Dataset 2014</a><a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See data for SE17 in Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">Dec 2014 Affordable Rent Study dataset</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See sheet 8, row 9 of the Council&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">Dec 2014 Affordable Rent Study update</a>.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Greenwich Developers Ordered to Show Their Sums]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/02/04/developers-ordered-to-show-their-sums/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-04T15:19:21+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/02/04/developers-ordered-to-show-their-sums</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://gsa-studios.com/images/uploads/projects/1168x650_greenwich.jpg" width="300" height="200">We reported last year how a residents group in Greenwich had followed our lead and requested the viability assessments justifying decisions to reduce affordable housing in the £5bn Greenwich Peninsula redevelopment. Similar to our request for the Heygate figures, Greenwich residents had won the support of the Information Commissioner but were then taken to appeal by the Council and developer Knight Dragon. We put them in touch with our legal friends at Leigh Day &amp; Monckton Chambers and expert witness <a href="http://www.northampton.ac.uk/directories/people/bob-colenutt">Dr Colenutt</a> who helped the campaigners take on the Council &amp; developer&rsquo;s barristers at an Information Tribunal hearing in October last year.</p>

<p>After a two month wait, the Tribunal issued its <a href="http://bit.ly/1zS9Qc0">decision notice</a> earlier this week. The decision was conclusive and damning; it rejected the Council&rsquo;s arguments and pointed out that councillors on Greenwich&rsquo;s planning committee had no more information about the viability figures than did the general public. Hong Kong developer Knight Frank&rsquo;s arguments about commercial confidentiality were also given short shrift by the Judge <strong> <em>&ldquo;This is a case where a company, robust enough to take on the development of a huge site over a period of 20 years.. immediately asks to be relieved of a planning obligation freely negotiated by its predecessor. It justifies this change on the basis of a downturn in house prices it knew about at the time of purchase, using a valuation model that looks at current values only and does not allow for change in the many factors that may affect a valuation over time. It seems to us that in those circumstances the public interest in openness about the figures is very strong.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>In contrast to the Heygate decision where developer Lend Lease was allowed to withhold its financial model in appendix 22 of the assessment, the Greenwich decision took a much tougher line: <strong> <em>&lsquo;once it is accepted that the EIR regulations apply, it is necessary to apply them in their full rigour.  There is no room for an “EIR lite” approach&rsquo;</em> </strong> (para. 24) <br/>
There are more details about the Greenwich decision on the <a href="http://853blog.com/2015/02/03/greenwich-peninsula-social-cleansing-council-loses-battle-to-keep-developer-document-secret/">853 blog</a>.</p>

<h2>Viability for dummies</h2>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/viabilityfordummies.pdf"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/viabilityfordummies.png" width="300" height="400"></a>In terms of EIR case law, there was still some doubt following the Heygate decision about exactly what developers are allowed to withhold, especially in light of the ongoing legal battle over the interpretation of the Heygate decision notice. The Greenwich decision appears to have addressed that ambiguity and provided a clear steer as to what exactly is subject to disclosure - everything.</p>

<p>This should now clear the path for other community groups to obtain viability information and participate more meaningfully in planning issues.</p>

<p>In an attempt to help them do so, we have drafted a <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/viabilityfordummies.pdf">&lsquo;dummies&rsquo; guide</a> to viability, part 1 of which explains how to obtain viability information using EIR requests.</p>

<h2>Heygate Tribunal battle continues</h2>

<p>The ongoing battle over the interpretation of the Tribunal&rsquo;s May 2014 <a href="http://www.informationtribunal.gov.uk/DBFiles/Decision/i1279/London%20Borough%20of%20Southwark%20EA.2013.0162%20%2809.05.14%29.pdf">decision notice</a> continues. The decision allowed Lend Lease to withhold its financial development model projections on retail and office floorspace. The notice ordered the parties to get together and agree on dividing up the information for disclosure along those lines. It acknowledged that there may be &lsquo;grey areas&rsquo; and stated that if parties are unable to reach agreement then it will reconvene to settle the argument.
After many months of stalling and heel dragging by Southwark and Lend Lease, the Tribunal reconvened partially in October and was due to reconvene for a full hearing on 11th Dec last year. But Lend Lease&rsquo;s Commercial Director was unable to attend so the hearing was postponed. The hearing was finally able to take place on 21st January when parties made their arguments on how the information should be divided up according to the Tribunal&rsquo;s May 2014 decision.</p>

<p>During the hearing Lend Lease&rsquo;s counsel argued that protecting its financial model in appendix 22, also extended to protecting the inputs and outputs to the model found elsewhere in the report and its appendices. Mr Glasspool&rsquo;s counsel pointed out that the inputs and outputs did not form &lsquo;part of the model&rsquo; and would not expose the model&rsquo;s underlying formulas that Lend Lease had so vehemently argued were its &lsquo;trade secret&rsquo;.</p>

<p>The Tribunal is expected to issue a decision notice detailing exactly which information can be withheld some time in the next few weeks.</p>

<h2>Southwark joins 35% campaign</h2>

<p>Southwark Council issued a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1903/southwark_council_slams_plans_to_reduce_affordable_housing_contributions">press statement</a> earlier this week entitled <strong> <em>&ldquo;Southwark Council slams plans to reduce affordable housing contributions.&rdquo;</em> </strong> The statement says it <strong> <em>&ldquo;has hit out at government plans to allow developers to reduce affordable housing contributions&rdquo;</em> </strong>. It is referring to the governments new <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2015/feb/01/property-developers-affordable-housing-councils-empty-building">&lsquo;vacant building credit&rsquo;</a>, which is said to cut back even further the amount of affordable housing delivered through planning gain.</p>

<p>Much as we applaud Southwark&rsquo;s sentiment, we point out that it first needs to sort out its problem of allowing developers to get away with avoiding affordable housing by viability assessments. Two such examples are these developments currently under construction at the Elephant, both of which are being built on land sold to developers by the Council. Thanks to Southwark&rsquo;s failure to question the viability assessments submitted at planning, neither of these will provide any affordable housing and the payments in-lieu are a fraction of what they should have been according to Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://affordable.heroku.com/images/affordablehousingspg.pdf">in-lieu tariff</a>.     <br/>
<img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/tribecaonetheelephant.jpg"></p>

<p>You can read more detailed info about the Tribeca Square development <a href="http://35percent.org/tribeca-square/">here</a> and One The Elephant <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/01/11/flogging-the-elephant/">here.</a></p>

<h2>Aylesbury Occupied</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/B8_4AbdIAAAb-ir.jpg" width="300" height="600"> Housing activists have occupied empty homes on the Aylesbury estate. The activists took up occupation directly following last weekend&rsquo;s <a href="http://marchforhomes.org">March for Homes</a> and are protesting at the failure to address London&rsquo;s growing housing crisis.</p>

<p>In an <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/development/protestors-occupy-estate-earmarked-for-15bn-regeneration/7008068.article">interview</a> with Inside Housing, Councillor Williams, Southwark&rsquo;s Cabinet member for Regeneration claimed that the protesters <strong> <em>&ldquo;are risking the delivery of the very homes they claim to be campaigning for.&rdquo;</em> </strong> He went on to explain that <strong> <em>&ldquo;The scheme will be 50% affordable, with 75% of these rented and 25% for shared ownership.&rdquo;</em> </strong> We are unsurprised to note the semantic subtlety of Cllr Williams&#8217; omitting to use either the word <strong>&lsquo;social&rsquo;</strong> or <strong>&lsquo;affordable&rsquo;</strong> in conjunction with the word <strong>&lsquo;rented&rsquo;</strong>.</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyTLF.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyTLF.png" width="300" height="400"></a>Cllr Williams also claims that the protestors don&rsquo;t represent the Aylesbury residents, but <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyTLF.pdf">this flyer</a> suggests that at least <a href="http://aylesburytenantsfirst.org.uk/">one tenants group</a> on the estate disagrees.</p>

<p>The Aylesbury occupiers have set up a website for their campaign <a href="http://fightfortheaylesbury.wordpress.com">http://fightfortheaylesbury.wordpress.com</a> and Twitter account: @OccupyAylesbury
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>Concrete Heartland</h2>

<p>Concrete Heartland, a film about the Heygate regeneration by Steven Ball and Rastko Novaković has now been released online. Following a number of screenings last year, it has now been uploaded for popular consumption and can be viewed online at <a href="http://concreteheartland.info">http://concreteheartland.info</a><br/>
Assembled from 12 years of archive materials, the film charts the struggles of the local community to keep their homes, stay living in the area and maintain communal benefits in the face of the advance of this now notorious &lsquo;urban redevelopment programme&rsquo;.</p>

<h2>West Hendon estate</h2>

<p>BBC&rsquo;s The One Show featured a piece on the West Hendon estate on Monday. Due to the notorius viability arguments, residents there are being forced out of the area after developers Barratt argued that it was no longer possible to rehouse them in the new development. The story sounds all too familiar to us down here in Southwark.
</center></p>

<iframe width="350" height="197" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5OXc814Q9ps" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p></center></p>

<h2>Affordable housing tenants excluded from communal gardens</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/media/brochure/b2678/files/assets/common/page-substrates/page0015.jpg" width="300" height="200">Southwark&rsquo;s planning committee <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/8077">has agreed</a> to a variation in planning conditions for the <a href="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/new-homes/london/tower-bridge/one-tower-bridge">One Tower Bridge development</a>, to prevent affordable housing tenants being able to use the communal garden available to private residents. Simon Bevan, Southwark&rsquo;s director of planning, told the planning committee that the exclusion of social tenants from the garden was <strong> <em>&ldquo;not seen as any significant restriction on how they enjoy their property&rdquo;.</em> </strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Peabody's Philanthropic Glass Towers - 0% Social Housing]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/01/27/peabody-borough-triangle-development/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-27T09:08:17+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/01/27/peabody-borough-triangle-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/BoroughTriangle.png" width="400" height="300">Peabody Housing Association has finally submitted a <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9556404">Planning application</a> for its long-awaited <em>Borough Triangle</em> development at Elephant &amp; Castle. This large triangle of land sits between Southbank University, Borough road and the Crown Court on Newington Causeway.</p>

<p>The site is currently home to the <a href="https://www.ipsos-mori.com/">IPSOS MORI</a> buildings and Baptist church on Borough road, which will be the only buildings to survive the redevelopment. The Georgian-built <a href="http://www.ioo.org.uk/">Institute of Optometry</a> and <a href="http://www.thestage.co.uk/news/2015/01/london-school-musical-theatre-relocate-southwark-site-demolished/">London School of Musical Theatre</a> (formerly the Institute for the Blind) will both be demolished under Peabody&rsquo;s plans. The latter being replaced by <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/NewMinistryOfSound.png">new premises</a> for the Ministry of Sound, which Peabody will build in its place.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/boroughtriangle.jpg"></p>

<p>The shops and warehouse spaces on the Newington side of the site will also be demolished. These are currently being used as a Pop-up arts and cultural space by <a href="http://www.hotelelephant.co.uk/">&lsquo;Hotel Elephant&rsquo;</a> and <a href="http://www.thepaperworks.co.uk/">&lsquo;The Paperworks&rsquo;</a>.<br/>
<img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/HotelElephant_Paperworks.jpg"></p>

<p>Besides new premises for the Ministry of Sound night club totalling ca. 6,000 sqm (allowing an extra capacity of 400 people over its current venue), Peabody plans to build some retail space; 10,000 sqm of office space in a shiny new corporate HQ for its staff; and a total of 529 new homes in a number of (predominantly glass) buildings of up to 38 storeys.</p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/388339_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Peabody_BoroughTriangle.png"></a></p>

<p>We originally had high hopes that this site would provide the desperately needed social rented housing that local people need. Unfortunately Peabody appears to have followed the trend of going for the more profitable &lsquo;affordable rented&rsquo; housing with rents of up to 80% market rent. It has also followed the trend of fudging and misleading about the precise nature of the affordable housing it is providing. In its <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387231_1.pdf">Housing Statement</a> Peabody states that it will be providing 96 <strong>intermediate</strong> units (16.7% of total) and 78 units at <strong>affordable rent</strong> (16.5% of total).</p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387231_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/affordable_rent_peabody.png" width="400" height="300"></a></p>

<p>However, Peabody&rsquo;s <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387199_1.pdf">Planning Statement</a> starts off by explaining the council&rsquo;s affordable housing policy: <strong> <em>&ldquo;5.117 In terms of affordable housing tenure, the Core Strategy at Strategic Policy 6 identifies that for development within the Elephant and Castle Opportunity Area the affordable housing should be delivered at 50% intermediate and 50% social rented.&rdquo;</em> </strong> but then dropping the word &lsquo;social&rsquo; from social rented, astonishingly goes on to claim that the application is policy compliant: <strong> <em>&ldquo;The proposal provides 16.7% intermediate and 16.5% for rented which is considered to comply with policy.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Peabody_ApplicationForm.png">We checked the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387188_1.pdf">application form</a> to see what had been written in the useful boxes that Southwark provides showing detailed tenure mix information. We found that the 78 units had indeed been entered under the category social rented, but that the applicant had doctored the application form to include the word &lsquo;AFFORDABLE&rsquo; over the title &lsquo;Social Rented&rsquo;.</p>

<p>We also checked the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/388020_1.pdf">Design &amp; Access Statement</a> which states not only that the units will be affordable rent, but that they will be <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Peabody_TenureMix.png">segregated</a> from the other tenures (the high-rise towers will be exclusively private and intermediate housing).</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/EmailDanielDavies.png" width="400" height="300">Finally, we wrote to the Council&rsquo;s planning department asking for some clarity on whether the 78 units were for social rent or affordable rent; this is the baffling response we received.</p>

<p>Southwark recently published a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/download/2914/affordable_rent_in_southwark_2011">detailed study</a> of the impact of the introduction of affordable rent in the borough. From its <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">underlying data</a> we can see that a 1-bed social rented flat in SE1 would cost an average £97 per week, but a 1-bed flat at the new &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; of 80% market rent would cost £316 per week. Given that the median household income for council tenants in Borough and Bankside is £9,100 per year, it is clear that Peabody&rsquo;s affordable housing offer will be of no help to local people in housing need.  <br/>
</br>
Borough Triangle is the second largest development in the Elephant &amp; Castle opportunity area after the Heygate. No doubt lengthy discussions have taken place between Peabody, the Ministry of Sound and Southwark about what should be delivered on this key regeneration site. It is very dissapointing that a Housing Association with Peabody&rsquo;s reputation is not only failing to provide social housing, but is also seeking to mislead people about the fact. It is doubly dissapointing - but not surprising on past record - that Southwark is going along with it.</p>

<p>It seems Peabody has come a long way from the philanthropic intentions it was founded on in 1862, by George Peabody who wanted to <a href="http://www.peabody.org.uk/about-us/our-story"><strong> <em>&ldquo;ameliorate the condition of the poor and needy in this great metropolis&rdquo;</em> </strong></a>.</p>

<p>You can object to Peabody&rsquo;s application (ref:14/AP/3130) by sending an email to <a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x70;&#108;&#97;&#x6e;&#110;&#105;&#x6e;&#x67;&#x2e;&#x61;&#112;&#x70;&#108;&#x69;&#x63;&#x61;&#x74;&#105;&#x6f;&#110;&#x73;&#64;&#x73;&#x6f;&#117;&#x74;&#x68;&#119;&#97;&#x72;&#107;&#x2e;&#x67;&#x6f;&#x76;&#x2e;&#x75;&#107;">&#112;&#108;&#97;&#x6e;&#x6e;&#105;&#110;&#103;&#x2e;&#x61;&#x70;&#x70;&#x6c;&#105;&#x63;&#97;&#x74;&#105;&#111;&#110;&#115;&#64;&#x73;&#111;&#117;&#116;&#x68;&#x77;&#97;&#114;&#x6b;&#46;&#103;&#x6f;&#x76;&#46;&#117;&#x6b;</a></p>

<h2>Peabody engages &lsquo;political intelligence&rsquo; services</h2>

<p>Peabody&rsquo;s application includes the mandatory <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387210_1.pdf">Statement of Community Involvement (SCI)</a>, which is required to show evidence that it has consulted on its plans with the local community. Peabody instructed a public affairs company called <a href="http://www.bellenden.co.uk/about-us/specialist-expertise/property-development/">Bellenden</a> to advise on its application, conduct the consultation exercise and prepare its SCI.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.bellenden.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/MarkGloverColour.jpg">Bellenden was founded and is run by former Chair of Southwark Labour and local councillor <a href="https://uk.linkedin.com/in/glovermark">Mark Glover</a>. It was named after the road in which <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/4075/statement_of_persons_nominated_and_notice_of_poll">he lives</a>, Bellenden road in Peckham. Glover stepped down as councillor in May 2014. Amongst other things, Bellenden offers its clients a <a href="http://www.bellenden.co.uk/public-affairs/political-intelligence/">&lsquo;political intelligence&rsquo; service</a>, which it says involves <strong> <em>&ldquo;learning how political parties and their individual members are thinking on any given issue&rdquo;</em> </strong> and then <strong> <em>&ldquo;seeks to enlarge and inform their thoughts on behalf of our clients.&rdquo;</em> </strong><br/>
With his 12 years as a senior Southwark councillor, we don&rsquo;t doubt that Mr Glover is very well placed to provide this service.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Council Housing - Going Up or Coming Down?]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2015/01/11/march-for-homes/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-11T12:21:55+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2015/01/11/march-for-homes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11416/housing_estates_and_sites_for_new_council_homes"><img class="right" src="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/Pictures/web/y/z/m/New-Council-Homes-deliver_633.jpg" width="400" height="270"></a>Just before Christmas Southwark Council issued a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1878/southwark_maps_out_1500_new_council_homes_in_just_four_years_as_part_of_the_most_ambitious_council_house_build_in_the_country">press release</a>, accompanied by a lovely <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11416/housing_estates_and_sites_for_new_council_homes">map</a> entitled <em>&ldquo;Housing Estates and Sites for New Council Homes&rdquo;</em>, which shows where 1500 of Southwark&rsquo;s 11000 new council homes will be built.</p>

<p>But as we showed in the <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/12/06/11000-new-private-and-social-council-homes-on-target/">previous blog</a>, this council-house building programme is not all it seems. For example, the 19 new homes planned on the East Dulwich estate (Gatebeck &amp; Southdown House), will be offset by 50 council homes which are being sold off on other parts of the estate - a net loss of 31 council homes in total<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://s0.geograph.org.uk/geophotos/02/70/11/2701156_6a4b82c2.jpg" width="300" height="200">Another site on the map, <em>Maydew House</em> will also show a net loss once completed. This 24-storey block containing 144 council flats overlooking Southwark Park, has been decanted <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Save-Maydew-House/316012601837">(amidst protest)</a> after the council <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/00,news,20152,440,00.htm">declared</a> the cost of repair <em>&ldquo;difficult to justify&rdquo;</em>. It is now being refurbished and 5 extra penthouse floors added to provide a total of 180 units, but only 74 will remain as council flats - a net loss of 70 council homes<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. The remaining 106 flats will all be sold off on the open market.</p>

<p>Building council homes is a popular pledge and one that we unquestionably support – it’s the best, most economical way of providing decent housing to those who most need it - but we are reminded of <a href="http://35percent.org/images/500newhomes.png">similar promises</a> from the not-so-distant past that were used to mask over the loss of the Heygate estate’s 1200 council homes<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>.</p>

<p>When we <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">blogged in October</a> about concerns that the new homes would only be replacements for council homes  sold off or demolished,  council leader Peter John reassured everyone that there would be a net gain of 11,000 council homes; he said -
<em>“To be absolutely clear, the 11,000 new homes that we promise to deliver will be new homes additional to our existing stock. ……These are new homes and do not include the existing stock of council housing.”</em></p>

<p>These latest findings show a different picture.  A council house building programme that depends upon ‘asset disposal’ and ‘estate renewal’ needs close scrutiny, if it is not going to end up leaving us with fewer council homes than we started with.</p>

<h2>March for Homes</h2>

<p><a href="http://marchforhomes.org"><img class="left" src="http://marchforhomes.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/MARCH_FOR_HOMES_SITE_LOGO.gif"></a>Housing (or the lack of it) is set to be a key issue in the parliamentary and mayoral elections in May. A <a href="http://marchforhomes.org/">&lsquo;March for Homes&rsquo;</a> has been called for Jan 31st by the <a href="http://www.southlondonpa.org/">South London People&rsquo;s Assembly</a>. It has an impressive list of supporters (including the 35% campaign) and is now to have two legs: one starting from South London and one from East London, both to converge on City Hall.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://li.zoocdn.com/c72dcb6efccb9584389cccf5dacc9330082f26fa_354_255.jpg" width="250" height="160">The South London leg will assemble at St Mary&rsquo;s Churchyard - in the shadow of <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/05/05/manx-connections-the-off-shore-home-of-the-elephants-developers/">Strata Tower</a>, <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/01/11/flogging-the-elephant/">One the Elephant</a> and the planned <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2013/08/10/towering-disgrace/">360 Tower</a>: three towers comprising 1162 new homes with zero social housing; the perfect place to start.<br/>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>West Hendon residents fight for their homes</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="https://fbcdn-sphotos-b-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xfp1/t31.0-8/c0.145.851.315/p851x315/10714465_1542589322623724_2087822952488384127_o.jpg" width="450" height="200">Meanwhile, residents of the <a href="http://www.londontenants.org/Pages/projectsderrick.htm">West Hendon estate</a> face a <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/legal/public-inquiry-to-investigate-misuse-of-compulsory-purchase-orders/7007668.article">public inquiry</a> into the compulsory purchase of their homes. The West Hendon regeneration is for 2,000 new homes and requires the demolition of 500 social rented units to be replaced by 250 affordable rent (up to 80% market rent).<br/>
They have organised a day of events on Jan 22nd:</p>

<ul>
<li>2pm: <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Focus-E15-Mothers/602860129757343">Focus E15 Mothers</a> talk about their campaign</li>
<li>4-5pm: Hot soup and rolls</li>
<li>5pm: March from the estate to the Public Inquiry at Hendon Town Hall</li>
<li>6pm: Rally outside Hendon Town Hall, joined by Women from The <a href="http://newera4all.org/">New Era campaign</a>, speakers from the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Our-West-Hendon/1476545849228072">Our West Hendon Group</a>, <a href="http://radicalhousingnetwork.org/">Radical Housing Network</a> , <a href="http://www.unitetheunion.org/">Unite The Union</a> and other estates in Barnet.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Fifty shades of embarrassment</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.independent.co.uk/incoming/article9969422.ece/alternates/w620/shades-of-gross.jpg" width="300" height="200">A marketing video for <a href="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/new-homes/london/southwark/one-blackfriars">One Blackfriars</a> tells us who this housing is really for, if we were in any doubt - people who can afford to go househunting in helicopters.</p>

<p>The video features a sexy affluent white young professional couple, indulging in Fifty Shades of Grey fantasies as they view One Blackfriars&#8217; swish appartments. The video was quickly removed from the web after widespread ridicule in the national press: <br/>
<a href="http://www.standard.co.uk/news/london/luxury-london-flat-advert-branded-the-creepiest-thing-you-will-ever-see-9966793.html">Evening Standard - &lsquo;London flat advert branded the creepiest thing you will ever see&rsquo;</a> <br/>
<a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/business/news/one-blackfriars-shades-of-gross-ad-for-luxury-flats-is-dropped-9969098.html">The Independent - &lsquo;Gross ad for luxury flats is dropped&rsquo;</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/architecture-design-blog/2015/jan/05/american-psycho-redrow-property-promo-pulled-after-twitterstorm">The Guardian - &lsquo;Property promo pulled after twitterstorm&rsquo;</a></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.savoyrealty.co.uk/sites/default/files/field/image/18360_lg.jpg?slideshow=true&slideshowAuto=false&slideshowSpeed=4000&speed=350&transition=elastic" width="200" height="250"><em>One Blackfriars</em> was granted planning permission by Southwark Council in July 2007, despite objections from English Heritage, Lambeth Council, Westminster Council and the Royal Parks. It will have 274 flats, none of which will be social rented or affordable. Instead an in-lieu payment of £29m is to be paid by developers St George, which is a fraction of the <a href="http://www.propertyweek.com/berkeley-buys-london-beetham-tower/5026546.article">£700m</a> Gross Development Value i.e. the total estimated sales value of all the appartments.</p>

<p>An FOI request for the viability assessment which justified this generous deal has been <a href="https://www.whatdotheyknow.com/request/2nd_economic_viability_study_for">lodged</a> with Southwark Council.</p>

<h2>Viability on the agenda</h2>

<p>The viability assessment fiasco is firmly on the agenda in the run up to the elections. In an <a href="http://www.24dash.com/news/housing/2015-01-08-My-housing-career-Peter-Marsh">interview</a> with <em>24Dash Housing</em>, a former housing quango chief has estimated that viability assessments caused the loss of £1bn of affordable housing and that many in the sector <em>&ldquo;consider these appraisals something of a joke&rdquo;</em>. The Guardian&rsquo;s editorial has <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/jan/01/guardian-view-affordable-housing-developers-must-made-show-sums">branded</a> the appraisal loophole a <em>&lsquo;public betrayal&rsquo;</em> and has called for developers to <em>&ldquo;show their sums&rdquo;</em>. A reporter who <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2014/sep/17/truth-property-developers-builders-exploit-planning-cities">wrote</a> about the problem earlier in the year has also put it at the top of his New Years wishlist, calling for <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2014/dec/29/what-i-want-cities-2015-severe-tax-on-empty-homes"><em>&ldquo;opening up this shady world of cooked books&rdquo;</em></a>.</p>

<p>We are also looking forward to helping lift the lid on the viability assessment scam. We have been talking to professionals from the across the sector, who will be helping us analyse the viability assessments obtained from the forthcoming Heygate &amp; Greenwich Peninsula Tribunal cases and put forward ideas for policy changes that could close the loophole. Watch this space!</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See paragraph 16 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s36276/Report%20East%20Dulwich%20Estate%20Regeneration%20Scheme%20and%20Scheme%20Finance%20Update.pdf">this March 2013 Cabinet Report</a><a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See paragraph 132 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s49973/Report%20Qtr%202%202014-15%20Capital%20Monitor.pdf">this November 2014 Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>This is an extract from the <a href="https://www.scribd.com/doc/198503633/EandC-RegenMk1SLRplans">2002 E&amp;C Regeneration Masterplan</a><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Council Sells Council Homes to Build New (Social &amp; Private) 'Council' Homes]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/12/06/11000-new-private-and-social-council-homes-on-target/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-06T09:16:18+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2014/12/06/11000-new-private-and-social-council-homes-on-target</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">wrote</a> in October about the council&rsquo;s plan to earmark a number of its housing estates for demolition using an <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SNhat.pdf">&lsquo;Asset Performance Evaluation Tool&rsquo;</a>, which would take into account factors like residents&#8217; income. The results of its survey were supposed to be presented at next week&rsquo;s Cabinet meeting, but the <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50476/Report%20Pipeline%20for%20the%20Delivery%20of%201500%20New%20Council%20Homes.pdf">December Cabinet report</a> shows that this has now been postponed until January.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50476/Report%20Pipeline%20for%20the%20Delivery%20of%201500%20New%20Council%20Homes.pdf">December Cabinet report</a> makes interesting reading: it concedes that its estate renewal programme alone may not provide enough capacity for its 11,000 proposed new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes and suggests two additional strategies:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Buying affordable housing built through s106 agreements directly from developers. (see <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50476/Report%20Pipeline%20for%20the%20Delivery%20of%201500%20New%20Council%20Homes.pdf">para. 58</a>).</p></li>
<li><p>Purchasing land that becomes available on the open market. (see <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50476/Report%20Pipeline%20for%20the%20Delivery%20of%201500%20New%20Council%20Homes.pdf">para. 60</a>)</p></li>
</ol>


<p>We can see two obvious problems with these new strategies:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Southwark&rsquo;s track record on securing affordable housing through s106 obligations is extremely poor. The viability assessment loophole means that developers often get away with building no affordable housing whatsoever. In those cases where affordable housing is provided, it normally takes the form of shared ownership and affordable rent (80% market), which are of little benefit unless these are the kind of &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes that Southwark is looking to provide.</p></li>
<li><p>We have already <a href="http://35percent.org/heygate-regeneration-faq/">reported</a> on Southwark&rsquo;s loss on the sale of its 25-acre Heygate site at a knock-down price to developer Lend Lease. We don&rsquo;t know how much it sold the Aylesbury for, but we think it&rsquo;s unlikely to recover the estimated £150m cost<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> of demolishing the 60-acre estate. So it doesn&rsquo;t need us to point out the absurdity of selling off structurally-sound council estates on the cheap and then buying back land from the private sector in order to build new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes.</p></li>
</ol>


<p><a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50478/Appendix%202%20Direct%20Delivery%20Sites.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/DirectDeliverySites.png" width="400" height="750"></a>The December Cabinet report also provided an update on the council&rsquo;s progress with its 11,000 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes &lsquo;Direct Delivery&rsquo; programme. Phase one of the programme involving the &lsquo;delivery&rsquo; of 1,500 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes by 2018 is now being finalised, with sites for 837 of these new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes now identified. <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50478/Appendix%202%20Direct%20Delivery%20Sites.pdf">Appendix 2</a> of the report gives a detailed schedule of these 837 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes and where they are to be located.</p>

<p>However, a closer look at the schedule reveals that many of these won&rsquo;t be council homes and that some are being funded by selling off existing stock. For example, the first two entries on the list are supposedly providing 27 new council homes on the East Dulwich estate (Gatebeck House:9 &amp; Southdown House:18). But it doesn&rsquo;t say that a third of these will be for shared ownership<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>; neither does it mention that these 27 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes on the East Dulwich estate, are being funded by selling off land and 50 existing council homes on other parts of the estate: <em>&ldquo;with £2.2m to be raised from the sale of 24 drying room conversions; £8.76m from the sale of 50 voids-for-sale and £4.1m to be raised from the disposal of land&rdquo;</em>.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<p>The next entry on the Direct Delivery schedule is Willow Walk near Old Kent Road, which is supposedly providing 75 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes. However, according to paragraphs 5 &amp; 6 of the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/284022_1.pdf">planning report</a> for this development, the 75 units comprise only 21 social rented homes, plus 54 rooms for temporary accommodation (replacing the existing temporary accommodation unit) - very welcome no doubt but not 75 council homes.</p>

<p>Next on the schedule is the site of the former Nunhead Community Centre, which is supposedly providing 8 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes. What it doesn&rsquo;t mention is that a large (1000 sqm) council-owned community centre is being demolished to make way for these and that the 8 new council homes will be <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/304415_1.pdf">accompanied</a> by 14 new homes for private sale.</p>

<p>Another council-owned community centre and some workshops are being demolished in Sumner road, Peckham. The schedule says that this site will provide 112 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes. What it doesn&rsquo;t say is that less than half of these (50) will be social-rented; 20 will be shared ownership and the remaining 42 units will be &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes for private sale. (see <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9555190">planning docs</a>)</p>

<p>Of the 25 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes built on the former Masterman House garages in Camberwell, only 15 will be social rented; the remainder will also be &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes for private sale. Just 34 of the 116 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes planned for Commmercial Way will be social rented and so the list goes on. We can&rsquo;t find details for many of the sites listed in the schedule, but we estimate that only around half of the 837 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes listed will be &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes as we know them. The remainder will be shared ownership and &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes for private sale, which doesn&rsquo;t come as a surprise in the wake of the revelations stemming from <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/18/southwark-mipim-and-the-11000-new-council-homes/">our reporting</a> of Southwark&rsquo;s MIPIM attendance this year.</p>

<h2>Footing the bill of regeneration</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://i.huffpost.com/gen/1713650/thumbs/o-ELEPHANT-AND-CASTLE-STATION-facebook.jpg" width="300" height="175">The <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/5293">long-running dispute</a> over who should pay for the capacity upgrades to the northern line tube station in order to meet increased demand from developments, has finally come to an end. Southwark News <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SNroundabout.pdf">reports</a> that of the £154m total cost, TFL have agreed to pay £91m while the council is left to find the remaining £63m. The council&rsquo;s regeneration partner Lend Lease is making a contribution of just £16.3m<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> towards the council&rsquo;s bill - proof that the regeneration partnership is not an equal one, with Southwark bearing the lion&rsquo;s share of costs and Lend Lease reaping the Elephantine profits.</p>

<h2>Untrustworthy imagery</h2>

<p>Lend Lease got a <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/private_eye.jpg">mention</a> in the latest edition of Private Eye. This time for a development in Chiswick, where its PR firm have been accused of producing misleading imagery. The column also pointed out that Paul Dimoldenberg, the head of Lend Lease&rsquo;s PR firm which created the images, also happens to be leader of the Labour group at Westminster council. We can add that Cllr Dimoldenberg also used to be a senior council officer at Southwark.</p>

<p>Our hats go off to Mr Dimoldenberg&rsquo;s firm for its PR image trickery. The following is a visualisation image from the Heygate application. <br/>
<img src="http://www.elephantandcastle-lendlease.com/wp-content/uploads/Homepage-Header-2-Not-sure-if-this-size-image-will-work1.jpg"></p>

<p>Looks nice doesn&rsquo;t it? but what the image doesn&rsquo;t tell you is that this is one of the developments&#8217; 12 &lsquo;raised courtyards&rsquo;, which are enclosed by buildings and will have zero public access:<br/>
<a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/267119_1.pdf"><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/heygate_raised_courtyards2.png"></a></p>

<h2>Coronet uncorrugated</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.theatrestrust.org.uk/store/ttdb/ttt0048/lowres/010997_regular.jpg?1410824878" width="300" height="600">New photographs have been <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SNcoronet.pdf">published</a> showing what the Art Deco Coronet building looks like behind its corrugated blue facade. <br/>
The Coronet is currently under threat of demolition from the shopping centre redevelopment. The shopping centre and neighbouring site are being redeveloped by real estate hedge fund DV4. George Soros backed DV4 is based in the British Virgin Islands and managed by <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2041229/Tory-donor-Jamie-Ritblat-snaps-Olympic-Village-knock-price--costing-275m.html">Delancey&rsquo;s Jamie Ritblatt</a>.</p>

<p>The Theatres Trust has recently submitted an application to have the Coronet listed. You can read more about the campaign on the <a href="http://www.theatrestrust.org.uk/resources/theatres/show/3344-coronet-london">Theatres Trust website</a>, the Save the Coronet campaign <a href="http://coronettheatre.co.uk/home/save-the-coronet/">web page</a> and <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/davehillblog/2014/dec/07/how-the-coronet-can-help-the-elephant">this article</a> by the Guardian&rsquo;s Dave Hill. <br/>
</br></p>

<h2>Unfair trial</h2>

<p>After being unlawfully evicted from his home, having his possessions destroyed and being left street homeless by Southwark council, a Sudanese refugee <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/crime/judge-blasts-southwark-council-for-evicting-sudanese-tenant-and-destroying-his-possessions-9796994.html">won</a> a long-running court case against the council in October. After spending six-figure sums on top QCs to fight the case against the claimaint (who had no legal representation), the council declared last week that the trial was &lsquo;unfair&rsquo; and &lsquo;clearly wrong&rsquo;. An <a href="http://nearlylegal.co.uk/blog/2014/11/southwark-not-appealing/">article</a> about the case by the Giles Peaker, a partner specialising in housing at solicitors Anthony Gold, sums up Southwark&rsquo;s attitude well: <em>&ldquo;disingenuous in the extreme&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<h2>Heygate viability assessment FOI/EIR appeal</h2>

<p>The ongoing battle to disclose the Heygate development viability assessment continues. The Information Tribunal has called a final hearing on 21st January to resolve the ongoing dispute concerning the implementation of its <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/FirstTierDecisionHeygate.pdf">May 2014 decision notice</a>. The hearing will be in closed session attended only by Lend Lease &amp; Southwark&rsquo;s counsel, who will recieve directions as to exactly which of the 22 appendices can be withheld. The Tribunal had previously ruled that the financial model in appendix 22 and the figures related to commercial negotiations for its retail floorspace could be withheld, but there has been a dispute over exactly which of the 22 appendices are related to these. We are expecting the Tribunal to order the viability assessment be disclosed within a short period after the hearing (barring further appeals and heeldragging by Lend Lease &amp; Southwark). After nearly 3 years of battling for its disclosure we are looking forward to finally being able to see why Lend Lease has been so reluctant to show its sums.</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See paragraph 142 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s43556/Report%20Selection%20of%20a%20Preferred%20Partner%20to%20Work%20with%20the%20Council%20to%20Deliver%20the%20Regeneration%20of%20the.pdf">this Jan 2014 council briefing report</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See paragraph 19 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s36276/Report%20East%20Dulwich%20Estate%20Regeneration%20Scheme%20and%20Scheme%20Finance%20Update.pdf">this March 2013 Cabinet report</a>.  <a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See paragraph 16 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s36276/Report%20East%20Dulwich%20Estate%20Regeneration%20Scheme%20and%20Scheme%20Finance%20Update.pdf">this March 2013 Cabinet report</a>.  <a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>See &lsquo;E&amp;C Strategic Transport&rsquo; contributions in each of Lend Lease&rsquo;s planning applications: <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/249091_1.pdf">One the Elephant (£2m)</a>, <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/224053_1.pdf">Heygate masterplan (£11.7m)</a> &amp; <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/238280_1.pdf">Heygate phase 1 (£2.6m)</a> <a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury Estate - Back to the Drawing Board?]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/15/aylesbury-estate-back-to-the-drawing-board/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-15T15:13:56+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/15/aylesbury-estate-back-to-the-drawing-board</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/pagenotfound.png" width="300" height="200">The planning documents for the Aylesbury estate outline masterplan have been <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557153">removed</a> from Southwark council&rsquo;s planning portal. The documents for the first development site under the masterplan have also been <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557152">removed</a>. The applications were <a href="http://35percent.org/images/scan0027.pdf">lodged</a> on 25th September and the documents uploaded about a month later. On inquiry, Southwark said that the applications had been <em>&ldquo;uploaded in error, they are currently invalid and not open to consultation.&rdquo;</em> It also said that <em>&ldquo;as soon as the relevant documentation has been received .. and been made valid they will be posted on the website&rdquo;</em>. It is not clear whether the applications have been withdrawn and now need to be re-submitted. Our <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">previous blog</a> on the Aylesbury applications pointed out - amongst other things - that 934 social rented homes are to be lost if the development goes ahead as planned.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, Aylesbury leaseholders are fighting to get a fair deal from the council and its development partners Notting Hill Housing &amp; Barratt Homes. A leaseholders&#8217; <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50093/Report%20Deputation%20Requests.pdf">deputation</a> will be submitting <a href="https://halag.files.wordpress.com/2014/11/alag_depuation18nov_finalversion.pdf">5 demands</a> to the council&rsquo;s Cabinet meeting on Tuesday. Amongst their very sensible requirements is one that any council officer who values their homes is actually qualified to do so, as it turns out this is not always the case: a leaseholder&rsquo;s complaint to the recognised professional body (RICS) could not be dealt with because the officers concerned were not RICS qualified or registered. The leaseholders have requested instead that valuations are conducted by the District Valuer Service.</p>

<p>At the same meeting, Southwark will also be receiving a deputation from the <a href="http://www.sgto.org.uk/">Southwark Group of Tenants Organisation</a>, who also have some <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s49943/Appendix%206%20Six%20alternative%20pledges%20from%20SGTO.pdf">suggestions</a>, this time about improving the six pledges Southwark has made for conducting its consultation on building 11,000 new council homes. Southwark should adopt these improved pledges, it will be a step in the right direction, but it is also <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/08/southwark-fails-to-deliver/">clear</a> that the Council already has definite ideas about how these new homes will be provided, including estate regeneration and estate infill.</p>

<h2>Head in the clouds</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/betterelephant/status/531882170424786944"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/tweet.png" width="400" height="800"></a>Southwark&rsquo;s Head of Regeneration Councillor Mark Williams, obviously got a bit giddy last week at the topping out ceremony of Lend Lease&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.onetheelephant.com/apartments/browse-apartments"><strong>One the Elephant</strong></a> tower (or maybe Lend Lease plied him with too much champagne). He <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/01/11/flogging-the-elephant/">tweeted</a> from the rooftop ceremony about the wonderful view as well as the <em>&ldquo;new homes, jobs and leisure centre for local residents&rdquo;</em>. A second tweet claimed that the development was providing £12.5m towards the new leisure centre (costing £25m), but as we can see below from the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/305818_1.pdf">legal agreement</a> the figure is actually only £3.5m. Lend Lease got out of providing any on-site affordable housing or making any payment in-lieu for the development through the magic of viability assessments and as we showed in a <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/01/11/flogging-the-elephant/">previous blog</a> Southwark should have netted £33.2m under its <a href="http://35percent.org/images/affordablehousingspg.pdf">in-lieu affordable housing payment tariff</a>.<br/>
<a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/305818_1.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/leisurecentrecontribution.png"></a></p>

<p>Southwark also <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LandRegistry_OneTheElephant.pdf">sold</a> the <strong>One the Elephant</strong> land to Lend Lease for the price of £6.5m (£4.6m per acre), which is a bargain considering that the gross development value of the tower will be upwards of £230m<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Our interactive map also shows how this compares to other land sales at the Elephant:</p>

<center>
<iframe src="http://35percent.org/map.html" width="800" height="600"></iframe>
</br><font size="2">Click <a href="http://35percent.org/map.html">here</a> to view our interactive map in a separate browser window</font>
</center>


<p></br></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/robertabwMP/status/531797457492250624"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/blackmanwoods.png" width="400" height="650"></a>While Cllr Williams&#8217; head was in the clouds, Labour shadow minister for planning, Roberta Blackman-Woods, was keeping her feet firmly on the ground when she visited the Heygate site last week, <a href="https://twitter.com/robertabwMP/status/531797457492250624">tweeting</a> that Lend Lease&rsquo;s scheme was <em>&ldquo;very interesting&rdquo;</em>. Ms Woods might also be interested in the risks local authorities run when they enter into partnership agreements with global property giants like Lend Lease, as illustrated by <a href="http://www.architectureanddesign.com.au/news/lend-lease-nsw-government-dispute-halts-barangaroo">this story</a> from its other major development site in Sydney, Australia, where city authorities stand to lose millions after losing a bitter court battle with Lend Lease over a profit-share agreement.</p>

<p></br>
</br>
</br></p>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>This is based on an expected average sales value of £815 per sq foot, which was the average sales price <a href="http://www.colliers.com/~/media/Files/EMEA/UK/research/residential/201202-central-london-residential-market.pdf">achieved</a> by the Strata tower.  <strong>One the Elephant</strong> comprises 269,000sq ft of residential floorspace in total; the total expected residential sales is therefore £219m (269k X £815), plus 13,000 sq ft of retail in <strong>One the Elephant</strong>&rsquo;s pavilion with an approximate value of £10m.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Southwark Fails to Deliver]]></title>
    <link href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/08/southwark-fails-to-deliver/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-08T19:10:35+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/08/southwark-fails-to-deliver</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/viability.png" width="300" height="200">The Heygate viability assessment saga took a new turn last week. Southwark Council failed to produce the assessment by the given deadline and all parties have been called back to a Tribunal hearing on 11th Dec.</p>

<p>We can only speculate on the cause of the delay, but Southwark Council is beginning to look a bit ridiculous. After spending a six-figure sum and two and a half years appealing against the Information Commissioner, last week Southwark claimed that it has <em>&ldquo;always been keen to see this matter resolved as quickly as possible&rdquo;</em> and that <em>&ldquo;the final version of the document is now on its way to Mr Glasspool&rdquo;</em> .</p>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/SN29Oct2014.pdf"><img class="left" src="http://allpeoplesparty.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/11/Southwark-Council-Release-Heygate-Deal-Now.png" width="500" height="300"></a></p>

<p>There are still serious oustanding questions about many aspects of the redevelopment, not just about the amount of affordable housing that the assessment can help answer (see our <a href="http://35percent.org/heygate-regeneration-faq/">FAQ</a> for a summary of the issues). Both the Information Commissioner and Information Tribunal have ruled that it is heavily in the public interest for this document to be revealed; Southwark should release the assessment without any further delay.</p>

<h2>Spot the difference</h2>

<p>While the tribunal case drags on, Lend Lease are motoring forward with the latest detailed planning application for the Heygate (now known as <a href="http://www.elephantpark.co.uk/">&lsquo;Elephant Park&rsquo;</a>). The application for <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1779/lend_lease_submits_detailed_planning_application_for_around_600_new_homes_at_elephant_park">West Grove (phase MP2)</a> comprises 593 new homes and 43,000 square feet of new retail space.</p>

<p>One thing we have noticed is that the <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/5621">visualisations</a> of the new Heygate supplied during public consultations on the outline application, were based on minimum plot/building sizes. To nobody&rsquo;s surprise it is the maximum plot sizes that Lend Lease are applying for in their detailed applications and as we can see from the image below<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, it makes for a significant difference. It seems that it&rsquo;s only now that we are becoming privy to the true scale of development.</p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/389783_1.pdf"><img src="http://35percent.org/images/parameterheights.png"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/389805_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/mp2affordablehousing.png" width="300" height="300"></a>Despite its size however, Lend Lease can only find room for 26 social rented flats in its latest phase, which won&rsquo;t make much of a dent in Southwark&rsquo;s 20,000-strong housing waiting list.
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>More viability struggles</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not just in Southwark where people are challenging the viability trump card and fighting developers for properly affordable housing. Two notable examples elsewhere are <a href="http://www.wcdg.net/content/waterloos-don-quixote-one-man-against-world">Riverside Communities vs Braeburn estates</a> at the Southbank&rsquo;s Shell Centre development, where developers are getting away with building just 11% affordable housing; and <a href="http://www.eastlondonlines.co.uk/2014/11/stokey-local-votes-to-take-planning-proposal-fight-to-court-of-appeal/">Stokey Local Community Group vs Sainsburys</a> who want to build a new supermarket and flats, but have reduced their offer of affordable housing from 50% to 17%. In both cases, campaigners are trying to get to the truth about viability and pierce the legal smoke screens of commercial confidentiality.</p>

<h2>Cooltan stuffed</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/11/img_0363.jpg?w=208&h=182" width="300" height="200">A new housing and student residence development was approved for Walworth road&rsquo;s Blanchard site last week, to the great disappointment of local mental health charity <a href="http://www.cooltanarts.org.uk/">Cooltan Arts</a> and its many supporters.  A previously approved application contained a legally binding agreement to supply Cooltan (who were previous occupants of the site) with new premises. The site (plus agreement) was sold to another developer, the planning agreement lapsed and the new developer said it was not economically viable to provide Cooltan with what it needed. Southwark Council claimed it had no power to enforce the lapsed agreement and the application was duly approved.</p>

<h2>Coming soon&hellip; a fairer future</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/fairerfuture.png">Southwark Council is beginning its consultation on the New Southwark Plan, which will both incorporate and replace the existing Southwark Plan and Core Strategy planning policy frameworks. It will determine how all land in Southwark will be developed - or not as the case may be. Contentious issues are likely going to be the possible regeneration of council estates, the density of new developments and the protection of green spaces.</p>

<p>The paragraph below in the foreword of the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11161/new_southwark_plan">draft new Plan</a> caught our eye. Southwark&rsquo;s intention to use infill land and pursue estate regeneration as a way of providing 11,000 new council homes, explains why it feels the need to make a <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s47489/Appendix%201%20Draft%20Charter%20of%20Principles.pdf">Charter of Principles</a> of good behaviour when it consults with its council estate residents.<br/>
<img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/newsouthwarkplan.png"></p>

<p>The consultation period for this first draft of the New Southwark Plan and this proposal lasts until 6th March 2015, but Southwark isn&rsquo;t wasting time: an &lsquo;asset management&rsquo; process is already <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">in train</a> and will be making recommendations about potential renewal/regeneration sites to Southwark&rsquo;s Cabinet in December.</p>

<h2>Estate renewal conference</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk/2014/09/30/conference-delivering-estate-renewal/"><img class="right" src="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk/futureoflondon/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/Delivering-Estate-Renewal-postcard-front-1024x721.jpg" width="400" height="300"></a>Last week saw a <a href="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk">Future of London</a> conference entitled <a href="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk/2014/09/30/conference-delivering-estate-renewal/">&lsquo;Delivering Estate Renewal&rsquo;</a>. The conference was co-sponsored by Lend Lease who are described in the <a href="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk/2014/09/30/conference-delivering-estate-renewal/">conference programme</a> as &lsquo;estate-savvy developers&rsquo;. The speakers included representatives from Lend Lease, Notting Hill&rsquo;s CEO Kate Davies and Southwark&rsquo;s Head of Regeneration, Stephen Platts.</p>

<p>A detailed <a href="http://chrisbrown.regen.net/2014/11/10/estate-renewal-community-coproduction/">write-up</a> of the event by Chris Brown from <a href="http://www.iglooregeneration.co.uk/">Igloo Regeneration</a> describes the arithmetic behind the crude logic of estate renewal: a council estate&rsquo;s rental income is subtracted from forecasted maintenance costs to give a &lsquo;net present cost&rsquo;; this is then compared against the estimated development value of the estate as a cleared site, so that local authorities can <em>&ldquo;get rid of the financial underperformers&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Brown says that he was <em>&ldquo;taken to task&rdquo;</em> during the conference, by Southwark&rsquo;s Stephen Platts over his <em>&ldquo;description of the Heygate estate renewal as a social disaster&rdquo;</em> and that his attempts to highlight the social cost of displacing communities seemed to fall on deaf ears.</p>

<h2>Baby shard gets go-ahead</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/imageuploads/1415187088_46.233.112.163.jpg" width="300" height="400">Irvine Sellar and son James attended Southwark&rsquo;s planning committee meeting last Tuesday evening (in a chauffeur-driven limousine). They were there to watch the the council&rsquo;s labour controlled planning committee <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7931">wave through</a> their plans for a 26 storey shard satellite tower.
In presenting the proposals, James Sellar claimed that <em>&ldquo;the proposal before you tonight will for the first time bring residents into the heart of this regeneration. It will create homes and bring vibrancy, ensuring that people working in London Bridge have the opportunity to live there as well.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>However, the Sellars had submitted a viability assessment showing that they couldn&rsquo;t afford to provide any on-site affordable housing provision. Instead, they first <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7915">proposed</a> to meet their affordable housing obligations by funding the stalled redevelopment of the Wood Dene Estate in Peckham. After criticism from opposition councillors the developers have now promised to &lsquo;try&rsquo; and find somewhere in the north of the borough instead. Failing this they have agreed to make an in-lieu payment of £18m - somewhat less than the price of some penthouses currently <a href="http://www.altomagazine.com/news/inside-londons-premier-penthouse-at-neo-bankside-4283694">being sold</a> in the area.</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Image taken from the planning <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9556728">application&rsquo;s</a>&rsquo;s <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/389783_1.pdf">reconciliation statement</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
