<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[35% Campaign]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.35percent.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.35percent.org/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-11T15:59:37+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.35percent.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[EAN]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Affordable Rent Is Not Social Rent]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2015/03/10/affordable-rent-is-not-social/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-10T20:37:50+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2015/03/10/affordable-rent-is-not-social</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/279910_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/wolvertons106SR2.png" width="400" height="400"></a>We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">blogged previously</a> about the last phase of the Aylesbury redevelopment, where we saw plans waived through as social rent, only to discover afterwards that the s106 legal agreement contained a corrupted definition of the term social rent, which referred to the legal definition of affordable rent (80% market rent).
</br>
</br></p>

<p><a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk/Manor-Place-Exhibition-Banners.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Manorplace_socialrent2.png" width="300" height="320"></a>Notting Hill Housing Group, which is developing the remaining phases of the Aylesbury estate, has taken a different approach: instead of substituting social rent for affordable rent via the back door, it is openly defining affordable rent as a subcategory of social rent. Its <a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk/Manor-Place-Exhibition-Banners.pdf">consultation document</a> for <a href="manorplacedepot.co.uk">Manor Place development</a> (a former Council <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/10070/recycling/1364/reuse_and_recycling_centre">refuse depot</a> in Walworth) shows rents for its new social rented homes will be set at <em>&ldquo;up to 50% of local market rents&rdquo;</em>. Those familiar with housing policy will know that social rents are not determined by Housing Associations; they are determined by the National Rent Regime regulatory framework - and that they are not set in relation to market rents; they are set in relation to average household incomes.</p>

<p>50% of market rents may sound like a good deal to some, but in an area where rents have rocketed to an average £300 per week for a 1-bed flat, it represents a 50% increase above exsiting social rent levels. The crucial difference is that market rents rise well beyond wages, which is an important consideration in an area where the average household income of a council tenant is £9,100 per year<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Some might see this as an inevitable consequence of the market and beyond the control of public authorities, but it is important to remember that this is council-owned land being sold off to a publicly-funded Housing Association, which could have been used to build much needed truly affordable and truly social rented homes.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/affordablerentstudy.png" width="350" height="300"></a>Southwark has been undertaking <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/download/2914/affordable_rent_in_southwark_2011">a study</a> of the affordability of affordable rent in the borough. <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">This spreadheet</a> from the study shows that the minimum household income required to afford one of Notting Hill&rsquo;s new 50% market rent &lsquo;social rented&rsquo; homes at Manor Place is £39,860 per year - well beyond the £9,100 average household income of council tenants in Walworth and the £21,000 average household income in Walworth.</p>

<p>Notting Hill are also involved in the Council&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/823/regeneration_projects/1798/elmington_regeneration/4">Elmingtion estate regeneration</a> where the council has just <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s48494/Report%20CPO%20for%20Elmington%20Estate.pdf">issued a Compulsory Purchase Order</a> on 144 homes in phase 3 of the regeneration. Phases 1 &amp; 2, where Notting Hill has already <a href="http://directobjective.blogspot.co.uk/2011/12/elmington-estate-revisited.html">demolished 373 council homes</a>, is nearing completion and the new &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; homes are currently being marketed in the development, which has now rebranded <a href="http://www.camberwellfields.com/">&lsquo;Camberwell Fields&rsquo;</a>.
<a href="http://www.camberwellfields.com/"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/camberwell-fields-logo.png"></a></p>

<p>Paragraph 12 of this <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s30291/Report%20Disposal%20of%20the%20Councils%20freehold%20interest%20in%20Elmington%20estate%20sites%20C%20D%20E%20and%20G%20Camberw.pdf">Council report</a> confirms that all replacement 1 &amp; 2 bed social housing in the redevelopment will be set at 65% market rent. According to <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">Southwark&rsquo;s figures</a> this will amount to £194 per week, which is more than double the existing council rents. Residents who have been &lsquo;decanted&rsquo; from the estate and wish to exercise their right to return, will therefore need to be able to afford a 100% rent hike.</p>

<p>Furthermore, the main component of the new &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; housing on the Elmington is shared ownership. Notting Hill has just released the price list for its new shared ownership homes in the development. This shows that the cheapest of the &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; shared ownership homes is a 1-bed flat priced at £380k, for which you will need to buy a minimum 40% share will need to be earning a minimum household income of £51,824 in order to pay the £1,438 per month rent, mortgage repayment and service charge. This is not affordable to those currently living in Camberwell, where the average household income is £24,400.</p>

<p><a href="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/properties/lq-trafalgar-place/?preview=true"><img class="left" src="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/LQ-@-Trafalfar-Place-Brochure.jpg" width="250" height="300"></a>Last week, L&amp;Q <a href="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/properties/lq-trafalgar-place/?preview=true">launched</a> its shared ownership homes on the redeveloped Heygate estate. The launch happened to coincide with the latest phase of the private flats being launched at a <a href="http://www.thestandard.com.hk/news_detail.asp?art_id=154851&amp;con_type=3">sales event in Hong Kong</a>. According to L&amp;Q&rsquo;s <a href="http://lqpricedin.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/LQ-@-Trafalgar-Place-Pricelist-12-bed-launch-2.pdf">price list</a>, the cheapest of the Heygate&rsquo;s new &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; shared ownership homes will set you back £126k for a 30% stake in a 1-bed flat, for which you will need to buy a 30% minimum share, requiring a household income of at least £57,500k per year. A 25% share in a 2-bed duplex will set you back £185,625, but with a minimum household income requirement of £64,500 it won&rsquo;t be long before you will be able to staircase up to full ownership of this duplex at a mere £742,500. It seems our council leader is finally delivering on his housing <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7585">pledge</a> to help poor Southwark residents on <em>&ldquo;£60-£80,000 a year – but who have absolutely no hope of buying&rdquo;</em>.   <br/>
</br></p>

<p><a href="http://southwark.communitymaps.org.uk/#/project/15?center=51.4653:-0.0707:12"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/interactivemap.png" width="250" height="250"></a>Last week Southwark Council also launched an <a href="http://southwark.communitymaps.org.uk/#/welcome">interactive map</a>, inviting people to suggest where it should build the 11,000 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes that it has pledged to build. Rumour has it that the Council is having a little difficulty identifying where these homes should be built, as vacant land in the borough is limited. In December, the Council even <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/12/06/11000-new-private-and-social-council-homes-on-target/">suggested</a> exploring the purchase of land on the open market from developers. Given its <a href="http://35percent.org/heygate-regeneration-faq/">track record</a> in negotiatiating with developers, we wonder why none of these new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes could be built on the vast estates that the Council is redeveloping (Heygate, Aylesbury, Wooddene &amp; Elmington etc)? Surely this would be better than selling the sites off to developers and corporated-minded Housing Associations, who provide nothing but a few unaffordable affordable homes in return?</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See sheet 8, row 9 of the Council&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">Dec 2014 Affordable Rent Study update</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Greenwich Developers Ordered to Show Their Sums]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2015/02/04/developers-ordered-to-show-their-sums/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-04T15:19:21+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2015/02/04/developers-ordered-to-show-their-sums</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://gsa-studios.com/images/uploads/projects/1168x650_greenwich.jpg" width="300" height="200">We reported last year how a residents group in Greenwich had followed our lead and requested the viability assessments justifying decisions to reduce affordable housing in the £5bn Greenwich Peninsula redevelopment. Similar to our request for the Heygate figures, Greenwich residents had won the support of the Information Commissioner but were then taken to appeal by the Council and developer Knight Dragon. We put them in touch with our legal friends at Leigh Day &amp; Monckton Chambers and expert witness <a href="http://www.northampton.ac.uk/directories/people/bob-colenutt">Dr Colenutt</a> who helped the campaigners take on the Council &amp; developer&rsquo;s barristers at an Information Tribunal hearing in October last year.</p>

<p>After a two month wait, the Tribunal issued its <a href="http://bit.ly/1zS9Qc0">decision notice</a> earlier this week. The decision was conclusive and damning; it rejected the Council&rsquo;s arguments and pointed out that councillors on Greenwich&rsquo;s planning committee had no more information about the viability figures than did the general public. Hong Kong developer Knight Frank&rsquo;s arguments about commercial confidentiality were also given short shrift by the Judge <strong> <em>&ldquo;This is a case where a company, robust enough to take on the development of a huge site over a period of 20 years.. immediately asks to be relieved of a planning obligation freely negotiated by its predecessor. It justifies this change on the basis of a downturn in house prices it knew about at the time of purchase, using a valuation model that looks at current values only and does not allow for change in the many factors that may affect a valuation over time. It seems to us that in those circumstances the public interest in openness about the figures is very strong.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p>In contrast to the Heygate decision where developer Lend Lease was allowed to withhold its financial model in appendix 22 of the assessment, the Greenwich decision took a much tougher line: <strong> <em>&lsquo;once it is accepted that the EIR regulations apply, it is necessary to apply them in their full rigour.  There is no room for an “EIR lite” approach&rsquo;</em> </strong> (para. 24) <br/>
There are more details about the Greenwich decision on the <a href="http://853blog.com/2015/02/03/greenwich-peninsula-social-cleansing-council-loses-battle-to-keep-developer-document-secret/">853 blog</a>.</p>

<h2>Viability for dummies</h2>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/viabilityfordummies.pdf"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/viabilityfordummies.png" width="300" height="400"></a>In terms of EIR case law, there was still some doubt following the Heygate decision about exactly what developers are allowed to withhold, especially in light of the ongoing legal battle over the interpretation of the Heygate decision notice. The Greenwich decision appears to have addressed that ambiguity and provided a clear steer as to what exactly is subject to disclosure - everything.</p>

<p>This should now clear the path for other community groups to obtain viability information and participate more meaningfully in planning issues.</p>

<p>In an attempt to help them do so, we have drafted a <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/viabilityfordummies.pdf">&lsquo;dummies&rsquo; guide</a> to viability, part 1 of which explains how to obtain viability information using EIR requests.</p>

<h2>Heygate Tribunal battle continues</h2>

<p>The ongoing battle over the interpretation of the Tribunal&rsquo;s May 2014 <a href="http://www.informationtribunal.gov.uk/DBFiles/Decision/i1279/London%20Borough%20of%20Southwark%20EA.2013.0162%20%2809.05.14%29.pdf">decision notice</a> continues. The decision allowed Lend Lease to withhold its financial development model projections on retail and office floorspace. The notice ordered the parties to get together and agree on dividing up the information for disclosure along those lines. It acknowledged that there may be &lsquo;grey areas&rsquo; and stated that if parties are unable to reach agreement then it will reconvene to settle the argument.
After many months of stalling and heel dragging by Southwark and Lend Lease, the Tribunal reconvened partially in October and was due to reconvene for a full hearing on 11th Dec last year. But Lend Lease&rsquo;s Commercial Director was unable to attend so the hearing was postponed. The hearing was finally able to take place on 21st January when parties made their arguments on how the information should be divided up according to the Tribunal&rsquo;s May 2014 decision.</p>

<p>During the hearing Lend Lease&rsquo;s counsel argued that protecting its financial model in appendix 22, also extended to protecting the inputs and outputs to the model found elsewhere in the report and its appendices. Mr Glasspool&rsquo;s counsel pointed out that the inputs and outputs did not form &lsquo;part of the model&rsquo; and would not expose the model&rsquo;s underlying formulas that Lend Lease had so vehemently argued were its &lsquo;trade secret&rsquo;.</p>

<p>The Tribunal is expected to issue a decision notice detailing exactly which information can be withheld some time in the next few weeks.</p>

<h2>Southwark joins 35% campaign</h2>

<p>Southwark Council issued a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1903/southwark_council_slams_plans_to_reduce_affordable_housing_contributions">press statement</a> earlier this week entitled <strong> <em>&ldquo;Southwark Council slams plans to reduce affordable housing contributions.&rdquo;</em> </strong> The statement says it <strong> <em>&ldquo;has hit out at government plans to allow developers to reduce affordable housing contributions&rdquo;</em> </strong>. It is referring to the governments new <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2015/feb/01/property-developers-affordable-housing-councils-empty-building">&lsquo;vacant building credit&rsquo;</a>, which is said to cut back even further the amount of affordable housing delivered through planning gain.</p>

<p>Much as we applaud Southwark&rsquo;s sentiment, we point out that it first needs to sort out its problem of allowing developers to get away with avoiding affordable housing by viability assessments. Two such examples are these developments currently under construction at the Elephant, both of which are being built on land sold to developers by the Council. Thanks to Southwark&rsquo;s failure to question the viability assessments submitted at planning, neither of these will provide any affordable housing and the payments in-lieu are a fraction of what they should have been according to Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://affordable.heroku.com/images/affordablehousingspg.pdf">in-lieu tariff</a>.     <br/>
<img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/tribecaonetheelephant.jpg"></p>

<p>You can read more detailed info about the Tribeca Square development <a href="http://35percent.org/tribeca-square/">here</a> and One The Elephant <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/01/11/flogging-the-elephant/">here.</a></p>

<h2>Aylesbury Occupied</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/B8_4AbdIAAAb-ir.jpg" width="300" height="600"> Housing activists have occupied empty homes on the Aylesbury estate. The activists took up occupation directly following last weekend&rsquo;s <a href="http://marchforhomes.org">March for Homes</a> and are protesting at the failure to address London&rsquo;s growing housing crisis.</p>

<p>In an <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/development/protestors-occupy-estate-earmarked-for-15bn-regeneration/7008068.article">interview</a> with Inside Housing, Councillor Williams, Southwark&rsquo;s Cabinet member for Regeneration claimed that the protesters <strong> <em>&ldquo;are risking the delivery of the very homes they claim to be campaigning for.&rdquo;</em> </strong> He went on to explain that <strong> <em>&ldquo;The scheme will be 50% affordable, with 75% of these rented and 25% for shared ownership.&rdquo;</em> </strong> We are unsurprised to note the semantic subtlety of Cllr Williams&#8217; omitting to use either the word <strong>&lsquo;social&rsquo;</strong> or <strong>&lsquo;affordable&rsquo;</strong> in conjunction with the word <strong>&lsquo;rented&rsquo;</strong>.</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyTLF.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyTLF.png" width="300" height="400"></a>Cllr Williams also claims that the protestors don&rsquo;t represent the Aylesbury residents, but <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/AylesburyTLF.pdf">this flyer</a> suggests that at least <a href="http://aylesburytenantsfirst.org.uk/">one tenants group</a> on the estate disagrees.</p>

<p>The Aylesbury occupiers have set up a website for their campaign <a href="http://fightfortheaylesbury.wordpress.com">http://fightfortheaylesbury.wordpress.com</a> and Twitter account: @OccupyAylesbury
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>Concrete Heartland</h2>

<p>Concrete Heartland, a film about the Heygate regeneration by Steven Ball and Rastko Novaković has now been released online. Following a number of screenings last year, it has now been uploaded for popular consumption and can be viewed online at <a href="http://concreteheartland.info">http://concreteheartland.info</a><br/>
Assembled from 12 years of archive materials, the film charts the struggles of the local community to keep their homes, stay living in the area and maintain communal benefits in the face of the advance of this now notorious &lsquo;urban redevelopment programme&rsquo;.</p>

<h2>West Hendon estate</h2>

<p>BBC&rsquo;s The One Show featured a piece on the West Hendon estate on Monday. Due to the notorius viability arguments, residents there are being forced out of the area after developers Barratt argued that it was no longer possible to rehouse them in the new development. The story sounds all too familiar to us down here in Southwark.
</center></p>

<iframe width="350" height="197" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5OXc814Q9ps" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p></center></p>

<h2>Affordable housing tenants excluded from communal gardens</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/media/brochure/b2678/files/assets/common/page-substrates/page0015.jpg" width="300" height="200">Southwark&rsquo;s planning committee <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/8077">has agreed</a> to a variation in planning conditions for the <a href="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/new-homes/london/tower-bridge/one-tower-bridge">One Tower Bridge development</a>, to prevent affordable housing tenants being able to use the communal garden available to private residents. Simon Bevan, Southwark&rsquo;s director of planning, told the planning committee that the exclusion of social tenants from the garden was <strong> <em>&ldquo;not seen as any significant restriction on how they enjoy their property&rdquo;.</em> </strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Peabody's Philanthropic Glass Towers - 0% Social Housing]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2015/01/27/peabody-borough-triangle-development/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-27T09:08:17+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2015/01/27/peabody-borough-triangle-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/BoroughTriangle.png" width="400" height="300">Peabody Housing Association has finally submitted a <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9556404">Planning application</a> for its long-awaited <em>Borough Triangle</em> development at Elephant &amp; Castle. This large triangle of land sits between Southbank University, Borough road and the Crown Court on Newington Causeway.</p>

<p>The site is currently home to the <a href="https://www.ipsos-mori.com/">IPSOS MORI</a> buildings and Baptist church on Borough road, which will be the only buildings to survive the redevelopment. The Georgian-built <a href="http://www.ioo.org.uk/">Institute of Optometry</a> and <a href="http://www.thestage.co.uk/news/2015/01/london-school-musical-theatre-relocate-southwark-site-demolished/">London School of Musical Theatre</a> (formerly the Institute for the Blind) will both be demolished under Peabody&rsquo;s plans. The latter being replaced by <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/NewMinistryOfSound.png">new premises</a> for the Ministry of Sound, which Peabody will build in its place.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/boroughtriangle.jpg"></p>

<p>The shops and warehouse spaces on the Newington side of the site will also be demolished. These are currently being used as a Pop-up arts and cultural space by <a href="http://www.hotelelephant.co.uk/">&lsquo;Hotel Elephant&rsquo;</a> and <a href="http://www.thepaperworks.co.uk/">&lsquo;The Paperworks&rsquo;</a>.<br/>
<img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/HotelElephant_Paperworks.jpg"></p>

<p>Besides new premises for the Ministry of Sound night club totalling ca. 6,000 sqm (allowing an extra capacity of 400 people over its current venue), Peabody plans to build some retail space; 10,000 sqm of office space in a shiny new corporate HQ for its staff; and a total of 529 new homes in a number of (predominantly glass) buildings of up to 38 storeys.</p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/388339_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Peabody_BoroughTriangle.png"></a></p>

<p>We originally had high hopes that this site would provide the desperately needed social rented housing that local people need. Unfortunately Peabody appears to have followed the trend of going for the more profitable &lsquo;affordable rented&rsquo; housing with rents of up to 80% market rent. It has also followed the trend of fudging and misleading about the precise nature of the affordable housing it is providing. In its <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387231_1.pdf">Housing Statement</a> Peabody states that it will be providing 96 <strong>intermediate</strong> units (16.7% of total) and 78 units at <strong>affordable rent</strong> (16.5% of total).</p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387231_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/affordable_rent_peabody.png" width="400" height="300"></a></p>

<p>However, Peabody&rsquo;s <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387199_1.pdf">Planning Statement</a> starts off by explaining the council&rsquo;s affordable housing policy: <strong> <em>&ldquo;5.117 In terms of affordable housing tenure, the Core Strategy at Strategic Policy 6 identifies that for development within the Elephant and Castle Opportunity Area the affordable housing should be delivered at 50% intermediate and 50% social rented.&rdquo;</em> </strong> but then dropping the word &lsquo;social&rsquo; from social rented, astonishingly goes on to claim that the application is policy compliant: <strong> <em>&ldquo;The proposal provides 16.7% intermediate and 16.5% for rented which is considered to comply with policy.&rdquo;</em> </strong></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Peabody_ApplicationForm.png">We checked the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387188_1.pdf">application form</a> to see what had been written in the useful boxes that Southwark provides showing detailed tenure mix information. We found that the 78 units had indeed been entered under the category social rented, but that the applicant had doctored the application form to include the word &lsquo;AFFORDABLE&rsquo; over the title &lsquo;Social Rented&rsquo;.</p>

<p>We also checked the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/388020_1.pdf">Design &amp; Access Statement</a> which states not only that the units will be affordable rent, but that they will be <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Peabody_TenureMix.png">segregated</a> from the other tenures (the high-rise towers will be exclusively private and intermediate housing).</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/EmailDanielDavies.png" width="400" height="300">Finally, we wrote to the Council&rsquo;s planning department asking for some clarity on whether the 78 units were for social rent or affordable rent; this is the baffling response we received.</p>

<p>Southwark recently published a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/download/2914/affordable_rent_in_southwark_2011">detailed study</a> of the impact of the introduction of affordable rent in the borough. From its <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11603/affordable_rent_study_december_2014_update">underlying data</a> we can see that a 1-bed social rented flat in SE1 would cost an average £97 per week, but a 1-bed flat at the new &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; of 80% market rent would cost £316 per week. Given that the median household income for council tenants in Borough and Bankside is £9,100 per year, it is clear that Peabody&rsquo;s affordable housing offer will be of no help to local people in housing need.  <br/>
</br>
Borough Triangle is the second largest development in the Elephant &amp; Castle opportunity area after the Heygate. No doubt lengthy discussions have taken place between Peabody, the Ministry of Sound and Southwark about what should be delivered on this key regeneration site. It is very dissapointing that a Housing Association with Peabody&rsquo;s reputation is not only failing to provide social housing, but is also seeking to mislead people about the fact. It is doubly dissapointing - but not surprising on past record - that Southwark is going along with it.</p>

<p>It seems Peabody has come a long way from the philanthropic intentions it was founded on in 1862, by George Peabody who wanted to <a href="http://www.peabody.org.uk/about-us/our-story"><strong> <em>&ldquo;ameliorate the condition of the poor and needy in this great metropolis&rdquo;</em> </strong></a>.</p>

<p>You can object to Peabody&rsquo;s application (ref:14/AP/3130) by sending an email to <a href="&#109;&#97;&#x69;&#x6c;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x70;&#108;&#97;&#x6e;&#110;&#105;&#x6e;&#x67;&#x2e;&#x61;&#112;&#112;&#x6c;&#x69;&#x63;&#97;&#116;&#105;&#111;&#110;&#x73;&#64;&#115;&#111;&#117;&#116;&#x68;&#x77;&#x61;&#114;&#x6b;&#46;&#103;&#x6f;&#x76;&#46;&#x75;&#107;">&#112;&#108;&#x61;&#110;&#110;&#105;&#x6e;&#x67;&#x2e;&#97;&#112;&#x70;&#108;&#x69;&#x63;&#97;&#116;&#105;&#111;&#x6e;&#x73;&#x40;&#x73;&#x6f;&#x75;&#116;&#104;&#119;&#97;&#114;&#107;&#46;&#103;&#x6f;&#x76;&#x2e;&#117;&#107;</a></p>

<h2>Peabody engages &lsquo;political intelligence&rsquo; services</h2>

<p>Peabody&rsquo;s application includes the mandatory <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/387210_1.pdf">Statement of Community Involvement (SCI)</a>, which is required to show evidence that it has consulted on its plans with the local community. Peabody instructed a public affairs company called <a href="http://www.bellenden.co.uk/about-us/specialist-expertise/property-development/">Bellenden</a> to advise on its application, conduct the consultation exercise and prepare its SCI.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.bellenden.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/MarkGloverColour.jpg">Bellenden was founded and is run by former Chair of Southwark Labour and local councillor <a href="https://uk.linkedin.com/in/glovermark">Mark Glover</a>. It was named after the road in which <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/4075/statement_of_persons_nominated_and_notice_of_poll">he lives</a>, Bellenden road in Peckham. Glover stepped down as councillor in May 2014. Amongst other things, Bellenden offers its clients a <a href="http://www.bellenden.co.uk/public-affairs/political-intelligence/">&lsquo;political intelligence&rsquo; service</a>, which it says involves <strong> <em>&ldquo;learning how political parties and their individual members are thinking on any given issue&rdquo;</em> </strong> and then <strong> <em>&ldquo;seeks to enlarge and inform their thoughts on behalf of our clients.&rdquo;</em> </strong><br/>
With his 12 years as a senior Southwark councillor, we don&rsquo;t doubt that Mr Glover is very well placed to provide this service.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Council Housing - Going Up or Coming Down?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2015/01/11/march-for-homes/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-11T12:21:55+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2015/01/11/march-for-homes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11416/housing_estates_and_sites_for_new_council_homes"><img class="right" src="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/Pictures/web/y/z/m/New-Council-Homes-deliver_633.jpg" width="400" height="270"></a>Just before Christmas Southwark Council issued a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1878/southwark_maps_out_1500_new_council_homes_in_just_four_years_as_part_of_the_most_ambitious_council_house_build_in_the_country">press release</a>, accompanied by a lovely <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11416/housing_estates_and_sites_for_new_council_homes">map</a> entitled <em>&ldquo;Housing Estates and Sites for New Council Homes&rdquo;</em>, which shows where 1500 of Southwark&rsquo;s 11000 new council homes will be built.</p>

<p>But as we showed in the <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/12/06/11000-new-private-and-social-council-homes-on-target/">previous blog</a>, this council-house building programme is not all it seems. For example, the 19 new homes planned on the East Dulwich estate (Gatebeck &amp; Southdown House), will be offset by 50 council homes which are being sold off on other parts of the estate - a net loss of 31 council homes in total<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://s0.geograph.org.uk/geophotos/02/70/11/2701156_6a4b82c2.jpg" width="300" height="200">Another site on the map, <em>Maydew House</em> will also show a net loss once completed. This 24-storey block containing 144 council flats overlooking Southwark Park, has been decanted <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Save-Maydew-House/316012601837">(amidst protest)</a> after the council <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/00,news,20152,440,00.htm">declared</a> the cost of repair <em>&ldquo;difficult to justify&rdquo;</em>. It is now being refurbished and 5 extra penthouse floors added to provide a total of 180 units, but only 74 will remain as council flats - a net loss of 70 council homes<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. The remaining 106 flats will all be sold off on the open market.</p>

<p>Building council homes is a popular pledge and one that we unquestionably support – it’s the best, most economical way of providing decent housing to those who most need it - but we are reminded of <a href="http://35percent.org/images/500newhomes.png">similar promises</a> from the not-so-distant past that were used to mask over the loss of the Heygate estate’s 1200 council homes<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>.</p>

<p>When we <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">blogged in October</a> about concerns that the new homes would only be replacements for council homes  sold off or demolished,  council leader Peter John reassured everyone that there would be a net gain of 11,000 council homes; he said -
<em>“To be absolutely clear, the 11,000 new homes that we promise to deliver will be new homes additional to our existing stock. ……These are new homes and do not include the existing stock of council housing.”</em></p>

<p>These latest findings show a different picture.  A council house building programme that depends upon ‘asset disposal’ and ‘estate renewal’ needs close scrutiny, if it is not going to end up leaving us with fewer council homes than we started with.</p>

<h2>March for Homes</h2>

<p><a href="http://marchforhomes.org"><img class="left" src="http://marchforhomes.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/MARCH_FOR_HOMES_SITE_LOGO.gif"></a>Housing (or the lack of it) is set to be a key issue in the parliamentary and mayoral elections in May. A <a href="http://marchforhomes.org/">&lsquo;March for Homes&rsquo;</a> has been called for Jan 31st by the <a href="http://www.southlondonpa.org/">South London People&rsquo;s Assembly</a>. It has an impressive list of supporters (including the 35% campaign) and is now to have two legs: one starting from South London and one from East London, both to converge on City Hall.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://li.zoocdn.com/c72dcb6efccb9584389cccf5dacc9330082f26fa_354_255.jpg" width="250" height="160">The South London leg will assemble at St Mary&rsquo;s Churchyard - in the shadow of <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/05/05/manx-connections-the-off-shore-home-of-the-elephants-developers/">Strata Tower</a>, <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/01/11/flogging-the-elephant/">One the Elephant</a> and the planned <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2013/08/10/towering-disgrace/">360 Tower</a>: three towers comprising 1162 new homes with zero social housing; the perfect place to start.<br/>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>West Hendon residents fight for their homes</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="https://fbcdn-sphotos-b-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xfp1/t31.0-8/c0.145.851.315/p851x315/10714465_1542589322623724_2087822952488384127_o.jpg" width="450" height="200">Meanwhile, residents of the <a href="http://www.londontenants.org/Pages/projectsderrick.htm">West Hendon estate</a> face a <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/legal/public-inquiry-to-investigate-misuse-of-compulsory-purchase-orders/7007668.article">public inquiry</a> into the compulsory purchase of their homes. The West Hendon regeneration is for 2,000 new homes and requires the demolition of 500 social rented units to be replaced by 250 affordable rent (up to 80% market rent).<br/>
They have organised a day of events on Jan 22nd:</p>

<ul>
<li>2pm: <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Focus-E15-Mothers/602860129757343">Focus E15 Mothers</a> talk about their campaign</li>
<li>4-5pm: Hot soup and rolls</li>
<li>5pm: March from the estate to the Public Inquiry at Hendon Town Hall</li>
<li>6pm: Rally outside Hendon Town Hall, joined by Women from The <a href="http://newera4all.org/">New Era campaign</a>, speakers from the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Our-West-Hendon/1476545849228072">Our West Hendon Group</a>, <a href="http://radicalhousingnetwork.org/">Radical Housing Network</a> , <a href="http://www.unitetheunion.org/">Unite The Union</a> and other estates in Barnet.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Fifty shades of embarrassment</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.independent.co.uk/incoming/article9969422.ece/alternates/w620/shades-of-gross.jpg" width="300" height="200">A marketing video for <a href="http://www.berkeleygroup.co.uk/new-homes/london/southwark/one-blackfriars">One Blackfriars</a> tells us who this housing is really for, if we were in any doubt - people who can afford to go househunting in helicopters.</p>

<p>The video features a sexy affluent white young professional couple, indulging in Fifty Shades of Grey fantasies as they view One Blackfriars&#8217; swish appartments. The video was quickly removed from the web after widespread ridicule in the national press: <br/>
<a href="http://www.standard.co.uk/news/london/luxury-london-flat-advert-branded-the-creepiest-thing-you-will-ever-see-9966793.html">Evening Standard - &lsquo;London flat advert branded the creepiest thing you will ever see&rsquo;</a> <br/>
<a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/business/news/one-blackfriars-shades-of-gross-ad-for-luxury-flats-is-dropped-9969098.html">The Independent - &lsquo;Gross ad for luxury flats is dropped&rsquo;</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/architecture-design-blog/2015/jan/05/american-psycho-redrow-property-promo-pulled-after-twitterstorm">The Guardian - &lsquo;Property promo pulled after twitterstorm&rsquo;</a></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.savoyrealty.co.uk/sites/default/files/field/image/18360_lg.jpg?slideshow=true&slideshowAuto=false&slideshowSpeed=4000&speed=350&transition=elastic" width="200" height="250"><em>One Blackfriars</em> was granted planning permission by Southwark Council in July 2007, despite objections from English Heritage, Lambeth Council, Westminster Council and the Royal Parks. It will have 274 flats, none of which will be social rented or affordable. Instead an in-lieu payment of £29m is to be paid by developers St George, which is a fraction of the <a href="http://www.propertyweek.com/berkeley-buys-london-beetham-tower/5026546.article">£700m</a> Gross Development Value i.e. the total estimated sales value of all the appartments.</p>

<p>An FOI request for the viability assessment which justified this generous deal has been <a href="https://www.whatdotheyknow.com/request/2nd_economic_viability_study_for">lodged</a> with Southwark Council.</p>

<h2>Viability on the agenda</h2>

<p>The viability assessment fiasco is firmly on the agenda in the run up to the elections. In an <a href="http://www.24dash.com/news/housing/2015-01-08-My-housing-career-Peter-Marsh">interview</a> with <em>24Dash Housing</em>, a former housing quango chief has estimated that viability assessments caused the loss of £1bn of affordable housing and that many in the sector <em>&ldquo;consider these appraisals something of a joke&rdquo;</em>. The Guardian&rsquo;s editorial has <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/jan/01/guardian-view-affordable-housing-developers-must-made-show-sums">branded</a> the appraisal loophole a <em>&lsquo;public betrayal&rsquo;</em> and has called for developers to <em>&ldquo;show their sums&rdquo;</em>. A reporter who <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2014/sep/17/truth-property-developers-builders-exploit-planning-cities">wrote</a> about the problem earlier in the year has also put it at the top of his New Years wishlist, calling for <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2014/dec/29/what-i-want-cities-2015-severe-tax-on-empty-homes"><em>&ldquo;opening up this shady world of cooked books&rdquo;</em></a>.</p>

<p>We are also looking forward to helping lift the lid on the viability assessment scam. We have been talking to professionals from the across the sector, who will be helping us analyse the viability assessments obtained from the forthcoming Heygate &amp; Greenwich Peninsula Tribunal cases and put forward ideas for policy changes that could close the loophole. Watch this space!</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See paragraph 16 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s36276/Report%20East%20Dulwich%20Estate%20Regeneration%20Scheme%20and%20Scheme%20Finance%20Update.pdf">this March 2013 Cabinet Report</a><a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See paragraph 132 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s49973/Report%20Qtr%202%202014-15%20Capital%20Monitor.pdf">this November 2014 Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>This is an extract from the <a href="https://www.scribd.com/doc/198503633/EandC-RegenMk1SLRplans">2002 E&amp;C Regeneration Masterplan</a><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Council Sells Council Homes to Build New (Social &amp; Private) 'Council' Homes]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/12/06/11000-new-private-and-social-council-homes-on-target/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-06T09:16:18+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/12/06/11000-new-private-and-social-council-homes-on-target</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">wrote</a> in October about the council&rsquo;s plan to earmark a number of its housing estates for demolition using an <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/Snhat.pdf">&lsquo;Asset Performance Evaluation Tool&rsquo;</a>, which would take into account factors like residents&#8217; income. The results of its survey were supposed to be presented at next week&rsquo;s Cabinet meeting, but the <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50476/Report%20Pipeline%20for%20the%20Delivery%20of%201500%20New%20Council%20Homes.pdf">December Cabinet report</a> shows that this has now been postponed until January.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50476/Report%20Pipeline%20for%20the%20Delivery%20of%201500%20New%20Council%20Homes.pdf">December Cabinet report</a> makes interesting reading: it concedes that its estate renewal programme alone may not provide enough capacity for its 11,000 proposed new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes and suggests two additional strategies:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Buying affordable housing built through s106 agreements directly from developers. (see <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50476/Report%20Pipeline%20for%20the%20Delivery%20of%201500%20New%20Council%20Homes.pdf">para. 58</a>).</p></li>
<li><p>Purchasing land that becomes available on the open market. (see <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50476/Report%20Pipeline%20for%20the%20Delivery%20of%201500%20New%20Council%20Homes.pdf">para. 60</a>)</p></li>
</ol>


<p>We can see two obvious problems with these new strategies:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Southwark&rsquo;s track record on securing affordable housing through s106 obligations is extremely poor. The viability assessment loophole means that developers often get away with building no affordable housing whatsoever. In those cases where affordable housing is provided, it normally takes the form of shared ownership and affordable rent (80% market), which are of little benefit unless these are the kind of &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes that Southwark is looking to provide.</p></li>
<li><p>We have already <a href="http://35percent.org/heygate-regeneration-faq/">reported</a> on Southwark&rsquo;s loss on the sale of its 25-acre Heygate site at a knock-down price to developer Lend Lease. We don&rsquo;t know how much it sold the Aylesbury for, but we think it&rsquo;s unlikely to recover the estimated £150m cost<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> of demolishing the 60-acre estate. So it doesn&rsquo;t need us to point out the absurdity of selling off structurally-sound council estates on the cheap and then buying back land from the private sector in order to build new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes.</p></li>
</ol>


<p><a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50478/Appendix%202%20Direct%20Delivery%20Sites.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/DirectDeliverySites.png" width="400" height="750"></a>The December Cabinet report also provided an update on the council&rsquo;s progress with its 11,000 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes &lsquo;Direct Delivery&rsquo; programme. Phase one of the programme involving the &lsquo;delivery&rsquo; of 1,500 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes by 2018 is now being finalised, with sites for 837 of these new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes now identified. <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50478/Appendix%202%20Direct%20Delivery%20Sites.pdf">Appendix 2</a> of the report gives a detailed schedule of these 837 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes and where they are to be located.</p>

<p>However, a closer look at the schedule reveals that many of these won&rsquo;t be council homes and that some are being funded by selling off existing stock. For example, the first two entries on the list are supposedly providing 27 new council homes on the East Dulwich estate (Gatebeck House:9 &amp; Southdown House:18). But it doesn&rsquo;t say that a third of these will be for shared ownership<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>; neither does it mention that these 27 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes on the East Dulwich estate, are being funded by selling off land and 50 existing council homes on other parts of the estate: <em>&ldquo;with £2.2m to be raised from the sale of 24 drying room conversions; £8.76m from the sale of 50 voids-for-sale and £4.1m to be raised from the disposal of land&rdquo;</em>.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<p>The next entry on the Direct Delivery schedule is Willow Walk near Old Kent Road, which is supposedly providing 75 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes. However, according to paragraphs 5 &amp; 6 of the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/284022_1.pdf">planning report</a> for this development, the 75 units comprise only 21 social rented homes, plus 54 rooms for temporary accommodation (replacing the existing temporary accommodation unit) - very welcome no doubt but not 75 council homes.</p>

<p>Next on the schedule is the site of the former Nunhead Community Centre, which is supposedly providing 8 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes. What it doesn&rsquo;t mention is that a large (1000 sqm) council-owned community centre is being demolished to make way for these and that the 8 new council homes will be <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/304415_1.pdf">accompanied</a> by 14 new homes for private sale.</p>

<p>Another council-owned community centre and some workshops are being demolished in Sumner road, Peckham. The schedule says that this site will provide 112 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes. What it doesn&rsquo;t say is that less than half of these (50) will be social-rented; 20 will be shared ownership and the remaining 42 units will be &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes for private sale. (see <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9555190">planning docs</a>)</p>

<p>Of the 25 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes built on the former Masterman House garages in Camberwell, only 15 will be social rented; the remainder will also be &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes for private sale. Just 34 of the 116 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes planned for Commmercial Way will be social rented and so the list goes on. We can&rsquo;t find details for many of the sites listed in the schedule, but we estimate that only around half of the 837 new &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes listed will be &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes as we know them. The remainder will be shared ownership and &lsquo;council&rsquo; homes for private sale, which doesn&rsquo;t come as a surprise in the wake of the revelations stemming from <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/18/southwark-mipim-and-the-11000-new-council-homes/">our reporting</a> of Southwark&rsquo;s MIPIM attendance this year.</p>

<h2>Footing the bill of regeneration</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://i.huffpost.com/gen/1713650/thumbs/o-ELEPHANT-AND-CASTLE-STATION-facebook.jpg" width="300" height="175">The <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/5293">long-running dispute</a> over who should pay for the capacity upgrades to the northern line tube station in order to meet increased demand from developments, has finally come to an end. Southwark News <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SNroundabout.pdf">reports</a> that of the £154m total cost, TFL have agreed to pay £91m while the council is left to find the remaining £63m. The council&rsquo;s regeneration partner Lend Lease is making a contribution of just £16.3m<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> towards the council&rsquo;s bill - proof that the regeneration partnership is not an equal one, with Southwark bearing the lion&rsquo;s share of costs and Lend Lease reaping the Elephantine profits.</p>

<h2>Untrustworthy imagery</h2>

<p>Lend Lease got a <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/private_eye.jpg">mention</a> in the latest edition of Private Eye. This time for a development in Chiswick, where its PR firm have been accused of producing misleading imagery. The column also pointed out that Paul Dimoldenberg, the head of Lend Lease&rsquo;s PR firm which created the images, also happens to be leader of the Labour group at Westminster council. We can add that Cllr Dimoldenberg also used to be a senior council officer at Southwark.</p>

<p>Our hats go off to Mr Dimoldenberg&rsquo;s firm for its PR image trickery. The following is a visualisation image from the Heygate application. <br/>
<img src="http://www.elephantandcastle-lendlease.com/wp-content/uploads/Homepage-Header-2-Not-sure-if-this-size-image-will-work1.jpg"></p>

<p>Looks nice doesn&rsquo;t it? but what the image doesn&rsquo;t tell you is that this is one of the developments&#8217; 12 &lsquo;raised courtyards&rsquo;, which are enclosed by buildings and will have zero public access:<br/>
<a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/267119_1.pdf"><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/heygate_raised_courtyards2.png"></a></p>

<h2>Coronet uncorrugated</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.theatrestrust.org.uk/store/ttdb/ttt0048/lowres/010997_regular.jpg?1410824878" width="300" height="600">New photographs have been <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SNcoronet.pdf">published</a> showing what the Art Deco Coronet building looks like behind its corrugated blue facade. <br/>
The Coronet is currently under threat of demolition from the shopping centre redevelopment. The shopping centre and neighbouring site are being redeveloped by real estate hedge fund DV4. George Soros backed DV4 is based in the British Virgin Islands and managed by <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2041229/Tory-donor-Jamie-Ritblat-snaps-Olympic-Village-knock-price--costing-275m.html">Delancey&rsquo;s Jamie Ritblatt</a>.</p>

<p>The Theatres Trust has recently submitted an application to have the Coronet listed. You can read more about the campaign on the <a href="http://www.theatrestrust.org.uk/resources/theatres/show/3344-coronet-london">Theatres Trust website</a>, the Save the Coronet campaign <a href="http://coronettheatre.co.uk/home/save-the-coronet/">web page</a> and <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/davehillblog/2014/dec/07/how-the-coronet-can-help-the-elephant">this article</a> by the Guardian&rsquo;s Dave Hill. <br/>
</br></p>

<h2>Unfair trial</h2>

<p>After being unlawfully evicted from his home, having his possessions destroyed and being left street homeless by Southwark council, a Sudanese refugee <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/crime/judge-blasts-southwark-council-for-evicting-sudanese-tenant-and-destroying-his-possessions-9796994.html">won</a> a long-running court case against the council in October. After spending six-figure sums on top QCs to fight the case against the claimaint (who had no legal representation), the council declared last week that the trial was &lsquo;unfair&rsquo; and &lsquo;clearly wrong&rsquo;. An <a href="http://nearlylegal.co.uk/blog/2014/11/southwark-not-appealing/">article</a> about the case by the Giles Peaker, a partner specialising in housing at solicitors Anthony Gold, sums up Southwark&rsquo;s attitude well: <em>&ldquo;disingenuous in the extreme&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<h2>Heygate viability assessment FOI/EIR appeal</h2>

<p>The ongoing battle to disclose the Heygate development viability assessment continues. The Information Tribunal has called a final hearing on 21st January to resolve the ongoing dispute concerning the implementation of its <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/FirstTierDecisionHeygate.pdf">May 2014 decision notice</a>. The hearing will be in closed session attended only by Lend Lease &amp; Southwark&rsquo;s counsel, who will recieve directions as to exactly which of the 22 appendices can be withheld. The Tribunal had previously ruled that the financial model in appendix 22 and the figures related to commercial negotiations for its retail floorspace could be withheld, but there has been a dispute over exactly which of the 22 appendices are related to these. We are expecting the Tribunal to order the viability assessment be disclosed within a short period after the hearing (barring further appeals and heeldragging by Lend Lease &amp; Southwark). After nearly 3 years of battling for its disclosure we are looking forward to finally being able to see why Lend Lease has been so reluctant to show its sums.</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See paragraph 142 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s43556/Report%20Selection%20of%20a%20Preferred%20Partner%20to%20Work%20with%20the%20Council%20to%20Deliver%20the%20Regeneration%20of%20the.pdf">this Jan 2014 council briefing report</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See paragraph 19 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s36276/Report%20East%20Dulwich%20Estate%20Regeneration%20Scheme%20and%20Scheme%20Finance%20Update.pdf">this March 2013 Cabinet report</a>.  <a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See paragraph 16 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s36276/Report%20East%20Dulwich%20Estate%20Regeneration%20Scheme%20and%20Scheme%20Finance%20Update.pdf">this March 2013 Cabinet report</a>.  <a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>See &lsquo;E&amp;C Strategic Transport&rsquo; contributions in each of Lend Lease&rsquo;s planning applications: <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/249091_1.pdf">One the Elephant (£2m)</a>, <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/224053_1.pdf">Heygate masterplan (£11.7m)</a> &amp; <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/238280_1.pdf">Heygate phase 1 (£2.6m)</a> <a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury Estate - Back to the Drawing Board?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/11/15/aylesbury-estate-back-to-the-drawing-board/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-15T15:13:56+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/11/15/aylesbury-estate-back-to-the-drawing-board</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/pagenotfound.png" width="300" height="200">The planning documents for the Aylesbury estate outline masterplan have been <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557153">removed</a> from Southwark council&rsquo;s planning portal. The documents for the first development site under the masterplan have also been <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557152">removed</a>. The applications were <a href="http://35percent.org/images/scan0027.pdf">lodged</a> on 25th September and the documents uploaded about a month later. On inquiry, Southwark said that the applications had been <em>&ldquo;uploaded in error, they are currently invalid and not open to consultation.&rdquo;</em> It also said that <em>&ldquo;as soon as the relevant documentation has been received .. and been made valid they will be posted on the website&rdquo;</em>. It is not clear whether the applications have been withdrawn and now need to be re-submitted. Our <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/">previous blog</a> on the Aylesbury applications pointed out - amongst other things - that 934 social rented homes are to be lost if the development goes ahead as planned.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, Aylesbury leaseholders are fighting to get a fair deal from the council and its development partners Notting Hill Housing &amp; Barratt Homes. A leaseholders&#8217; <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s50093/Report%20Deputation%20Requests.pdf">deputation</a> will be submitting <a href="https://halag.files.wordpress.com/2014/11/alag_depuation18nov_finalversion.pdf">5 demands</a> to the council&rsquo;s Cabinet meeting on Tuesday. Amongst their very sensible requirements is one that any council officer who values their homes is actually qualified to do so, as it turns out this is not always the case: a leaseholder&rsquo;s complaint to the recognised professional body (RICS) could not be dealt with because the officers concerned were not RICS qualified or registered. The leaseholders have requested instead that valuations are conducted by the District Valuer Service.</p>

<p>At the same meeting, Southwark will also be receiving a deputation from the <a href="http://www.sgto.org.uk/">Southwark Group of Tenants Organisation</a>, who also have some <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s49943/Appendix%206%20Six%20alternative%20pledges%20from%20SGTO.pdf">suggestions</a>, this time about improving the six pledges Southwark has made for conducting its consultation on building 11,000 new council homes. Southwark should adopt these improved pledges, it will be a step in the right direction, but it is also <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/11/08/southwark-fails-to-deliver/">clear</a> that the Council already has definite ideas about how these new homes will be provided, including estate regeneration and estate infill.</p>

<h2>Head in the clouds</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/betterelephant/status/531882170424786944"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/tweet.png" width="400" height="800"></a>Southwark&rsquo;s Head of Regeneration Councillor Mark Williams, obviously got a bit giddy last week at the topping out ceremony of Lend Lease&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.onetheelephant.com/apartments/browse-apartments"><strong>One the Elephant</strong></a> tower (or maybe Lend Lease plied him with too much champagne). He <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/01/11/flogging-the-elephant/">tweeted</a> from the rooftop ceremony about the wonderful view as well as the <em>&ldquo;new homes, jobs and leisure centre for local residents&rdquo;</em>. A second tweet claimed that the development was providing £12.5m towards the new leisure centre (costing £25m), but as we can see below from the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/305818_1.pdf">legal agreement</a> the figure is actually only £3.5m. Lend Lease got out of providing any on-site affordable housing or making any payment in-lieu for the development through the magic of viability assessments and as we showed in a <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/01/11/flogging-the-elephant/">previous blog</a> Southwark should have netted £33.2m under its <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/affordablehousingspg.pdf">in-lieu affordable housing payment tariff</a>.<br/>
<a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/305818_1.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/leisurecentrecontribution.png"></a></p>

<p>Southwark also <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/LandRegistry_OneTheElephant.pdf">sold</a> the <strong>One the Elephant</strong> land to Lend Lease for the price of £6.5m (£4.6m per acre), which is a bargain considering that the gross development value of the tower will be upwards of £230m<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Our interactive map also shows how this compares to other land sales at the Elephant:</p>

<center>
<iframe src="http://35percent.org/map.html" width="800" height="600"></iframe>
</br><font size="2">Click <a href="http://35percent.org/map.html">here</a> to view our interactive map in a separate browser window</font>
</center>


<p></br></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/robertabwMP/status/531797457492250624"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/blackmanwoods.png" width="400" height="650"></a>While Cllr Williams&#8217; head was in the clouds, Labour shadow minister for planning, Roberta Blackman-Woods, was keeping her feet firmly on the ground when she visited the Heygate site last week, <a href="https://twitter.com/robertabwMP/status/531797457492250624">tweeting</a> that Lend Lease&rsquo;s scheme was <em>&ldquo;very interesting&rdquo;</em>. Ms Woods might also be interested in the risks local authorities run when they enter into partnership agreements with global property giants like Lend Lease, as illustrated by <a href="http://www.architectureanddesign.com.au/news/lend-lease-nsw-government-dispute-halts-barangaroo">this story</a> from its other major development site in Sydney, Australia, where city authorities stand to lose millions after losing a bitter court battle with Lend Lease over a profit-share agreement.</p>

<p></br>
</br>
</br></p>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>This is based on an expected average sales value of £815 per sq foot, which was the average sales price <a href="http://www.colliers.com/~/media/Files/EMEA/UK/research/residential/201202-central-london-residential-market.pdf">achieved</a> by the Strata tower.  <strong>One the Elephant</strong> comprises 269,000sq ft of residential floorspace in total; the total expected residential sales is therefore £219m (269k X £815), plus 13,000 sq ft of retail in <strong>One the Elephant</strong>&rsquo;s pavilion with an approximate value of £10m.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Southwark Fails to Deliver]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/11/08/southwark-fails-to-deliver/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-08T19:10:35+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/11/08/southwark-fails-to-deliver</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/viability.png" width="300" height="200">The Heygate viability assessment saga took a new turn last week. Southwark Council failed to produce the assessment by the given deadline and all parties have been called back to a Tribunal hearing on 11th Dec.</p>

<p>We can only speculate on the cause of the delay, but Southwark Council is beginning to look a bit ridiculous. After spending a six-figure sum and two and a half years appealing against the Information Commissioner, last week Southwark claimed that it has <em>&ldquo;always been keen to see this matter resolved as quickly as possible&rdquo;</em> and that <em>&ldquo;the final version of the document is now on its way to Mr Glasspool&rdquo;</em> .</p>

<p><a href="http://35percent.org/images/SN29Oct2014.pdf"><img class="left" src="http://allpeoplesparty.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/11/Southwark-Council-Release-Heygate-Deal-Now.png" width="500" height="300"></a></p>

<p>There are still serious oustanding questions about many aspects of the redevelopment, not just about the amount of affordable housing that the assessment can help answer (see our <a href="http://35percent.org/heygate-regeneration-faq/">FAQ</a> for a summary of the issues). Both the Information Commissioner and Information Tribunal have ruled that it is heavily in the public interest for this document to be revealed; Southwark should release the assessment without any further delay.</p>

<h2>Spot the difference</h2>

<p>While the tribunal case drags on, Lend Lease are motoring forward with the latest detailed planning application for the Heygate (now known as <a href="http://www.elephantpark.co.uk/">&lsquo;Elephant Park&rsquo;</a>). The application for <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1779/lend_lease_submits_detailed_planning_application_for_around_600_new_homes_at_elephant_park">West Grove (phase MP2)</a> comprises 593 new homes and 43,000 square feet of new retail space.</p>

<p>One thing we have noticed is that the <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/5621">visualisations</a> of the new Heygate supplied during public consultations on the outline application, were based on minimum plot/building sizes. To nobody&rsquo;s surprise it is the maximum plot sizes that Lend Lease are applying for in their detailed applications and as we can see from the image below<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, it makes for a significant difference. It seems that it&rsquo;s only now that we are becoming privy to the true scale of development.</p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/389783_1.pdf"><img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/parameterheights.png"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/389805_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/mp2affordablehousing.png" width="300" height="300"></a>Despite its size however, Lend Lease can only find room for 26 social rented flats in its latest phase, which won&rsquo;t make much of a dent in Southwark&rsquo;s 20,000-strong housing waiting list.
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>More viability struggles</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s not just in Southwark where people are challenging the viability trump card and fighting developers for properly affordable housing. Two notable examples elsewhere are <a href="http://www.wcdg.net/content/waterloos-don-quixote-one-man-against-world">Riverside Communities vs Braeburn estates</a> at the Southbank&rsquo;s Shell Centre development, where developers are getting away with building just 11% affordable housing; and <a href="http://www.eastlondonlines.co.uk/2014/11/stokey-local-votes-to-take-planning-proposal-fight-to-court-of-appeal/">Stokey Local Community Group vs Sainsburys</a> who want to build a new supermarket and flats, but have reduced their offer of affordable housing from 50% to 17%. In both cases, campaigners are trying to get to the truth about viability and pierce the legal smoke screens of commercial confidentiality.</p>

<h2>Cooltan stuffed</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/11/img_0363.jpg?w=208&h=182" width="300" height="200">A new housing and student residence development was approved for Walworth road&rsquo;s Blanchard site last week, to the great disappointment of local mental health charity <a href="http://www.cooltanarts.org.uk/">Cooltan Arts</a> and its many supporters.  A previously approved application contained a legally binding agreement to supply Cooltan (who were previous occupants of the site) with new premises. The site (plus agreement) was sold to another developer, the planning agreement lapsed and the new developer said it was not economically viable to provide Cooltan with what it needed. Southwark Council claimed it had no power to enforce the lapsed agreement and the application was duly approved.</p>

<h2>Coming soon&hellip; a fairer future</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/fairerfuture.png">Southwark Council is beginning its consultation on the New Southwark Plan, which will both incorporate and replace the existing Southwark Plan and Core Strategy planning policy frameworks. It will determine how all land in Southwark will be developed - or not as the case may be. Contentious issues are likely going to be the possible regeneration of council estates, the density of new developments and the protection of green spaces.</p>

<p>The paragraph below in the foreword of the <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/11161/new_southwark_plan">draft new Plan</a> caught our eye. Southwark&rsquo;s intention to use infill land and pursue estate regeneration as a way of providing 11,000 new council homes, explains why it feels the need to make a <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s47489/Appendix%201%20Draft%20Charter%20of%20Principles.pdf">Charter of Principles</a> of good behaviour when it consults with its council estate residents.<br/>
<img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/newsouthwarkplan.png"></p>

<p>The consultation period for this first draft of the New Southwark Plan and this proposal lasts until 6th March 2015, but Southwark isn&rsquo;t wasting time: an &lsquo;asset management&rsquo; process is already <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">in train</a> and will be making recommendations about potential renewal/regeneration sites to Southwark&rsquo;s Cabinet in December.</p>

<h2>Estate renewal conference</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk/2014/09/30/conference-delivering-estate-renewal/"><img class="right" src="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk/futureoflondon/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/Delivering-Estate-Renewal-postcard-front-1024x721.jpg" width="400" height="300"></a>Last week saw a <a href="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk">Future of London</a> conference entitled <a href="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk/2014/09/30/conference-delivering-estate-renewal/">&lsquo;Delivering Estate Renewal&rsquo;</a>. The conference was co-sponsored by Lend Lease who are described in the <a href="http://www.futureoflondon.org.uk/2014/09/30/conference-delivering-estate-renewal/">conference programme</a> as &lsquo;estate-savvy developers&rsquo;. The speakers included representatives from Lend Lease, Notting Hill&rsquo;s CEO Kate Davies and Southwark&rsquo;s Head of Regeneration, Stephen Platts.</p>

<p>A detailed <a href="http://chrisbrown.regen.net/2014/11/10/estate-renewal-community-coproduction/">write-up</a> of the event by Chris Brown from <a href="http://www.iglooregeneration.co.uk/">Igloo Regeneration</a> describes the arithmetic behind the crude logic of estate renewal: a council estate&rsquo;s rental income is subtracted from forecasted maintenance costs to give a &lsquo;net present cost&rsquo;; this is then compared against the estimated development value of the estate as a cleared site, so that local authorities can <em>&ldquo;get rid of the financial underperformers&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Brown says that he was <em>&ldquo;taken to task&rdquo;</em> during the conference, by Southwark&rsquo;s Stephen Platts over his <em>&ldquo;description of the Heygate estate renewal as a social disaster&rdquo;</em> and that his attempts to highlight the social cost of displacing communities seemed to fall on deaf ears.</p>

<h2>Baby shard gets go-ahead</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/imageuploads/1415187088_46.233.112.163.jpg" width="300" height="400">Irvine Sellar and son James attended Southwark&rsquo;s planning committee meeting last Tuesday evening (in a chauffeur-driven limousine). They were there to watch the the council&rsquo;s labour controlled planning committee <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7931">wave through</a> their plans for a 26 storey shard satellite tower.
In presenting the proposals, James Sellar claimed that <em>&ldquo;the proposal before you tonight will for the first time bring residents into the heart of this regeneration. It will create homes and bring vibrancy, ensuring that people working in London Bridge have the opportunity to live there as well.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>However, the Sellars had submitted a viability assessment showing that they couldn&rsquo;t afford to provide any on-site affordable housing provision. Instead, they first <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7915">proposed</a> to meet their affordable housing obligations by funding the stalled redevelopment of the Wood Dene Estate in Peckham. After criticism from opposition councillors the developers have now promised to &lsquo;try&rsquo; and find somewhere in the north of the borough instead. Failing this they have agreed to make an in-lieu payment of £18m - somewhat less than the price of some penthouses currently <a href="http://www.altomagazine.com/news/inside-londons-premier-penthouse-at-neo-bankside-4283694">being sold</a> in the area.</p>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Image taken from the planning <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9556728">application&rsquo;s</a>&rsquo;s <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/389783_1.pdf">reconciliation statement</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury Estate Planning Applications - 934 Social Rented Homes to Be Lost]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-01T07:57:54+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/11/01/aylesbury-estate-planning-application</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/398988_1.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/aylesburynetloss.png" width="450" height="450"></a>After waiting over a month for them to be &lsquo;validated&rsquo; by the council, the planning documents for the Aylesbury estate revelopment are now online.
The application for the First Development Site seeks permission to demolish the Bradenham, Chartridge &amp; Chiltern blocks comprising 630 homes and replace them with 815 new homes (<a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557152">ref:14-AP-3843</a>); 362 of these will be at &lsquo;target rent&rsquo; - a net loss of 204 units (provided that target rent is equivalent to social rent). The amount of free market housing on this first phase will increase from 64 homes (initially bought under right-to-buy) to 412 and there will also be 102 intermediate units.</p>

<p>The 204 social rented units lost on the first phase is a fraction of the total net loss from the Aylesbury regeneration as a whole.  The <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/398988_1.pdf">Housing Statement</a> for the outline application <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557153">(2,735 new homes - ref:14/AP/3844)</a> shows that the social rented housing provision will be reduced by over a third, with a net loss of 934 social rented homes across the estate once the regeneration is completed.</p>

<h3>Target Rent = affordable rent or social rent?</h3>

<p>The table in paragraph 5.11 of the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/398988_1.pdf">Housing Statement</a>, describes &lsquo;Estate Baseline&rsquo; homes as &lsquo;Target and Affordable Rent&rsquo; which they never were; they were council homes at council rents. Using &lsquo;target rent&rsquo;, &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo; and &lsquo;social rent&rsquo; as if they are all the same thing confuses and misleads. What people really need to know is how much total rent will new-build tenants be paying, whatever the housing is called?</p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/279910_1.pdf"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/wolvertons106SR.png" width="450" height="450"></a>The previous phase of the Aylesbury redevelopment currently under construction by L&amp;Q gives good reason to worry on this point: as we reported in a <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/05/05/manx-connections-the-off-shore-home-of-the-elephants-developers/">previous blog post</a>, the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/279910_1.pdf">legal agreement</a> for <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/lq-wins-work-on-next-phase-of-aylesbury-plan/6522708.article">that phase</a> contains a definition of &lsquo;social rented&rsquo;, which refers to the <a href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/affordable-rent">HCA definition</a> of Boris Johnson&rsquo;s &lsquo;affordable rented&rsquo; housing product of up to 80% market rents:</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/heygates106SR.png" width="450" height="400">One would normally expect to find a reference to the National Rent Regime under the definition of social rented housing in such documents. This is the regulatory framework which decides the level of social rents based - among other things - on the average level of income. Here is an example of the wording normally used in Southwark&rsquo;s legal agreements securing planning obligations.</p>

<p>Before the legal agreement securing the Aylesbury planning obligations can be signed, the application has to be approved by Southwark&rsquo;s planning committee;  Southwark is also a partner in the regeneration, so it is up to Southwark to ensure that this situation is not repeated and we don&rsquo;t end up with &lsquo;social rented housing&rsquo; that is nothing of the kind.</p>

<h3>Cycling and car parking</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/aylesburycycling.png"><img class="right" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/aylesburycycling.png" width="400" height="300"></a>The council recently <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7895">announced</a> plans for a &lsquo;Southwark Spine&rsquo; cycle route linking the south to the north of the borough, which is due to cut straight through the new Aylesbury development<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. However, cycle campaign groups have pointed out that the planning applications make no provision for any segregated cycle lanes, instead cyclists will be forced to continue to compete for road space on Thurlow street with buses and cars as the illustrations here show. A <a href="http://www.change.org/p/southwark-council-s-planning-committee-and-transport-department-we-want-physically-segregated-cycle-lanes-on-albany-rd-thurlow-st-and-dutch-standard-prioritised-protected-crossings-for-cyclists-pedestrians-at-cycle-route-junctions-in-the-aylesbury-es">petition</a> has been set up by cycle campaign group <a href="http://stopkillingcyclists.org.">http://stopkillingcyclists.org.</a></p>

<p>Paragraph 2.5 of the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/397955_1.pdf">Transport Statement</a> also confirms that <em>&ldquo;the proposals are for 1378 residential car parking spaces across the development&rdquo;</em>. We think this is excessive in an area with such strong public transport links on the border of zone 1 London. The aerial photo below, taken from the application&rsquo;s <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/397933_1.pdf">Design &amp; Access statement</a> shows the Aylesbury estate masterplan in its geographical context:</p>

<p><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/aylesburyincontext.png"></p>

<h3>Environmental Impact</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2011/1824/schedule/4/made">Planning regulations</a> require major redevelopment applications to provide <em>&ldquo;An outline of the main alternatives studied by the applicant or appellant and an indication of the main reasons for the choice made, taking into account the environmental effects.&rdquo;</em> This is to ensure that developers have properly considered the environmental impact of their proposals against the possible lower impact of alternatives and refurbishment. It would appear that no such appraisal or any detailed cost/benefit analysis has been undertaken in relation to the Aylesbury redevelopment.</p>

<p>UCL&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.engineering.ucl.ac.uk/engineering-exchange/">Engineering Exchange</a> recently published a detailed <a href="http://www.engineering.ucl.ac.uk/engineering-exchange/demolition-refurbishment-social-housing/">report</a> showing that <em>&ldquo;refurbishment of housing is often preferable to demolition and reconstruction&rdquo;</em> when taking into account environmental and social factors. We saw with the Heygate that wholesale decant and demolition costs can far outstrip refurbishment costs: the council spent £65m emptying<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> &amp; £15m demolishing<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> the Heygate when comprehensive refurbishment would have cost just £35m<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>.</p>

<h3>Equalities Impact</h3>

<p><a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/Data/Executive/20050927/Agenda/Item%2007%20-%20The%20AylesburyEstate%20Revised%20Strategy%20-%20Annex%20D.pdf">Council papers</a> state that <em>&ldquo;the Aylesbury is a very diverse community with 67% of people belonging to a minority ethnic group&rdquo;</em>. According to the Equalities Act 2010, the planning application should have included a detailed equalities impact assessment to consider whether the planning proposals will have an adverse effect on any Black and Minority Ethnic(BME) groups. We have been unable to find any such assessment in the supporting documents for either application.</p>

<p>Should you wish to object to the Aylesbury applications you can use the template we have set up on our online comments submission form. Simply click on the following link, enter your details and click to send the objection to the council&rsquo;s planning department:<br/>
<a href="http://commentform.herokuapp.com">http://commentform.herokuapp.com</a></p>

<h2>Southwark suddenly &lsquo;keen to disclose viability assessment&rsquo;</h2>

<p>Southwark&rsquo;s spin doctors were in full spin this week when they <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SN29Oct2014.pdf">announced</a> that the council is about to disclose the Heygate viability assessment. Having spent two years and a sum running into six figures fighting the Information Commissioner&rsquo;s order to disclose the document, Southwark&rsquo;s new regen boss Mark Williams claimed <em>&ldquo;Southwark Council has always been keen to see this matter resolved as quickly as possible.&rdquo;</em> <br/>
The council&rsquo;s sudden keenness to &lsquo;resolve the matter&rsquo; has surely got nothing to do with the fact that at a recent Case Management Hearing, the Tribunal judge gave Southwark a deadline of 5th Nov to disclose the viability assessment&hellip;</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See pg 52 of the council&rsquo;s <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s49335/Appendix%201%20Cycling%20strategy.pdf">draft cycling strategy</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See paragraph 50(ix) of the <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/rnblpa0ajaxk8em/LON_LIB1-%239487917-v1-Lend_Lease_EA_2013_0162_Response_to_LBS_Grounds_of_....pdf">Heygate Tribunal evidence</a> - <em>&ldquo;The Council’s costs as at January 2013 amounted to about £47.5 million in capital expenditure and just under £18 million in review costs managing the estate&rdquo;</em>.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See paragraph 18 of this <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/documents/s30387/120709%20Heygate%20Estate%20Demolition%20Business%20Case%20signed%20report.pdf">council report</a> - <em>&ldquo;The baseline budget for the Heygate demolition is estimated to be a total of £15.225m including 10% contingency.&rdquo;</em><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>See this <a href="http://heygateestate.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/genslerheygate.pdf">2012 cost appraisal study</a> by global architects <a href="http://gensler.com">Gensler</a> and construction consultancy <a href="http://baqus.co.uk">Baqus</a>. <a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MIPIM, Southwark and Its 11000 New 'Private and Social' Council Homes]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/10/18/southwark-mipim-and-the-11000-new-council-homes/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-18T11:54:16+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/10/18/southwark-mipim-and-the-11000-new-council-homes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://static.guim.co.uk/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2014/10/15/1413393213631/Mipim-property-conference-011.jpg" width="300" height="200">The MIPIM Jamboree last week attracted much protest and media comment, including articles in the <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/oct/14/yacht-cannes-selling-homes-local-government-officials-mipim">Guardian</a> and on the <a href="http://leftfootforward.org/2014/10/the-mipim-property-fair-everything-wrong-with-regeneration/">Left Foot Forward</a> blog, which noted that <em>&ldquo;the Heygate Estate has become the paradigmatic example of the MIPIM-model of property development&rdquo;</em>.
</br></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.lbhf.gov.uk/Images/cllr-stephen-cowan-at-nipim_432_tcm21-191385.jpg" width="250" height="200">MIPIM itself revealed the contrasting attitudes of 3 London Labour boroughs towards developers:
Hammersmith &amp; Fulham <a href="http://www.lbhf.gov.uk/Directory/News/Homes_for_residents_not_overseas_investors.asp">used their stand</a> to make a strong case for development that provides <em>&ldquo;Homes for residents, not overseas investors&rdquo;</em>. It highlighted developers using <em>&ldquo;ridiculous viability assessments that offer piffling amounts of affordable homes&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Islington council leader Richard Watts said in <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/islington.pdf">his response</a> to <a href="http://www.unitetheunion.org/news/labour-councillors-urged-to-boycott-property-developers-fair-as-londons-housing-crisis-mounts/">Unite&rsquo;s call</a> for a boycott: <em>&ldquo;neither I nor anyone else from Islington council will be attending the event&rdquo;</em>. He explained that he was <em>&ldquo;deeply concerned at the lack of genuinely affordable housing in London .. and the increase in foreign investors who are pushing up housing prices to the detriment of our residents.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Southwark council leader Peter John&rsquo;s <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SouthwarkUniteResponse.pdf">response</a> took a different view. He said he would be unable to attend himself, but <em>&ldquo;does not agree with the request and the reasoning behind it&rdquo;</em> because the council needs to <em>&ldquo;continue working with the private sector to ensure that we can deliver as many homes as we can&rdquo;</em>. He concludes by reiterating his <em>&ldquo;commitment to build 11,000 new council homes at social rents.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>This commitment to build 11,000 new council homes has come under increasing scrutiny. Our <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">previous blog post</a> and <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2014/oct/07/southwark-london-regeneration-urban-renewal-social-cleansing-fears">this recent Guardian article</a> show how questions are being asked about whether they will be council homes and whether existing council homes will have to be lost for there to be any gains. So it&rsquo;s not reassuring that Southwark&rsquo;s MIPIM stand display describes the 11,000 new council homes as comprising <em>&ldquo;both private and social&rdquo;</em> housing as this image below shows:<br/>
<a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/southwarkMIPIMstand.png"><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/southwarkMIPIMstand.png"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/MipimStevePlattsJonAbbott.JPG"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/MipimStevePlattsJonAbbott.JPG" width="300" height="200"></a> Heckling protesters spotted Southwark&rsquo;s Head of Property Steve Platts and Head of Regeneration Jon Abbott attending the fair. It&rsquo;s a day out of the office, but they looked a little downcast; no doubt disappointed that Southwark was <a href="http://blog.mipimworld.com/2014/10/announcing-winners-mipim-uk-estates-gazette-awards/">beaten</a> by Croydon and Lambeth to the awards of &lsquo;Best UK Planning Authority&rsquo; and &lsquo;Best Public/Private Partnership&rsquo;.</p>

<p>If you would like to enjoy the full MIPIM experience without the canapés and champagne, click on this <a href="http://www.inspiredlabs.com/mipimuk/?project=MIPIM/Mipim-Uk-2014/GroundR/main&amp;bubble=day&amp;yaw=0.09&amp;fov=65&amp;location=loc000&amp;pitch=0">interactive floorplan</a> of the property fair.</p>

<h3>Developers ride the bus</h3>

<p><a href="http://t.co/LZwNl9yC2T"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/mipimbus.png" width="300" height="200"></a>We hope if you live in Southwark, you didn&rsquo;t see this bus driving down your street last week. It was full of MIPIM property developers making a quick trip from Earls Court, no doubt scoping out sites in the developer-friendly <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/11/southwark-gets-its-reward/">&lsquo;can do&rsquo;</a> borough of Southwark.
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>Evicting Aylesbury</h2>

<p><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/4/3941/14931046894_7eca1011dd_n.jpg" align="right">A High Court ruling <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/crime/judge-blasts-southwark-council-for-evicting-sudanese-tenant-and-destroying-his-possessions-9796994.html">condemning</a> Southwark officers for having conspired to evict a tenant from an estate in its North Peckham regeneration, is followed by news of a temporary tenant on the Aylesbury estate <a href="http://housingactionsouthwarkandlambeth.wordpress.com/2014/09/27/keeping-people-in-their-homes-a-southwark-council-guide-to-homelessness/">evicted</a> and left entirely homeless. HASL staged a protest in the Council&rsquo;s HQ on Thursday accompanied by the Focus E15 mums and the evictee; and refused to leave the lobby until the poor disabled woman was given a roof over her head. Southwark <a href="http://housingactionsouthwarkandlambeth.wordpress.com/2014/10/16/massive-housing-solidarity-southwark-council-ineptitude/">acquiesced</a> to the request and she was offered temporary accommodation (albeit with stairs..)</p>

<h3>Aylesbury estate SGTO meeting</h3>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SGTO25OctLeaflet4.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SGTOFlyer.png" width="200" height="350"></a>The disruptive impact of regenerations like the Heygate and the Aylesbury on people throughout Southwark has become more apparent day by day. It is not just that council tenants lose their homes, but that leaseholders get displaced and that housing and rehousing opportunities are lost for anyone on the council waiting list. The Southwark Group of Tenants Association has called a <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SGTO25OctLeaflet4.pdf">public meeting</a> about the future of the Aylesbury estate and the demolition of council homes. <a href="http://halag.wordpress.com/">Threatened Aylesbury leaseholders</a> will also be taking part in the meeting. In the meantime - 3 weeks since their submission - the Aylesbury planning applications have appeared on Southwark Council&rsquo;s planning portal (ref. numbers <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557152">14/AP/3843</a> and <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557153">14/AP/3844</a>) but we can&rsquo;t tell whether the applications meet with affordable housing requirements because there are still no planning documents online. Last week we emailed the council&rsquo;s planning dept to ask about the delay and we have still had no reply.</p>

<h2>Heygate FOI/EIR Tribunal Case</h2>

<p>Parties to the Heygate FOI/EIR Tribunal case reconvened at a &lsquo;Case Management Hearing&rsquo; last week. The hearing was called by respondent to the case Adrian Glasspool, who had complained that disclosure of the viability assessment had still not taken place following the Tribunal&rsquo;s decison at the beginning of May. After hearing an account of progress so far, Southwark, Lend Lease and the Information Commissioner were directed to meet on 29th October to try to resolve any outstanding issues concerning the final disclosure. The judge also asked for parties&#8217; availability for a further hearing - should it be needed - in December.</p>

<p>Another <a href="http://discussion.theguardian.com/comment-permalink/42351530">challenge</a> against a developer&rsquo;s use of viability assessments in Stoke Newington can be added to the list of challenges in our <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/11/southwark-gets-its-reward/">previous blog post</a>. Again the developer is arguing that local people simply would not understand what it is all about, just as was the argument in the Heygate FOI/EIR Tribunal case. After 3 days of argument in the High Court, the judge has retired to consider his verdict.</p>

<h2>Lyons Review reviews viability</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/lyonsreview.png" width="200" height="75">Viability assessments are also rapidly rising up the political agenda: the <a href="http://www.yourbritain.org.uk/uploads/editor/files/The_Lyons_Housing_Review_2.pdf">Lyons Housing Review</a> commissioned by the Labour Party and published last week, has identified <em>&ldquo;substantial concerns about the way in which the viability of local plans, CIL charging schedules and sites are tested. Evidence to the review suggested that this is compounded by the fact that there is no agreed methodology for viability assessment, which allows different parties to pick the methodology most to their advantage .. evidence to the review suggested that the current arrangements create a great deal of uncertainty and complexity, which works in favour of the partner with the most skilled consultants acting for it.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>The report then makes some suggestions for how the viability testing process can be improved:</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Definitive guidance should be produced to ensure a single and robust methodology for viability assessments to reduce the scope for different interpretations of viability and reduce uncertainty.&rdquo;</em> It argues that an <em>&ldquo;&lsquo;open-book&rsquo; approach to negotiating site specific viability is required, to increase transparency and speed of negotiations.&rdquo;</em> It also proposes <em>&ldquo;an arbitration service for S106 on large scale developments to be funded by the parties involved in the negotiation&rdquo;</em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Southwark Gets Its Reward]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/10/11/southwark-gets-its-reward/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-11T13:06:21+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/10/11/southwark-gets-its-reward</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.mipimuk-awards.co.uk/mipimukawards2014/shortlist"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/MipimAwards.jpg" width="350" height="230"></a>Southwark prides itself on being a &lsquo;developer friendly&rsquo; borough. It has been <a href="http://vimeo.com/71882474#t=125s">endorsed</a> by Lend Lease Director Rob Deck as a <strong>&lsquo;can do&rsquo;</strong> council and it has been <a href="http://www.mipimuk-awards.co.uk/mipimukawards2014/shortlist">shortlisted</a> (by developers) for the award of <strong>&lsquo;Best UK Planning Authority&rsquo;</strong> at next week&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.mipimuk.co.uk/"><strong>MIPIM</strong> jamboree</a>. But pressure is mounting on all councils including Southwark to withdraw from the MIPIM backscratching get-together. Over two dozen community groups, charities and trade unions have <a href="http://radicalhousingnetwork.org/mipim-uk/whos-opposing-mipim/">opposed MIPIM</a>. Unite, Britains largest union has <a href="http://www.unitetheunion.org/news/labour-councillors-urged-to-boycott-property-developers-fair-as-londons-housing-crisis-mounts/">written</a> to all of London&rsquo;s Labour-controlled councils  asking them to <em>&ldquo;withdraw from participation in MIPIM and the close relationships with private developers that the event seeks to foster.&rdquo;</em>; three have done so but not Southwark.</p>

<p><a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BzdVDNBCAAMCUu0.png"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BzdVDNBCAAMCUu0.png" width="350" height="230"></a>So it is a particulary embarrasing moment for Lend Lease to <a href="http://www.asx.com.au/asxpdf/20141009/pdf/42ss0tfmnqrw92.pdf">announce</a> on the Sydney Stock Exchange pre-sales totalling £312m (AUD$ 570m) from just 20% of the 3,000 homes it is building at the Elephant &amp; Castle. As we detailed in our <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/09/20/setting-the-record-straight/">previous blog</a>, Southwark is going to have to wait 11 years before it gets a sniff of any profit from the Heygate and so far Southwark has received just £15m of its £50m Heygate land receipt while having spent over £65m emptying and demolishing the estate.</p>

<h2>Developers behaving badly</h2>

<p>Some good examples of bad behaviour by developers using viability assessments to avoid building affordable housing are beginning to emerge.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/neobanksidecomparison.jpg" width="400" height="300">In Southwark, properties in the Neo Bankside development, opposite Tate Modern, were  <a href="http://www.colliers.com/~/media/Files/EMEA/UK/research/residential/201202-central-london-residential-market.pdf">reported</a> to be selling for an average of <strong>£1,326 per square foot</strong> in 2012, nearly double that claimed by developer <strong>Grosvenor</strong> when planning permission was granted: <strong>Grosvenor</strong>&rsquo;s <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6014_1.pdf">viability assessment</a> claimed its residential properties would sell for an average of just <strong>£754 per square foot</strong><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. These figures also take no account of the <a href="http://online.wsj.com/articles/europe-house-of-the-day-luxury-penthouse-on-the-bank-of-the-thames-photos-1412674116">unsold penthouses</a>, which are <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7512">currently on the market</a> for £22m (each). Put simply: the developer undervalued its development by at least £143m in order to avoid affordable housing requirements<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/NEOBanksidePenthouse.jpg" width="300" height="200">Southwark Council didn&rsquo;t refer the Neo Bankside viability assessment to the <a href="http://www.voa.gov.uk/DVS/index.html">District Valuer</a> or other independent expert for appraisal, but had its Internal Property Division look it over instead<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>. Its Property team recommended that the council accept the developer&rsquo;s poverty plea and settle for a <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/5356">conciliatory offer of a £9m in-lieu payment</a>. Based on Southwark&rsquo;s in-lieu affordable housing tariff <sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> this was a whopping gain to the developer of £16.2m.
The absence of any review or reappraisal mechanism in the planning approval, means that there is no chance that Southwark - or anyone in Southwark who needs affordable housing - will benefit from the properties being sold for twice the developer&rsquo;s original estimate.</p>

<p>Developer <strong>Grosvenor</strong>&rsquo;s viability assessment can currently be <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6014_1.pdf">viewed</a> on the council&rsquo;s planning portal. We presume this was a mistake by Southwark, so in the event that it gets removed we have uploaded a backup copy which can be viewed online <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6014_1.pdf">here</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SKMBT_DVSReport.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/DVSReport.png" width="200" height="350"></a>In Kensington &amp; Chelsea, the <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SKMBT_DVSReport.pdf">District Valuer&rsquo;s report</a> evaluating the developer&rsquo;s viability assessment for the Earl&rsquo;s Court regeneration was <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/development/earls-court-developer-ignored-house-price-rises/7005985.article">finally disclosed</a> thanks to the efforts of local campaigners. The report was highly critical, stating that the developer&rsquo;s assessment <em>&ldquo;ignores residential growth in values that occurs between construction start on site and the commencement of marketing and phased release of the dwellings&rdquo;</em>. The report concluded by recommending that the council implement a <em>‘review mechanism’</em> so that it could increase the level of affordable housing in line with changing market conditions throughout the 22 year scheme. Unfortunately, no such review mechanism was put in place.</p>

<p>In Fitzrovia, developer <strong>TMCT Associates</strong> has adopted a different tack: instead of underestimating sales values it has inflated build costs in its application for an office to residential conversion at Eastgate House, just around the corner from Tottenham Court Rd. As is usually the case here and elsewhere, Westminster planning committee were initially denied access to the viability assessment, but councillors have now demanded to see it. <a href="http://fitzrovia.org.uk/">Fitzrovia Neighbourhood Association</a> has got there first, and it has published <a href="http://news.fitzrovia.org.uk/2014/10/09/affordable-housing-viability-and-profit/">an account</a> of what it found in its newspaper Fitzrovia News. The Developer has estimated that it will cost a staggering £1.2m <strong>per flat</strong> to convert from offices to residential.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://ystudio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/gp2.jpg" width="300" height="200">Over in the huge <a href="http://knightdragon.com/greenwich-peninsula/current">Greenwich Peninsula regeneration</a> of 10,000 homes, Hong Kong developer <a href="http://knightdragon.com/"><strong>Knight Dragon</strong></a> has secured a reduction in the amount of affordable housing from 38% to 21%. Local campaigners City Peninsula Residents Association are fighting back and are due to appear at an Information Tribunal hearing in January in their efforts to reveal the viability assessment, which justifies the loss of around 1,700 affordable homes. The use of viability assessments in Greenwich <a href="http://www.thisislocallondon.co.uk/news/11500983._Pushing_poor_people_out____Greenwich_accused_of_affordable_housing_failure/">appears to be rampant</a>: none of the approved major developments over the last 12 months meets Greenwich&rsquo;s minimum requirement for 35% affordable housing.</p>

<h2>The benefit of review mechanisms</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BprjPdsCQAEG0ze.png" width="300" height="200">A recurring feature of planning approvals involving viability assessments is the absence of any review mechanism. This means that any uplift in London property prices between the approval of planning and sale of new homes will not be reflected in an increased affordable housing offer. This will be the case on the Heygate estate, where Southwark failed to follow the District Valuer&rsquo;s recommendation that a <em>&lsquo;review mechanism linked with delivery&rsquo;</em> should be made a condition of planning approval<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>. The 37% increase in Southwark&rsquo;s property prices since The Heygate planning application was submitted, will therefore be translated directly into developer profit; the £101m worth of affordable housing that Lend Lease said it couldn&rsquo;t afford to provide remains permanently written off. The Heygate development is not due to be completed until 2025. Any further increase in London property prices over the next 11 years will be converted into Lend Lease profit; the measly affordable housing offer of 79 social rented units out of 2,735 new homes will remain unchanged.</p>

<p>Review/re-appraisal mechanisms for viability assessments don&rsquo;t just make good sense: as well as being in Southwark&rsquo;s case a policy requirement<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>, they are recommended in the official RICS guidance on viability testing[^6].</p>

<p>Some other councils are starting to wake up to the problem of the misuse of viability assessments: Inside Housing <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/islingtons-planning-backlash-at-developer-super-profits/7005936.article">reported</a> that Islington Council plans to <em>&ldquo;clamp down on ‘artificially pessimistic’ viability studies used by developers to minimise affordable housing obligations.&rdquo;</em> Islington Council said it comes after it had <em>&ldquo;received a ‘significant number’ of viability studies that do not provide underlying methodology and modelling. These studies are ‘unsupported by robust evidence’ and create ‘an artificially pessimistic outcome’.&rdquo;</em></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See page 11 of the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6014_1.pdf">viability assessment</a> submitted by the developer and which is currently published (we presume mistakably) on the council&rsquo;s planning portal.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>£1,326 - £754 = £572 x 250,000 (<a href="http://www.native-land.com/development-portfolio/neo-bankside">total sqft residential</a>) = undervalued by £143m.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See paragraph 46 of the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/159669_1.pdf">Officer&rsquo;s report.</a><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://35percent.org/images/affordablehousingspg.pdf">planning policy</a> requires all developments in the North of the borough without on-site affordable housing to pay a minimum of £100,000 per habitable room in lieu of each affordable housing unit not provided (i.e. 35% of the total number of habitable rooms which in this case is <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6006_1.pdf">720 habitable rooms</a> = 252 x £100k = £25.2m). Indeed, developments on the riverside should provide more and are determined on a &lsquo;case-by-case&rsquo; basis. <a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>See paragraph 3.6.4 of RICS Guidance <a href="http://www.pas.gov.uk/c/document_library/get_file?uuid=2c5c4f63-5010-4839-83f9-4955cf09e0a9&amp;groupId=332612">Financial Viability in Planning 2012</a><a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>See paragraph 7.3.4 of Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/6069/draft_affordable_housing_spd_2011">Affordable Housing SPD</a><a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let's Talk About... Peter's Promises]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-04T15:21:48+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SNHeygateOverage.pdf"><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SN1100homes.png" width="400" align="right"></a>Southwark Council leader Peter John has pledged that the 11,000 new council homes to be built over the next 30 years will not entail the demolition of the same number of existing council homes. In an <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10997/an_open_letter_from_cllr_peter_john_leader_of_southwark_council">open letter</a> to all residents Cllr John says;</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;To be absolutely clear, the 11,000 new homes that we promise to deliver will be new homes additional to our existing stock. These will be council homes on council rents for those that need them. It has been said that what we are intending to do is demolish 11,000 existing council homes and replace them to reach our target of 11,000. This is just not true. These are new homes and do not include the existing stock of council housing.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200463/community_conversations/2923/lets_talk_about_new_council_homes_for_southwark"><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/communityconversation.png" width="300" height="200" align="left"></a>This emphatic promise has been prompted by residents’ concern about some of the questions Southwark are asking in their <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200463/community_conversations/2923/lets_talk_about_new_council_homes_for_southwark">resident survey</a> entitled <strong>‘Let’s talk about&hellip;new council homes for Southwark’</strong>. The survey seeks resident approval of a Charter of Principals for how the Council <em>‘will work with residents on our programme of investment and renewal’</em>. The <a href="http://www.sgto.org.uk/">Southwark Group of Tenants Association</a>&rsquo;s newsletter (issue 15) says that the survey <em>‘seems to confuse the building of 11,000 homes with the ‘renewal’ or ‘redevelopment’ of estates’</em>. Southwark Defend Council Housing puts it stronger - <em>‘Southwark Council threatens massive redevelopment of its housing estates in Camberwell &amp; Peckham’</em>, and links the questions to Southwark’s new CIL <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/07/23/mystery-objector-1301/"><em>‘Estate Renewal Zone&#8217;</em></a>.</p>

<h3>..the price tag</h3>

<p><img src="http://35percent.org/images/CILChargingZones.png" width="200" align ="right">All agree that building 11,000 council homes is a good promise and is off to a good start<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, but the promise now looks as if it has a price attached, a price which the resident survey is very artfully concealing. The survey talks of ‘principles’ and ‘pledges’ but makes no mention of the asset appraisal study of council stock that will determine which estates are chosen for redevelopment, nor the part the survey itself will play in making those choices. The asset appraisal study is due to be completed by December and is described in a recent council <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">cabinet report - ‘Next steps on Developing Long Term Plans for the Delivery of New Council Homes’</a>. The report says that the council must <em>‘identify as much potential land as possible for development opportunity’</em><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. This requires <em>‘a detailed and comprehensive appraisal be undertaken of the performance of the Housing Revenue Account (HRA) assets’</em><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> (ie council homes), leading to <em>‘an assessment of their worth to the housing business’</em><sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>.</p>

<h3>..the <strong>Asset Performance Evaluation Tool</strong></h3>

<p>Establishing the financial ‘worth’ of each council home does not end the process. Southwark will also look at ‘non-financial’ factors – income, employment, health, education and social exclusion – to see which stock <em>‘prevents the council effectively meeting its social housing objectives’</em><sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>. An <em>&lsquo;Asset Performance Evaluation Tool&rsquo;</em>, which includes <em>‘a measure of social return based on feedback from engagement with residents’</em><sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>, will ‘enable’ the council to reach its decisions.</p>

<p>Finally Southwark will make <em>‘a correlation of these results with open market values and development potential across the stock will identify candidate groups of assets where more detailed options appraisal could result in either opportunities for additional homes or improvements in values to the overall HRA business plan, increasing the surpluses that may be available to subsidise new developments.’</em><sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" rel="footnote">7</a></sup></p>

<p>Putting all this into plain English, Southwark will put a financial value on each of its estates, take a look at the lifestyles of its tenants and residents and estimate how much the land is worth to developers. The ‘options’ will then open up, including sell-offs (aka ‘improvements in value to the overall HRA business plan’). Putting it even more simply, it looks like Southwark will;</p>

<ul>
<li>see how much each council estate is worth&hellip;</li>
<li>see which ones it doesn’t like&hellip;.</li>
<li>see which ones it wants to ‘redevelop’&hellip;.</li>
</ul>


<p>This all paints a rather alarming picture, particularly in light of the Heygate experience where an <a href="http://betterelephant.org/blog/2012/12/23/1998-southwark-housing-stock-survey/">options appraisal study</a> which recommended retaining half the estate&rsquo;s buildings was ignored. The 35% campaign has requested a copy of the <strong>&lsquo;Asset Performance Evaluation Tool&rsquo;</strong> given the key part it looks like playing in the future of every Southwark council estate resident.</p>

<h2>Aylesbury - Stop Press</h2>

<p>The long-anticipated outline planning application and phase 1b/1c demolition applications have been submitted to Southwark Council. Residents in the first phase have received <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/scan0027.pdf">this letter</a> from agents acting on behalf of Notting Hill Housing Trust and Barratt. However, despite having been submitted on 25th September, there are no planning documents online yet. All we know at the moment is that the outline application is for 2,745 new &lsquo;private and affordable units&rsquo; including 1,070 parking spaces plus retail, office &amp; community space. The detailed application proposals include 815 new homes, new roads and some <em>&lsquo;public and private open space&rsquo;</em>.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Phases 1 &amp; 2 of the programme will deliver 447 social rented homes out of 669 total units by early 2016. <a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See para. 41 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See para. 50 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>See para. 50 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>See para. 51 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>See para. 55 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:7">
<p>See para. 53 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elephant Traders - Not in the Pink]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/09/27/penrose-street-sorting-office/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-27T09:31:46+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/09/27/penrose-street-sorting-office</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://tradingplaces-elephant.tumblr.com/"><img class="right" src="http://33.media.tumblr.com/eb768bd9c749502c3d8926ced246593f/tumblr_nbcjwdMLuv1tklzg2o1_1280.jpg" width="200" height="300"></a>We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/07/12/the-more-rent-seeking-elephants-at-elephant-the-better/">blogged</a> on 12th July about <a href="http://www.social-life.co/blog/post/Trading_Places_Elephant_and_Castle_regen/"><em>Social Life</em></a>, a social enterprise based on the Pullens estate. They have now completed their research on the Elephant &amp; Castle shopping centre redevelopment and how it is affecting the traders there. A concise and impressive report is now available <a href="http://tradingplaces-elephant.tumblr.com/">here</a>. Its conclusions will not surprise people familiar with the shopping centre. It says: <em>&ldquo;Overall, traders are anxious and concerned about the redvelopment. Many of the traders have mixed feelings about the plans.&rdquo;</em>;<em>&ldquo;The shopping centre is an important social space for traders, local people and regular customers and it plays a hugely important role in the social life of the local community.&rdquo;</em>;<em>&ldquo;The shopping centre supports dense networks of social relationships in the local area, across London and globally.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>We hope developers Delancey have read this report and are giving it full weight in their forthcoming planning application for the shopping centre&rsquo;s redevelopment. However, we hear from several sources that they are not treating the current occupants very well: rents are being raised and new rental agreements are in the form of licences rather than leases, which points towards them getting rid of shopkeepers rather than keeping them. An <a href="http://www.theprisma.co.uk/2014/09/21/how-changes-in-elephant-castle-will-affect-the-latino-community/">interview</a> with respected academic and Director of <a href="http://latinelephant.wordpress.com/">Latin Elephant</a> Patria Roman paints a similar picture. Nevertheless, one shopping centre leaseholder and popular venue for Latin American events appears to be fighting back - the <a href="https://www.change.org/p/southwark-council-save-the-coronet">&lsquo;Save the Coronet&rsquo; petition</a> now stands at 3,856 signatures.</p>

<h2>Sorting Office sorted?</h2>


<p><img class="left" src="http://walworthsociety.co.uk/images/Copy%20of%20image%20001%20-%20resized.jpg" width="300" height="150">Two contentious planning applications are pending just down the road from the Elephant in Walworth. One of these would see the effective demolition of a local heritage asset - the former sorting office on Penrose street, the other could jeopardise the future of much loved and valued local mental health charity <em>Cooltan Arts</em>.</p>

<p>The Sorting Office was built in 1897 and the Walworth Society has long been <a href="http://walworthsociety.co.uk/index.php/blog/116-31-penrose-street-walworths-victorian-sorting-office">campaigning</a> to have it retained as part of the extensive redevelopment of the area. A previous planning application was refused after a large number of objections to its demolition. Its owner is now back with <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9554889">another application</a> which looks like a prime example of &lsquo;facadism&rsquo;: an increasingly common practice which has been <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/architecture-design-blog/2014/aug/25/front-facade-bad-developments-ruining-historic-buildings">described</a> in the development industry as a <em>&ldquo;wilful two fingers up&rdquo;</em> to local planners.</p>

<p>The application is for 6 x 3 storey and 2 x 2 storey town houses, 8 being just below Southwark&rsquo;s threshold for an affordable housing contribution. They will be squeezed behind the retained facade and side wall, but require the demolition of the rest of the sorting office and surrounding outbuildings.</p>

<h2>Cooltan Arts - threat</h2>


<p><img class="right" src="http://www.cooltanarts.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/DSCF4054-lr.jpg" width="300" height="200">Cooltan Arts, long term residents of the Walworth road were relocated last year on the <a href="http://www.cooltanarts.org.uk/2013/10/cooltan-arts-community-space-for-237-walworth-road/">promise</a> that they would be able to return to redveloped premises on their former site off the Walworth road. But a revised planning application for the site no longer contains this promise to reprovide space for Cooltan (nor does it contain the amount of affordable housing required by policy). Objections to the application <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeResultDetail&amp;TheSystemkey=9553921">ref:(14/AP/0830)</a> can still be sent to <a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#x74;&#x6f;&#58;&#112;&#x6c;&#97;&#110;&#110;&#x69;&#x6e;&#x67;&#x2e;&#x61;&#x70;&#112;&#x6c;&#105;&#x63;&#97;&#116;&#105;&#x6f;&#110;&#x73;&#x40;&#x73;&#x6f;&#117;&#x74;&#x68;&#x77;&#97;&#x72;&#x6b;&#x2e;&#103;&#111;&#x76;&#46;&#x75;&#107;&#x2e;">&#112;&#x6c;&#97;&#110;&#x6e;&#105;&#x6e;&#x67;&#x2e;&#97;&#112;&#x70;&#x6c;&#105;&#99;&#x61;&#116;&#105;&#111;&#x6e;&#115;&#x40;&#115;&#x6f;&#x75;&#116;&#104;&#x77;&#x61;&#114;&#x6b;&#x2e;&#103;&#x6f;&#x76;&#x2e;&#117;&#x6b;&#46;</a></p>

<h2>Developers award Southwark top marks</h2>


<p>Southwark Council has been <a href="http://www.mipimuk-awards.co.uk/mipimukawards2014/shortlist">shortlisted</a> for two awards at the latest property developers&#8217; jamboree <strong>&lsquo;MIPIM UK&rsquo;</strong>, due to be held at Kensington Olympia on 15th-17th October. Southwark is in the running to be both <em>&ldquo;UK best planning authority of the year&rdquo;</em> and <em>&ldquo;Public-Private Partnership of the Year&rdquo;</em> for the Aylesbury estate. The MIPIM awards <a href="http://www.mipimuk-awards.co.uk/mipimukawards2014/shortlist">web page</a> claims that for developers, Southwark is both <em>&ldquo;welcoming and demanding&rdquo;</em>. We agree that it is certainly welcoming but as we have shown, it is not so demanding - especially when it comes to enforcing its own minimum policies on affordable housing contributions.</p>

<p>MIPIM also states in the citation for the Aylesbury partnership award that 75% of its affordable housing will be social rented. We doubt very much that all the new social rented homes will be at social rents and suspect that the forthcoming Aylesbury outline planning application will replace at least some of it with the new so-called &lsquo;affordable rents&#8217;of up to 80% market rent.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/09/peter-j-mipim.jpg?w=500&h=409" width="375" height="375">MIPIM itself is usually held in sunny <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/6687">Cannes</a>. In 2013 the Council leader was <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/SNCannesMipim.pdf">accused</a> of <em>&lsquo;going on a jolly&rsquo;</em> to the event paid for by developer Lend Lease and last year he <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7449">withdrew</a> after protests and demonstrations. This year it is proving equally controversial: several Councils have pulled out after media pressure and an <a href="http://southwarknotes.wordpress.com/2014/09/21/open-letter-to-southwark-council-to-not-attend-mipim/">open letter</a> signed by several local campaign groups asks Southwark to join them. So far Council leader Peter John is unimpressed.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://radicalhousingnetwork.org/">Radical Housing Network</a> is organising protests during the exhibiton on 15th - 17th October.</p>

<h2>Heygate viability assessment latest</h2>


<p>After a long appeal against the Information Commisioner&rsquo;s decision, the Information Tribunal ordered Southwark Council and Lend Lease to disclose the Heygate viability assessment back in May. The Tribunal extended the time for forwarding the assessment to the Information Commissioner back in June, but the assessment has still not been revealed. After inquiries to the Tribunal by Mr Glasspool who requested the information, a case management hearing has now been scheduled for 15th October.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting the Record Straight]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/09/20/setting-the-record-straight/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-20T13:15:14+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/09/20/setting-the-record-straight</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Southwark Council has had its feathers ruffled by both the Guardian and the BBC lately. A <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2014/sep/17/truth-property-developers-builders-exploit-planning-cities">Guardian article</a> by Oliver Wainright uses the redevelopment of the Heygate estate as an example of how developers are <em>&lsquo;exploiting planning authorities and ruining our cities&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Southwark Council has posted a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1785/setting_the_record_straight_the_true_value_of_the_elephant_and_castle_regeneration">press statement</a> <strong>&lsquo;setting the record straight&rsquo;</strong>, in which it claims it will receive <em>&ldquo;phased payments as the scheme progresses&rdquo;</em> and this will amount to <em>&ldquo;hundreds of millions&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/HeygateLandReceipts.png"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/rapage70.png" width="400" height="620"></a>It is true that there will be phased payments amounting to £50m (£46m for the main site + £4m for the Rodney road site) - this figure is now well known from the leaked <a href="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf">Regeneration Agreement</a>, but getting the <em>&ldquo;hundreds of millions&rdquo;</em> of pounds depends upon the so-called &lsquo;overage&rsquo; or &lsquo;super-profit&rsquo; and how much this will be, if anything, won&rsquo;t be known until the project is completed in 2025.</p>

<p>The overage will be what is left over after building costs, a 2.6% management fee and 20% priority developer return is deducted from the total sales revenue and it will be calculated according to Lend Lease&rsquo;s financial model, as detailed in a 3000 page spreadsheet known as Appendix 22 of the Heygate viability assessment. This complicated accounting process is entirely under Lend Lease&rsquo;s control and while the Council has the right to inspect the financial model, this may not guarantee the expected overage windfall as the Barangaroo Delivery Authority in Sydney Australia <a href="http://www.smh.com.au/nsw/barangaroo-public-works-in-doubt-after-government-loses-court-battle-with-lend-lease-20140821-106lke.html">is finding out</a> to its cost.</p>

<p>Any reckoning of the gain due to Southwark must also take into account the £65m<a href="#footnote-1">[1]</a> it has spent on Heygate decant costs plus an unquantified amount of public money devoted to regeneration since the wider E&amp;C scheme was conceived, starting with the £25m Single Regeneration Budget (SRB) funding received back in 1999.</p>

<p>On top of the Guardian’s Heygate story the BBC has taken up the plight of Aylesbury leaseholders being &lsquo;forced out of the city&rsquo;, with an <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-london-29098960">online article</a> and televised reports on both its London News and <a href="http://youtu.be/RtvghCKNJjQ">Inside Out programme</a> on 8th Sep. Inside Out did not think much of the paltry amount of compensation leaseholders on the Aylesbury estate were being offered, particularly in comparison to the £340k cost of one-bed properties in the area and described the situation as <em>&lsquo;the Right to Buy dream turned sour&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<center>
<iframe width="350" height="197" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/RtvghCKNJjQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</center>


<p>Southwark again &lsquo;sets the record straight&rsquo; and <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1767/southwark_councils_full_response_to_bbc_inside_out_programme">insists</a> that offers such as <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/05/16/southwark-gives-green-light-to-slum-landlords/">£85k for a 1-bed flat</a> are based on <em>&ldquo;actual market evidence of properties being sold on the Aylesbury estate&rdquo;</em>. This method of basing valuations on the sales prices of other properties depressed by the prospect of demolition has been <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/05/30/aylesbury-leaseholder-fights-incestuous-valuation/">criticised</a> by the Lands Tribunal. Southwark Council&rsquo;s valuers are also pretty imaginative in the way they gather &lsquo;market evidence&rsquo;, using a <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/05/16/southwark-gives-green-light-to-slum-landlords/">1-bed property which had been illegally converted</a> to 4 beds flat as the basis of the compensation for one unfortunate leaseholder.  The derisory compensation offered to Aylesbury leaseholders is in stark contrast to the abundant profit that the builder of the Aylesbury redevelopment Barratt has just <a href="http://www.thisismoney.co.uk/money/markets/article-2750592/Booming-UK-housing-market-fuels-doubling-annual-profits-Barratt.html">announced</a>.</p>

<p>The Guardian and BBC stories reflect a wide-spread public view that developers and housebuilders are making big profits at local people’s expense and taking Southwark for a ride (an <a href="https://www.change.org/p/heygate-estate-scandal-demand-an-investigation">online petition</a> demanding an investigation into the Heygate development has gained over 700 signatures in 3 days) and a couple of press releases from Southwark won’t change this view.</p>

<p><font size="2"><p id="footnote-1">[1] See paragraphs 5.34 &amp; 5.35 of the Project Director&rsquo;s Jan 2013 <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/8171/proofs_of_evidence_%E2%80%93_jon_abbot_%E2%80%93_final_proof">CPO public inquiry evidence.</a> </p></font></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notting Hill Housing Trust - Quids in With Boris]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/08/19/notting-hill-housing-trust-quids-in-with-boris/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-19T17:53:38+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/08/19/notting-hill-housing-trust-quids-in-with-boris</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Notting Hill Housing Trust is an important provider of housing in Southwark, both &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; and <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/00,news,26531,440,00.htm">private</a>. It has plans to build more than 4000 homes in Southwark; 3500 of these will be on the Aylesbury estate, which it is redeveloping <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/about-us/building-new-homes/our-developments/aylesbury-estate-southwark">in partnership</a> with Britain&rsquo;s largest - and the mayor&rsquo;s favourite - housebuilder Barratt Homes. According to the NHHT <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/asset/view/6912.pdf">website</a>, a hybrid application comprising outline planning for the whole Aylesbury and detailed planning for the first phase is due to be submitted by the NHHT/Barratt consortium next month.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/development/greater-london-authority-allocates-404m-for-affordable-homes/7004790.article"><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/nottinghillfunding.png" width="400" height="300"></a>Notting Hill has secured more money than any other housing association from the Mayor&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.london.gov.uk/priorities/housing-land/increasing-housing-supply/affordable-homes-programme">affordable housing fund</a> (£59m - nearly three times the amount of the next highest provider). However, it is <a href="http://www.cih.org/news-article/display/vpathDCR/templatedata/cih/news-article/data/Losing_social_homes_means_we_are_storing_up_trouble">well known</a> that a condition of getting money from this funding stream is that only affordable rented homes can be built - not social rented. This was <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk//7005104.article">cited</a> by London Labour housing spokesperson Tom Copley as the reason why so few housing associations had applied for the funding, of which £380m still remains unallocated.</p>

<p>Notting Hill Housing Trust enthusiastically <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/06/16/notting-hill-housing-no-social-housing">endorses</a> the Mayor&rsquo;s affordable rent policies, which may explain why Boris Johnson is so happy to give it so much money.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/SouthwarkMarketRents.png">Aylesbury estate tenants will have the right to a tenancy in the new Notting Hill development and those already &lsquo;decanted&rsquo; to other parts of the borough will have the right to return, but if the affordable rents are 80% of market rent this won&rsquo;t mean very much. Southwark Council&rsquo;s recently published &lsquo;Affordable Rent Product Study&rsquo; gives £289pw as the market rent of a 1-bed flat in SE17 – 80% of this would be £231pw.  A council rent for a 1-bed flat in SE17 is currently around £100pw.</p>

<p>Southwark Council has repeatedly said in public that there would be 50% affordable housing on the new Aylesbury, of which 75% would be social rented and this was written into its <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200211/area_action_plans/1327/aylesbury_area_action_plan">planning policy for the scheme</a>. Notting Hill Housing Trust now says that social rent is the same as affordable rent and probably thinks that people are too stupid to tell the difference.</p>

<p>We think that any Aylesbury tenant moving into one of the replacement homes should not be expected to pay much more than their current council rent. If Southwark doesn&rsquo;t want to see another Heygate-style diaspora of long-standing communities then it should hold good on its promises, stick to its policies and ensure that policy definitions are not allowed to be blurred.</p>

<h2>Notting Hill Housing Trust - Manor Place Depot</h2>


<p><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/manorplace.jpg" width="300" height="200">We <a href="http://affordable.heroku.com/blog/2014/06/16/notting-hill-housing-no-social-housing/">blogged</a> in June about the prospect of no social housing in Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s Manor Place Depot development. Since then NHHT appears to have had a change of heart.</p>

<p>One of our members visited NHHT&rsquo;s second exhibition for its Manor Place Depot development and reported back as follows:</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;The exhibition gave no figures for the housing , simply saying some of the housing would be affordable rent, of which social rent was as a subset.  However discussions with NHHT staff yielded the following information:</em></p>

<p><em>The 35% target for affordable housing would be met, with 95 units out of the 270 proposed.  Of these 95 units, 50% will be affordable rent and 50% shared ownership.  NHHT defines affordable rent as including social rent, and there will be some social rent though they don&rsquo;t know how much until the viability assessment.  NHHT policy, they say, is for all the family units to be at social rent.</em></p>

<p><em>Since the first exhibition, NHHT has received GLA funds for all of its sites.  This contributes £30,000 - £40,000 of the cost per unit, they say.  NHHG were unwilling to provide information as to what exact tenure mix this public funding will subsidise, and how it differs per site.</em></p>

<p><em>On affordable market rent, NHHT say they don&rsquo;t go anywhere near 80% market rent and have a cap in London of £230 (i.e. this is the maximum affordable market rent they will charge, they say).</em></p>

<p><em>They said that there will be a further exhibition in September/October ahead of the planning application in November/December.&ldquo;</em></p>

<h4>We say:</h4>


<p>Social rented housing and affordable rented housing are not one and the same thing, Notting Hill Housing Trust needs to stop muddying the waters. If it wants to start consulting meaningfully with local people it must tell them exactly how much social rented housing there will be and how much affordable rented housing there will be and exactly how much rent they will be charging for each.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mind the (Elephantine) Gap]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/08/12/mind-the-gap/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-12T18:09:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/08/12/mind-the-gap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A £64m funding gap for the infrastructure improvements of the Elephant &amp; Castle regeneration has been identified by Southwark Council. The figure is given in its <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10740/addendum_to_cdeip1">submission</a> to the Government inspector examining Southwark&rsquo;s plans for raising funds from developers through the new Community Infrastructure Levy.</p>

<p><img src="http://affordable.herokuapp.com/images/fundinggap.png"></p>

<p>The hoped-for improvements include a new northern line ticket hall, better access to the mainline station, a remodelled northern roundabout, new leisure centre, GP surgeries and refurbished Town Hall with library and museum.</p>

<p>Evidently the money raised from developments at the Elephant so far has not been enough to provide all the benefits that everybody was expecting from the regeneration and so far committed public funding is not enough to fill the gap. This gap comprises a £40m shortfall for the northern line tube station upgrade, £12m needed for the mainline train station upgrade and about £9m needed for the northern roundabout improvements. The reason for the shortfalls is that developers are not paying enough. The CIL predecessor at the Elephant was the Elephant &amp; Castle Strategic Transport Tariff, which required developers to pay £175 per m2 of any new residential floorspace towards public transport infrastructure. The problem is that developers regularly submitted viability assessments showing that they couldn&rsquo;t afford to pay the full tariff. For example, Lend Lease was able to re-negotiate the tariff for its Heygate redevelopment down to a level of £104 per m2, providing a total transport contribution of £13m when it should have paid £22m:</p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/254761_1.pdf"><img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/s106headsofterms.png"></a></p>

<p>In making up the shortfall, Southwark hopes to gain £18.5m in CIL contributions from future developments at the Elephant over the next 15 years, but this is obviously not enough and it could mean raiding CIL yields from elsewhere in the borough or CIL destined for health facilities, open space or public realm benefits.</p>

<p><a href="https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/rbi-blogs/wp-content/blogs.dir/303/files/2014/06/the-blades-MoS.jpg"><img class="right" src="https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/rbi-blogs/wp-content/blogs.dir/303/files/2014/06/the-blades-MoS.jpg" width="300" height="200"></a>The model of private development cross-subsidising public benefits is plainly not working. While public assets (eg. the disposal of public land or spending from public funds) is fuelling the regeneration, developers aren&rsquo;t paying enough towards the improvements. As we have <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/04/15/the-elephants-new-ivory-towers">shown</a> they systematically use viability assessments to wriggle out of planning contributions and all we are ending up with is social-housing free towers sprouting up across the Elephant (the latest proposed being the Ministry of Sound&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.estatesgazette.com/blogs/london-residential-research/2014/06/planning-battle-ministry-move/">&lsquo;the blades&rsquo;</a>).</p>

<h2>360 Tower PRS deal collapses</h2>


<p><img class="left" src="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/imageuploads/1299150006_80.177.117.97.jpg" width="300" height="200">We <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/03/31/middlemen-on-the-make">blogged</a> earlier in the year about Elephant tower of shame the &lsquo;London 360 Tower&rsquo;. The latest news is that the groundbreaking plans for it to be one of the first large PRS - private rented sector developments in London have collapsed according to an <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/03/31/middlemen-on-the-make">article</a> in Property Week magazine. There is no information as to why this has happened - perhaps developers want a quicker return on their investment than PRS will provide? Delancey &amp; APG are also proposing a PRS development for the new shopping centre - will it go the same way? Maybe former deputy Council leader <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2013/12/07/kim-humphreys-exit-stage-left">turned development consultant</a> Kim Humphries knows?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Southwark's Mysterious Estate Renewal Zone]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/07/23/mystery-objector-1301/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-23T09:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/07/23/mystery-objector-1301</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Our <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/07/19/community-infrastructure-levy/">search</a> to identify mystery Objector 1301 - who is lobbying for subsidies to knock down Southwark&rsquo;s council estates at next week&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/856/planning_policy/2696/community_infrastructure_levy">CIL public inquiry</a> - has brought some clarity but also some more mystery with it.</p>

<p>Having been pointed towards Southwark Council&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10738/cdcil5_appendix_i_of_regulation_19_consultation_statement">table of responses</a> to CIL objector representations, we noted that the Council&rsquo;s response to <strong>Objector 1301</strong>&rsquo;s objection makes it fairly clear who the objector is, but it also raises some worrying questions about the Aylesbury redevelopment and the Council&rsquo;s plan for the future of some of its housing estates in general.</p>

<p>In its response to <strong>Objector 1301</strong>, the Council makes the worrying admission that <strong> <em>&ldquo;The appraisal showed the [Aylesbury] site to be unviable with the requisite of providing 50% affordable housing.&rdquo;</em> </strong><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10738/cdcil5_appendix_i_of_regulation_19_consultation_statement">(pg 106)</a> and it then goes on to confirm that under the terms of the development agreement Notting Hill will be providing<strong> <em>&ldquo;affordable rented units&rdquo;.</em> </strong><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10738/cdcil5_appendix_i_of_regulation_19_consultation_statement">(pg 107)</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/zone3.png"><img class="right" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/zone3.png" width="400" height="300"></a>But more worrying is the Council&rsquo;s response on page 109, where it states that it has <strong> <em>&ldquo;recommended a lower CIL rate in the lower value area of the Borough, within which the majority of housing estates identified for Estate renewal are located.&rdquo;</em> </strong><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10738/cdcil5_appendix_i_of_regulation_19_consultation_statement">(pg 109)</a>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
<a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/CILChargingZones.png"><img class="left" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/CILChargingZones.png" width="400" height="800"></a>This estate renewal zone is shown as zone 3 in the map above. You can see from the map on the left that the Council&rsquo;s planners have split the borough into 3 zones for the puroposes of its CIL charging schedule. Zone 1 (bankside) will charge developers £400 per sqm for new residential buildings, zone 2 (the rest of the borough) will charge £200 per sqm, and developers in zone 3 - the <strong> <em>&lsquo;low value area&rsquo;</em> </strong>where <strong> <em>&lsquo;the majority of housing estate identified for renewal are located&rsquo;</em> </strong>- will be charged just £50 per sqm.</p>

<p></br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
<a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/MapSouthwarkEstates.png"><img class="right" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/MapSouthwarkEstates.png" width="300" height="300"></a>Southwark&rsquo;s new estate renewal zone reaches right up to East Street, extends down to include most of Peckham and stretches from Rotherhithe in the East across to include most of the Brandon estate in the west. The map on the right illustrates that a significant proportion of the Council&rsquo;s housing stock is within the boundary of zone 3 and much of this comprises estates that haven&rsquo;t yet been brought up to Decent Homes standard.</p>

<p>No reference can be found in any other policy documents relating to this estate renewal zone. So is this a precursory indication of what could be found in the forthcoming replacement of the borough&rsquo;s Core Strategy? (which is as usual currently being drafted behind closed doors), or is it more an insight into Southwark&rsquo;s contradictory <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1617/southwark_council_challenges_mayor_over_affordable_rent">outwardly oppositional</a> but inwardly complicit stance towards controversial <a href="http://www.standard.co.uk/news/politics/eric-pickles-tear-down-estates-to-boost-poor-innercity-homes-9277330.html">government</a> and mayoral housing policy? In any case we would be interested to know if any council tenants or leaseholders in zone 3 have been notified that their estates have been <strong> <em>&ldquo;identified for estate renewal&rdquo;</em> </strong>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PRS - (Private Rip-off Sector)]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/07/19/community-infrastructure-levy/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-19T13:20:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/07/19/community-infrastructure-levy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Delancey has been very shy about telling us what rents it will be charging for its new Private Rented Sector (PRS) homes in its <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7258">shopping centre</a> and <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7208">Tribeca Square</a> developments (which could total around 2000 units). We can now tell you: at least £375 per week for a 1-bed and £500 per week for a 2-bed flat; hardly rents that are <em>&ldquo;relevant to Londoners earning London wages&rdquo;</em> as Delancey has hitherto <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7378">maintained</a>. We know this because it is written in the evidence<a href="#footnote-1">[1]</a> submitted on behalf of Delancey by its representative Deloitte to next week&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/856/planning_policy/2696/community_infrastructure_levy">public inquiry</a> examining Southwark&rsquo;s new Community Infrastructure Levy (CIL) charging schedules:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/DelanceyCILSubmissionPRSRentLevels.png"></p>

<p>CIL is the amount a developer must pay towards public infrastructure and largely replaces the current s106 contributions. Developers don&rsquo;t like CIL because - unlike s106 - it is non-negotiable and they are now busy pleading poverty to try and get the CIL levy reduced. Delancey, joined by British Land, Berkeley homes, Sellar, Lend Lease etc. are claiming that the CIL tariffs proposed are a big threat to the viability of future projects and the delivery of affordable housing (not that the absence of affordable housing has worried them in the past!).</p>

<p>Delancey is also making an argument for reducing CIL in the particular case of Private Rented Sector developments, which is no surprise given the two sizeable PRS developments it has in its pipeline. Despite the eye-watering rents, it claims that it can&rsquo;t make as much money out of PRS as it would do if it were building private housing for sale. Added to this it has to wait longer to extract its customary 20% profit. Thankfully on this occasion Southwark Council appears to be standing its ground and rejects Delancey&rsquo;s argument<a href="#footnote-2">[2]</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/LBSResponseToCILSubmissions.png"></p>

<h3>Wanted: Objector 1301</h3>


<p><img class="left" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/objector1301.jpg" width="300" height="200">As well as Delancey, Deloitte is representing several other developers at the inquiry, but none are as mysterious as <strong>Objector 1301</strong> whose identity is &lsquo;confidential&rsquo;<a href="#footnote-3">[3]</a>. We are not surprised that objector 1301 wants to keep himself in the shadows, because his great idea is that anybody knocking down and redeveloping a council estate should not pay any CIL at all! <strong>Objector 1301</strong>&rsquo;s argument is that the cost of having to give ex-tenants and leaseholders fair compensation for losing their homes (although it is seldom fair) is too high to maintain the customary 20% profit, while also paying for local public infrastructure. <strong>Objector 1301</strong>&rsquo;s solution to the problem is simple and elegant - just insert a footnote saying that none of the above applies to council estate regenerations<a href="#footnote-4">[4]</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/objector1301.png"></p>

<p>Who can this mystery <strong>Objector 1301</strong> be? Property developers have no qualms about being unpopular in their pursuit of profit, it is the nature of the beast. But a Housing Association may well feel the need to maintain its anonymity. Their free-market orientation is becoming more <a href="http://www.socialhousing.co.uk/free-preview-social-housings-2014-sales-and-development-activity-special-report/7004650.article">apparent</a> day by day, but Housing Associations must at least keep up the pretense of being affordable housing providers. If <strong>Objector 1301</strong> is a housing association could it possibly be one with extensive interests in Southwark? maybe one with the initials NHHT? We don&rsquo;t know for sure, but the 35% campaign is offering a small reward for any information that leads to the identification of this mystery objector.</p>

<p><font size="2"><p id="footnote-1">[1] See page 187 of <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10287/cdcil9_regulation_17_representations_to_revised_draft_cil_charging_schedule">submitted written representations to CIL Charging Schedule</a></p></font></p>

<p><font size="2"><p id="footnote-2">[2] See para 38 of <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10211/cdcil10_revised_draft_cil_charging_schedule_submission_report_april_2014">April 2014 CIL Charging Schedule Submission Report</a></p></font></p>

<p><font size="2"><p id="footnote-3">[3] See page 144 of <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10287/cdcil9_regulation_17_representations_to_revised_draft_cil_charging_schedule">submitted written representations to CIL Charging Schedule</a></p></font></p>

<p><font size="2"><p id="footnote-4">[4] See page 146 of <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10287/cdcil9_regulation_17_representations_to_revised_draft_cil_charging_schedule">submitted written representations to CIL Charging Schedule</a></p></font></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Where There's Bronze There's Brass]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/07/12/the-more-rent-seeking-elephants-at-elephant-the-better/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-12T11:03:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/07/12/the-more-rent-seeking-elephants-at-elephant-the-better</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/samkeilelephant.jpg"><img class="left" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/samkeilelephant.jpg" width="300" height="200"></a>Just when we thought the Heygate pyramid had set the limits on misconceived artistic collaborations at the Elephant, we got wind of the latest &lsquo;triumphant elephant&rsquo; sculpture proposal.
According to <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/samkeil_bio_2010.pdf">documents</a> posted on artist Sam Keil&rsquo;s website <em>&ldquo;the team responsible for the redevelopment of the Elephant and Castle district in South London have commissioned Sam to sculpt a major piece for a new public square&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p>The sculpture proposed on the site of the former Heygate estate football pitch is to comprise a bronze elephant <a href="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/keil_elephant.pdf"><em>&ldquo;standing on its hind legs on top of a tall castle tower, in the act of leaping into the air with its water-spraying trunk raised high in triumph.&rdquo;</em></a> The project also includes <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/samkeil_bio_2010.pdf"><em>&ldquo;a series of small elephants which will be distributed as bronze key rings to the owners of the many new apartments associated with the redevelopment.&rdquo;</em></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.vallico.net/sam/img/relief/2.jpg"><img class="right" src="http://www.vallico.net/sam/img/relief/2.jpg" width="300" height="200"></a>Sam has <a href="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/keil_elephant.pdf">published the full proposal</a> of the project on her website along with an example of her previous work at a St. John&rsquo;s Wood development, where - under the heading <em>&ldquo;The Effect of a Sam Keil Bronze on Property&rdquo;</em> - she claims that her sculptures enable developers to <em>&ldquo;charge whatever rent you like&rdquo;</em> . A letter from Southwark is also appended to her proposal in which Council bosses claim to be <em>&ldquo;very enthusiastic&rdquo;</em> about the idea, because it would be <em>&ldquo;well received locally&rdquo;</em> and that <em>&ldquo;the more elephants at the elephant the better!&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.vallico.net/sam/img/prince_philip.jpg" width="300" height="200">International artist Keil, seen here rubbing shoulders with Prince Philip, is represented by a <a href="http://www.whpatterson.com/">fine-art gallery</a> in Mayfair. Although Sam&rsquo;s husband claims that she got the commission <a href="http://www.barganews.com/blogs/towler/?p=37"><em>&ldquo;essentially because she knows one guy with connections&rdquo;</em></a> and that <a href="http://www.barganews.com/blogs/towler/?p=37"><em>&ldquo;not only can she sculpt, but she’s got a nice bottom&rdquo;</em></a>. Sam says that in her spare time she enjoys riding horses <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/samkeil_bio_2010.pdf"><em>&ldquo;bareback in the Arizona Badlands and also in the Negev desert in Israel&rdquo;</em></a>.</p>

<p>Sam <a href="http://www.vallico.net/sam/biography.html">works</a> from her studios in Cambridge and Tuscany and has delivered other high-profile sculptures during her career. In 2011 she <a href="http://www.vallico.net/sam/docs/ft.pdf">presented</a> a bronze eagle to former BP Chief Exec Lord Browne at the Royal Academy of Engineering. Her eagle is <a href="http://www.vallico.net/sam/docs/mike_towler_royal_academy.txt">claimed</a> to signify a <em>&ldquo;symbol of power&rdquo;</em> in manifesting the desire to make the <em>&ldquo;UK the King of Nations again&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Sam claims her bronze elephant <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/samkeil_bio_2010.pdf"><em>&ldquo;`Phoenix&#8217; with water soaring from his trunk will be a new twenty-first century update of the well-known elephant motif for the area&rdquo;</em></a>. We think it will be a tasteless and poorly thought-out marketing gimmick with little public value and a monument to how out-of-touch Southwark regen bosses are with local opinion.</p>

<h2>Kim Consulting (Limited)</h2>


<p><a href="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/photo-5-1.jpg"><img class="right" src="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/photo-5-1.jpg" width="300" height="200"></a>Delancey&rsquo;s long-promised consultation on the future of the shopping centre has finally begun. Ex-deputy Council Leader <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2013/12/07/kim-humphreys-exit-stage-left">turned development consultant</a> Kim Humphries, could be seen buttonholing unsuspecting shoppers last Friday to get their views on the redevelopment. One of the key questions being put is: <em>&ldquo;Do you think that the whole of the shopping centre site should be redeveloped rather than refurbished?“</em> This can only be rhetorical, because as our friends at <a href="http://southwarknotes.wordpress.com">Southwark Notes</a> point out - the decision to demolish the shopping centre has already been <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7378">taken</a> by Delancey. Southwark Council has also <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1368/council_will_insist_on_demolition_of_shopping_centre_at_elephant">decided</a> to &lsquo;insist&rsquo; on demolition of the centre.</p>

<p>At a recent Walworth Society meeting, Delancey said that it hopes to complete the consultation and submit a planning application by May 2014. They listed 94 community groups of different kinds that they said they will consult. One group omitted from the list were the shopkeepers. When challenged, Delancey insisted that shopkeepers&#8217; views would be taken fully into account, but that another team of Delancey operatives would be talking to the shopkeepers at the same time as re-negotiating their leases. We are sure this twin-track approach will not inhibit shopkeepers expressing their views. We hear that leases currently offered for renewal are limited to 5 years with a &lsquo;break clause&rsquo; in November 2016, which suggests that this might be the time that those who don&rsquo;t fit the profile of the new town centre will be leaving us.</p>

<p>Delancey is a private developer and a big one. It is registered in the British Virgin Islands and how Delancey turns this to good advantage has already been exposed in <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/PrivateEyeNo1311.pdf">Private Eye</a> and a Channel 4 Dispatches programme. It is <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/newsbysector/constructionandproperty/8606978/Minerva-deal-sees-Jamie-Ritblat-follow-in-fathers-property-footsteps.html">run</a> by Jamie Ritblat and funded by George Soros. Jamie is following in his dad&rsquo;s footsteps - former British Land chief executive Sir John Ritblat - and is a donor to the Tory party. He courted <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2041229/Tory-donor-Jamie-Ritblat-snaps-Olympic-Village-knock-price--costing-275m.html">controversy</a> in 2011 when he snapped up the Olympic Village at a knock down price of £557million – £275million less than the taxpayer paid <a href="http://www.thelondonmagazine.co.uk/property-experts/expert-opinions/the-olympic-village.html">bailing out</a> the previous owner - Lend Lease. Standing behind Jamie is the richest man in the world, George Soros. Mr Soros is notorious for nearly bankrupting the Bank of England and tipping the rest of us into poverty. Mr Soros claims to be <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2012/sep/13/black-wednesday-20-years-pound-erm">proud</a> of the fact the he made £1bn selling sterling that he didn&rsquo;t own. We obviously need have no fear about the future of the shopping centre development not being in good hands.</p>

<h3>Shopping Centre who&#8217;s who?</h3>


<p>The shopping centre was originally to be redeveloped by Lend Lease under the <a href="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf">Regeneration Agreement</a> signed in 2010 with Southwark Council. St Modwens (KPI) was the owner of the shopping centre at that time. A year later it signed an agreement with Southwark Council and another, tripartite agreement with both Southwark and Lend Lease for the redevelopment of the centre<a href="#footnote-1">[1]</a>. These agreements have been kept confidential<a href="#footnote-2">[2]</a>. St Modwen then sold the site to Delancey &amp; funding partner APG in 2013. The question then, is what is the current contractual relationship between Southwark, Lend Lease and Delancey for the redevelopment of the shopping centre? It appears to be another instance where Southwark Council has several hats: development partner; public authority with CPO powers; author of enforcer of planning policy, and as former Heygate residents know it does not always resolve these competing roles in the best interests of local people.</p>

<h2>Save the Coronet</h2>


<p><img class="left" src="http://crackmagazine.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/Screen-shot-2013-12-03-at-14.55.50-660x403.png" width="300" height="200">The Coronet is taking no chances with its future, it has launched the <a href="http://coronettheatre.co.uk/home/save-the-coronet/">&lsquo;Save the Coronet&rsquo;</a> campaign and has gained impressive support from a long list of <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/SNSaveTheCoronet.pdf">distinguished artists</a> who have performed there. A sizeable part of the shopping centre site is occupied by the Coronet - a music and event venue, it has also been a cinema and music hall <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7701">dating back to 1872</a> and is a popular local institution.</p>

<h2>Trading Places</h2>


<p>Welcome to &lsquo;Social Life&rsquo; -a social enterprise based on the Pullens estate. Funded by the Young Foundation, their mission is <em>&ldquo;to reconnect placemaking with people&rsquo;s everyday experience and the way that communities work.&rdquo;</em> They have turned their attention to the Elephant &amp; Castle and the impact of the regeneration on local people. The say this: <em>&ldquo;we are carrying out an independent research project to understand how traders in the Elephant &amp; Castle Shopping Centre are being affected by the proposed regeneration. We want to understand how the proposed changes are affecting people now and how they will impact on traders and customers and their businesses, livelihoods, friendships and local relationships in the future. We want to understand more about the Shopping Centre’s social value.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>The results of the research which will be made available in a number of ways: a short report, which will be available on Social Life’s website; a local exhibition of stories and photographs; and a festival about social change being organised by the Social Innovation Exchange. The research findings will be available in September 2014. Further details can be found on <a href="http://www.social-life.co/blog/post/Trading_Places_Elephant_and_Castle_regen/">their website</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/snag-walk-july-2014-new.jpg"><img class="left" src="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/snag-walk-july-2014-new.jpg?w=500&h=669" width="300" height="150"></a>Last but not least, our friends at Southwark Notes are organising a <a href="http://southwarknotes.wordpress.com/2014/07/06/regeneration-rip-the-elephant-sat-19th-july-walk-sound-films/">day of excitement and interest</a> on Sat 19th July. The day begins with an anti-gentrification walk followed by &lsquo;Soundscape&rsquo; - <em>&ldquo;an immersive multimedia sound piece investigating community and gentrification&rdquo;</em> ending with the screening of 3 films including the much-awaited <a href="http://concreteheartland.info">&lsquo;Concrete Heartland&rsquo;</a> - a film <em>&ldquo;exposing the social cleansing of the Heygate Estate in Elephant and Castle.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><font size="1"><p id="footnote-1">[1] See para 2 of this <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/mgConvert2Pdf.aspx?ID=5663&amp;T=9">22 Nov 2011 Cabinet paper.</a></p></font>
<font size="1"><p id="footnote-2">[2] See para 4 of this <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/mgConvert2Pdf.aspx?ID=5663&amp;T=9">22 Nov 2011 Cabinet paper.</a>   </p></font></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury Estate - 42 More Residents Face Compulsory Purchase]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/06/30/aylesbury-estate-compulsory-purchase-order/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-30T16:17:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/06/30/aylesbury-estate-compulsory-purchase-order</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/gallery/2014/apr/15/china-nail-houses-in-pictures-property-development"><img class="left" src="http://static.guim.co.uk/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2014/4/13/1397410555601/baac3533-f9fe-4c47-994d-eeadf76d8ee1-620x461.jpeg" width="300" height="200"></a> In China homeowners who stand in the way of new developments can refuse compensation if they are prepared to stay put in <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/gallery/2014/apr/15/china-nail-houses-in-pictures-property-development">&lsquo;nail houses&rsquo;</a>. In Britain homeowners don&rsquo;t have that option - sooner or later they would have to accept whatever is offered, as the leaseholders on Southwark&rsquo;s Aylesbury estate are finding out.</p>

<p>Last week Southwark Council served a Compulsory Purchase Order on 22 leaseholders, 12 secure tenants and 8 non-secure tenants whose homes are to be demolished in the next phase of the Aylesbury redevelopment. We reported briefly last year on the <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/SNWolverton.pdf">elderly</a> residents <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/ObjectionCPOAugust2012.pdf">objecting</a> to the <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/WolvertonCPO.pdf">Compulsory Purchase</a> of their homes during the previous phase of the scheme and how they were subsequently <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/30/aylesbury-leaseholder-fights-incestuous-valuation/">forced into litigation</a> in order to obtain fair compensation for their homes.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/pictures/643xAny/2/6/5/18265_Regen_Aylesbury_032.jpg" width="300" height="200">The Council&rsquo;s justification for the CPO - its <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/AylesburyPhase3CPO.pdf">Statement of Reasons</a> for making the order is full of the usual arguments: &ldquo;the Aylesbury estate is amongst the most deprived areas in England&rdquo;; &ldquo;the built fabric is dated&rdquo;; &ldquo;it goes against good design principles&rdquo;; &ldquo;elements of its layout such as the raised walkways contribute to crime&rdquo;.
Many of these arguments can be contested, for example the 2005 Council-commissioned structural survey declared the buildings sound and Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200179/aylesbury_estate/2686/aylesbury_development_partnership/2">own admission</a> that the estate&rsquo;s crime rate is 45% below the borough average. Even if the Council&rsquo;s arguments are accepted it doesn&rsquo;t justify the Council&rsquo;s use of Compulsory Purchase powers against these residents.</p>

<p>One difference between this CPO and that of the Heygate is that it has been served not just on leaseholders but also on council tenants. The Heygate&rsquo;s 1,000 tenants were instead removed from the estate under the Landlord &amp; Tenant Act with the help of 198 Notices to Quit and 4 eventual evictions. Whatever the procedure used, the Council is obliged to make secure tenants an offer of alternative accommodation. Non-secure tenants aren&rsquo;t so lucky: under the Aylesbury CPO there is no guarantee of any offer at all.</p>

<p>Leaseholders will have to rely on their compensation to buy a new home in the area. We know from the two cases that recently went to the Lands Tribunal that this is woefully inadequate with offers of just £85k for a 1-bed and £165k for a 4-bed flat. While current leaseholders are being offered a pittance, 2-bed new-build flats in the <a href="http://www.burgessterrace.co.uk/">completed phase 1</a> Aylesbury development are being <a href="http://www.dropbox.com/s/v02kjcryf8ni15r/LandRegistryTitleTGL392009.pdf">sold for £490,000</a>.</p>

<p>It is difficult to understand this when Southwark should be getting plenty of money from the sale of 28.5 hectares of prime central London real estate. It got £20m for the sale of its nearby Manor Place development site to Notting Hill Housing (£11.8m per Hectare); on this comparison the Aylesbury site could be worth a staggering £330m.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.albany-place.co.uk/"><img class="left" src="http://www.ruskinwalk.co.uk/images/common/ruskin-walk-brochure.jpg"></a>Aylesbury leaseholders are being offered shared ownership options on the nearby Elmington estate regeneration, but this is on very unfavourable terms as shown by <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s45196/Representation%20from%20Aylesbury%20Leaseholders%20Action%20Group.pdf">submissions</a> from leaseholders to the Council&rsquo;s recent Overview and Scrutiny Committee meeting.</p>

<p>Aylesbury Leaseholders have formed themselves into an action group and have released <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/vjtwnow85uwfta0/AylesburyCPOPressStatement4July2014v3.pdf">this press statement</a> in their fight to get a fair deal. They have objected to the CPO and there is likely to be a public inquiry.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notting Hill No Social Housing Trust]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/06/16/notting-hill-housing-no-social-housing/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-16T19:17:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/06/16/notting-hill-housing-no-social-housing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://www.britishlistedbuildings.co.uk/images/buildings/en/471/471093-18941-800.jpg" width="300" height="200">One of the most characterful development sites within the the Elephant and Castle Opportunity Area is the <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/elephant-and-castle-home/elephant-and-castle-history/00,news,10016,5757,00.htm">Manor Place Baths</a>.  The baths provided laundry and bathing facilities to Walworth people for 80 years, until demolition of the surrounding streets and the removal of the local population to the Heygate and Ayelsbury estates sounded its death knell in the 80’s; it was replaced as a swimming pool by the Elephant &amp; Castle leisure centre, the baths were filled in by Southwark Council in 1998 and the buildings were then used by the Council&rsquo;s Environmental Services department until their relocation in 2012.</p>

<p>Notting Hill Housing Trust (NHHT) purchased the 1.7 hectare site from the Council in Nov 2013 for the reasonable sum of £20m - reasonable compared to the <a href="http://www.standard.co.uk/news/london/elephant-and-castle-estate-revamp-ripped-off-taxpayers-8482794.html">£50m figure</a> it sold the 9.9 Hectare Heygate site for. NHHT is now putting out feelers to local community groups in anticipation of a planning application before the end of the year.   The omens do not look good.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/manorplace.jpg"><img class="right" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/manorplace.jpg" width="370" height="240"></a> First, rather than deal directly with the local community NHTT have engaged M&amp;N Place to do the work for them.  M&amp;N Place is eminently qualified – it has an <a href="http://www.mnplace.co.uk/contact-us/">office in Abu Dhabi</a>, provides <a href="http://www.mnplace.co.uk/case-studies/pre-planning/">&lsquo;political intelligence&rsquo;</a> about local authorities and is well versed in bending local opinion to the developers will on behalf of London boroughs. M&amp;N Place is also eminently <a href="http://www.mnplace.co.uk/case-studies/pre-planning/kidbrooke-greenwich/">experienced</a> - having successfully bent opinion for Berkeley homes&#8217; <a href="http://halag.files.wordpress.com/2010/11/ferrier.pdf">deplorable redevelopment</a> of the Ferrier estate in Greenwich.</p>

<p>Undeterred, a concerned local resident attended the first <a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk/manor-place-banners.pdf">public exhibition</a> for the development. There was no information about affordable housing on display, but after probing NHHT staff it turns out there will be no social housing - we will be getting the dreaded affordable rent instead. They agreed this would be beyond the means of people on low or average incomes. <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/manorplacedepotconsultation.pdf">Here</a> is a link to his full report.</p>

<p>NHHT are shy about saying what exactly the rents will be, but below is a screenshot taken <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/customers/permanent-rented-housing/information-for-permanent-rented-housing-tenants/affordable-rent-update">from its website</a> which gives us some idea what to expect:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/nhhtrents.png"></p>

<h3>Housing contradictions</h3>


<p>Some housing associations have <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/affordable-rent-not-worth-the-risk-say-associations/6513502.article">complained</a> about the introduction of affordable rent, but NHHT is a true believer: as reported in Labour&rsquo;s <a href="http://redbrickblog.wordpress.com/2014/06/04/what-are-housing-associations-for-part-4/">redbrick blog</a> &lsquo;NHHT chief Kate Davies chaired the ‘Housing and Dependency Working Group’ of Iain Duncan Smith’s think tank the Centre for Social Justice. The name of the group almost says it all, but her conclusion is: ‘social housing is not a desirable destination; private ownership is preferable to state provided solutions’.</p>

<p>NHHT&rsquo;s hostility to social housing is evident in its <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/customers/permanent-rented-housing/information-for-permanent-rented-housing-tenants/affordable-rent-update">conversion policy</a> - social rented homes will be converted to affordable rent as soon as there is a change of tenant.</p>

<p>NHHT will be providing 1,200 of Southwark&rsquo;s new homes over the next three years in Camberwell, Peckham, Bermondsey &amp; Blackfriars plus the 3,500 new homes on the Aylesbury estate. In a <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/05/manx-connections-the-off-shore-home-of-the-elephants-developers">previous blog</a> we raised concerns about exactly what kind of affordable housing the Aylesbury estate would get. As the picture becomes clearer that concern deepens. Up to now Southwark has fought the very idea of introducing affordable rent to the borough, joining with seven other boroughs in <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1387/councils_to_take_mayor_of_london_to_court_over_affordable_rents">taking Boris Johnson to court</a>. Former head of regeneration Cllr Fiona Colley <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/fionacolleyresponsetolondonplan.pdf">summed up</a> the matter simply: <em>&lsquo;affordable rent will be very difficult for people in housing need to afford&rsquo;</em>. So why is NHHT - the champion of affordable rent - providing so many of Southwark&rsquo;s new homes?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
