<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[35% Campaign]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.35percent.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.35percent.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-20T09:23:45+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.35percent.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[EAN]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MIPIM, Southwark and Its 11000 New 'Private and Social' Council Homes]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/10/18/southwark-mipim-and-the-11000-new-council-homes/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-18T11:54:16+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/10/18/southwark-mipim-and-the-11000-new-council-homes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://static.guim.co.uk/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2014/10/15/1413393213631/Mipim-property-conference-011.jpg" width="300" height="200">The MIPIM Jamboree last week attracted much protest and media comment, including articles in the <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/oct/14/yacht-cannes-selling-homes-local-government-officials-mipim">Guardian</a> and on the <a href="http://leftfootforward.org/2014/10/the-mipim-property-fair-everything-wrong-with-regeneration/">Left Foot Forward</a> blog, which noted that <em>&ldquo;the Heygate Estate has become the paradigmatic example of the MIPIM-model of property development&rdquo;</em>.
</br></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.lbhf.gov.uk/Images/cllr-stephen-cowan-at-nipim_432_tcm21-191385.jpg" width="250" height="200">MIPIM itself revealed the contrasting attitudes of 3 London Labour boroughs towards developers:
Hammersmith &amp; Fulham <a href="http://www.lbhf.gov.uk/Directory/News/Homes_for_residents_not_overseas_investors.asp">used their stand</a> to make a strong case for development that provides <em>&ldquo;Homes for residents, not overseas investors&rdquo;</em>. It highlighted developers using <em>&ldquo;ridiculous viability assessments that offer piffling amounts of affordable homes&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Islington council leader Richard Watts said in <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/islington.pdf">his response</a> to <a href="http://www.unitetheunion.org/news/labour-councillors-urged-to-boycott-property-developers-fair-as-londons-housing-crisis-mounts/">Unite&rsquo;s call</a> for a boycott: <em>&ldquo;neither I nor anyone else from Islington council will be attending the event&rdquo;</em>. He explained that he was <em>&ldquo;deeply concerned at the lack of genuinely affordable housing in London .. and the increase in foreign investors who are pushing up housing prices to the detriment of our residents.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Southwark council leader Peter John&rsquo;s <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SouthwarkUniteResponse.pdf">response</a> took a different view. He said he would be unable to attend himself, but <em>&ldquo;does not agree with the request and the reasoning behind it&rdquo;</em> because the council needs to <em>&ldquo;continue working with the private sector to ensure that we can deliver as many homes as we can&rdquo;</em>. He concludes by reiterating his <em>&ldquo;commitment to build 11,000 new council homes at social rents.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>This commitment to build 11,000 new council homes has come under increasing scrutiny. Our <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/">previous blog post</a> and <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2014/oct/07/southwark-london-regeneration-urban-renewal-social-cleansing-fears">this recent Guardian article</a> show how questions are being asked about whether they will be council homes and whether existing council homes will have to be lost for there to be any gains. So it&rsquo;s not reassuring that Southwark&rsquo;s MIPIM stand display describes the 11,000 new council homes as comprising <em>&ldquo;both private and social&rdquo;</em> housing as this image below shows:<br/>
<a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/southwarkMIPIMstand.png"><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/southwarkMIPIMstand.png"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/MipimStevePlattsJonAbbott.JPG"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/MipimStevePlattsJonAbbott.JPG" width="300" height="200"></a> Heckling protesters spotted Southwark&rsquo;s Head of Property Steve Platts and Head of Regeneration Jon Abbott attending the fair. It&rsquo;s a day out of the office, but they looked a little downcast; no doubt disappointed that Southwark was <a href="http://blog.mipimworld.com/2014/10/announcing-winners-mipim-uk-estates-gazette-awards/">beaten</a> by Croydon and Lambeth to the awards of &lsquo;Best UK Planning Authority&rsquo; and &lsquo;Best Public/Private Partnership&rsquo;.</p>

<p>If you would like to enjoy the full MIPIM experience without the canapés and champagne, click on this <a href="http://www.inspiredlabs.com/mipimuk/?project=MIPIM/Mipim-Uk-2014/GroundR/main&amp;bubble=day&amp;yaw=0.09&amp;fov=65&amp;location=loc000&amp;pitch=0">interactive floorplan</a> of the property fair.</p>

<h3>Developers ride the bus</h3>

<p><a href="http://t.co/LZwNl9yC2T"><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/mipimbus.png" width="300" height="200"></a>We hope if you live in Southwark, you didn&rsquo;t see this bus driving down your street last week. It was full of MIPIM property developers making a quick trip from Earls Court, no doubt scoping out sites in the developer-friendly <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/11/southwark-gets-its-reward/">&lsquo;can do&rsquo;</a> borough of Southwark.
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>Evicting Aylesbury</h2>

<p><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/4/3941/14931046894_7eca1011dd_n.jpg" align="right">A High Court ruling <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/crime/judge-blasts-southwark-council-for-evicting-sudanese-tenant-and-destroying-his-possessions-9796994.html">condemning</a> Southwark officers for having conspired to evict a tenant from an estate in its North Peckham regeneration, is followed by news of a temporary tenant on the Aylesbury estate <a href="http://housingactionsouthwarkandlambeth.wordpress.com/2014/09/27/keeping-people-in-their-homes-a-southwark-council-guide-to-homelessness/">evicted</a> and left entirely homeless. HASL staged a protest in the Council&rsquo;s HQ on Thursday accompanied by the Focus E15 mums and the evictee; and refused to leave the lobby until the poor disabled woman was given a roof over her head. Southwark <a href="http://housingactionsouthwarkandlambeth.wordpress.com/2014/10/16/massive-housing-solidarity-southwark-council-ineptitude/">acquiesced</a> to the request and she was offered temporary accommodation (albeit with stairs..)</p>

<h3>Aylesbury estate SGTO meeting</h3>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SGTO25OctLeaflet4.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SGTOFlyer.png" width="200" height="350"></a>The disruptive impact of regenerations like the Heygate and the Aylesbury on people throughout Southwark has become more apparent day by day. It is not just that council tenants lose their homes, but that leaseholders get displaced and that housing and rehousing opportunities are lost for anyone on the council waiting list. The Southwark Group of Tenants Association has called a <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SGTO25OctLeaflet4.pdf">public meeting</a> about the future of the Aylesbury estate and the demolition of council homes. <a href="http://halag.wordpress.com/">Threatened Aylesbury leaseholders</a> will also be taking part in the meeting. In the meantime - 3 weeks since their submission - the Aylesbury planning applications have appeared on Southwark Council&rsquo;s planning portal (ref. numbers <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557152">14/AP/3843</a> and <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9557153">14/AP/3844</a>) but we can&rsquo;t tell whether the applications meet with affordable housing requirements because there are still no planning documents online. Last week we emailed the council&rsquo;s planning dept to ask about the delay and we have still had no reply.</p>

<h2>Heygate FOI/EIR Tribunal Case</h2>

<p>Parties to the Heygate FOI/EIR Tribunal case reconvened at a &lsquo;Case Management Hearing&rsquo; last week. The hearing was called by respondent to the case Adrian Glasspool, who had complained that disclosure of the viability assessment had still not taken place following the Tribunal&rsquo;s decison at the beginning of May. After hearing an account of progress so far, Southwark, Lend Lease and the Information Commissioner were directed to meet on 29th October to try to resolve any outstanding issues concerning the final disclosure. The judge also asked for parties&#8217; availability for a further hearing - should it be needed - in December.</p>

<p>Another <a href="http://discussion.theguardian.com/comment-permalink/42351530">challenge</a> against a developer&rsquo;s use of viability assessments in Stoke Newington can be added to the list of challenges in our <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/10/11/southwark-gets-its-reward/">previous blog post</a>. Again the developer is arguing that local people simply would not understand what it is all about, just as was the argument in the Heygate FOI/EIR Tribunal case. After 3 days of argument in the High Court, the judge has retired to consider his verdict.</p>

<h2>Lyons Review reviews viability</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/lyonsreview.png" width="200" height="75">Viability assessments are also rapidly rising up the political agenda: the <a href="http://www.yourbritain.org.uk/uploads/editor/files/The_Lyons_Housing_Review_2.pdf">Lyons Housing Review</a> commissioned by the Labour Party and published last week, has identified <em>&ldquo;substantial concerns about the way in which the viability of local plans, CIL charging schedules and sites are tested. Evidence to the review suggested that this is compounded by the fact that there is no agreed methodology for viability assessment, which allows different parties to pick the methodology most to their advantage .. evidence to the review suggested that the current arrangements create a great deal of uncertainty and complexity, which works in favour of the partner with the most skilled consultants acting for it.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>The report then makes some suggestions for how the viability testing process can be improved:</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Definitive guidance should be produced to ensure a single and robust methodology for viability assessments to reduce the scope for different interpretations of viability and reduce uncertainty.&rdquo;</em> It argues that an <em>&ldquo;&lsquo;open-book&rsquo; approach to negotiating site specific viability is required, to increase transparency and speed of negotiations.&rdquo;</em> It also proposes <em>&ldquo;an arbitration service for S106 on large scale developments to be funded by the parties involved in the negotiation&rdquo;</em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Southwark Gets Its Reward]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/10/11/southwark-gets-its-reward/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-11T13:06:21+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/10/11/southwark-gets-its-reward</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.mipimuk-awards.co.uk/mipimukawards2014/shortlist"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/MipimAwards.jpg" width="350" height="230"></a>Southwark prides itself on being a &lsquo;developer friendly&rsquo; borough. It has been <a href="http://vimeo.com/71882474#t=125s">endorsed</a> by Lend Lease Director Rob Deck as a <strong>&lsquo;can do&rsquo;</strong> council and it has been <a href="http://www.mipimuk-awards.co.uk/mipimukawards2014/shortlist">shortlisted</a> (by developers) for the award of <strong>&lsquo;Best UK Planning Authority&rsquo;</strong> at next week&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.mipimuk.co.uk/"><strong>MIPIM</strong> jamboree</a>. But pressure is mounting on all councils including Southwark to withdraw from the MIPIM backscratching get-together. Over two dozen community groups, charities and trade unions have <a href="http://radicalhousingnetwork.org/mipim-uk/whos-opposing-mipim/">opposed MIPIM</a>. Unite, Britains largest union has <a href="http://www.unitetheunion.org/news/labour-councillors-urged-to-boycott-property-developers-fair-as-londons-housing-crisis-mounts/">written</a> to all of London&rsquo;s Labour-controlled councils  asking them to <em>&ldquo;withdraw from participation in MIPIM and the close relationships with private developers that the event seeks to foster.&rdquo;</em>; three have done so but not Southwark.</p>

<p><a href="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BzdVDNBCAAMCUu0.png"><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BzdVDNBCAAMCUu0.png" width="350" height="230"></a>So it is a particulary embarrasing moment for Lend Lease to <a href="http://www.asx.com.au/asxpdf/20141009/pdf/42ss0tfmnqrw92.pdf">announce</a> on the Sydney Stock Exchange pre-sales totalling £312m (AUD$ 570m) from just 20% of the 3,000 homes it is building at the Elephant &amp; Castle. As we detailed in our <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/09/20/setting-the-record-straight/">previous blog</a>, Southwark is going to have to wait 11 years before it gets a sniff of any profit from the Heygate and so far Southwark has received just £15m of its £50m Heygate land receipt while having spent over £65m emptying and demolishing the estate.</p>

<h2>Developers behaving badly</h2>

<p>Some good examples of bad behaviour by developers using viability assessments to avoid building affordable housing are beginning to emerge.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/neobanksidecomparison.jpg" width="400" height="300">In Southwark, properties in the Neo Bankside development, opposite Tate Modern, were  <a href="http://www.colliers.com/~/media/Files/EMEA/UK/research/residential/201202-central-london-residential-market.pdf">reported</a> to be selling for an average of <strong>£1,326 per square foot</strong> in 2012, nearly double that claimed by developer <strong>Grosvenor</strong> when planning permission was granted: <strong>Grosvenor</strong>&rsquo;s <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6014_1.pdf">viability assessment</a> claimed its residential properties would sell for an average of just <strong>£754 per square foot</strong><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. These figures also take no account of the <a href="http://online.wsj.com/articles/europe-house-of-the-day-luxury-penthouse-on-the-bank-of-the-thames-photos-1412674116">unsold penthouses</a>, which are <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7512">currently on the market</a> for £22m (each).</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/NEOBanksidePenthouse.jpg" width="300" height="200">Southwark Council didn&rsquo;t refer the Neo Bankside viability assessment to the <a href="http://www.voa.gov.uk/DVS/index.html">District Valuer</a> or other independent expert for appraisal, but had its Internal Property Division look it over instead<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Its Property team recommended that the council accept the developer&rsquo;s poverty plea and settle for a <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/5356">conciliatory offer of a £9m in-lieu payment</a>. Based on Southwark&rsquo;s in-lieu affordable housing tariff <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> this was a whopping gain to the developer of £16.2m.
The absence of any review or reappraisal mechanism in the planning approval, means that there is no chance that Southwark - or anyone in Southwark who needs affordable housing - will benefit from the properties being sold for twice the developer&rsquo;s original estimate.</p>

<p>Developer <strong>Grosvenor</strong>&rsquo;s viability assessment can currently be <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6014_1.pdf">viewed</a> on the council&rsquo;s planning portal. We presume this was a mistake by Southwark, so in the event that it gets removed we have uploaded a backup copy which can be viewed online <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6014_1.pdf">here</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SKMBT_DVSReport.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/DVSReport.png" width="200" height="350"></a>In Kensington &amp; Chelsea, the <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SKMBT_DVSReport.pdf">District Valuer&rsquo;s report</a> evaluating the developer&rsquo;s viability assessment for the Earl&rsquo;s Court regeneration was <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/development/earls-court-developer-ignored-house-price-rises/7005985.article">finally disclosed</a> thanks to the efforts of local campaigners. The report was highly critical, stating that the developer&rsquo;s assessment <em>&ldquo;ignores residential growth in values that occurs between construction start on site and the commencement of marketing and phased release of the dwellings&rdquo;</em>. The report concluded by recommending that the council implement a <em>‘review mechanism’</em> so that it could increase the level of affordable housing in line with changing market conditions throughout the 22 year scheme. Unfortunately, no such review mechanism was put in place.</p>

<p>In Fitzrovia, developer <strong>TMCT Associates</strong> has adopted a different tack: instead of underestimating sales values it has inflated build costs in its application for an office to residential conversion at Eastgate House, just around the corner from Tottenham Court Rd. As is usually the case here and elsewhere, Westminster planning committee were initially denied access to the viability assessment, but councillors have now demanded to see it. <a href="http://fitzrovia.org.uk/">Fitzrovia Neighbourhood Association</a> has got there first, and it has published <a href="http://news.fitzrovia.org.uk/2014/10/09/affordable-housing-viability-and-profit/">an account</a> of what it found in its newspaper Fitzrovia News. The Developer has estimated that it will cost a staggering £1.2m <strong>per flat</strong> to convert from offices to residential.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://ystudio.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/gp2.jpg" width="300" height="200">Over in the huge <a href="http://knightdragon.com/greenwich-peninsula/current">Greenwich Peninsula regeneration</a> of 10,000 homes, Hong Kong developer <a href="http://knightdragon.com/"><strong>Knight Dragon</strong></a> has secured a reduction in the amount of affordable housing from 38% to 21%. Local campaigners City Peninsula Residents Association are fighting back and are due to appear at an Information Tribunal hearing in January in their efforts to reveal the viability assessment, which justifies the loss of around 1,700 affordable homes. The use of viability assessments in Greenwich <a href="http://www.thisislocallondon.co.uk/news/11500983._Pushing_poor_people_out____Greenwich_accused_of_affordable_housing_failure/">appears to be rampant</a>: none of the approved major developments over the last 12 months meets Greenwich&rsquo;s minimum requirement for 35% affordable housing.</p>

<h2>The benefit of review mechanisms</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BprjPdsCQAEG0ze.png" width="300" height="200">A recurring feature of planning approvals involving viability assessments is the absence of any review mechanism. This means that any uplift in London property prices between the approval of planning and sale of new homes will not be reflected in an increased affordable housing offer. This will be the case on the Heygate estate, where Southwark failed to follow the District Valuer&rsquo;s recommendation that a <em>&lsquo;review mechanism linked with delivery&rsquo;</em> should be made a condition of planning approval<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>. The 37% increase in Southwark&rsquo;s property prices since The Heygate planning application was submitted, will therefore be translated directly into developer profit; the £101m worth of affordable housing that Lend Lease said it couldn&rsquo;t afford to provide remains permanently written off. The Heygate development is not due to be completed until 2025. Any further increase in London property prices over the next 11 years will be converted into Lend Lease profit; the measly affordable housing offer of 79 social rented units out of 2,735 new homes will remain unchanged.</p>

<p>Review/re-appraisal mechanisms for viability assessments don&rsquo;t just make good sense: as well as being in Southwark&rsquo;s case a policy requirement<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>, they are recommended in the official RICS guidance on viability testing<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Some other councils are starting to wake up to the problem of the misuse of viability assessments: Inside Housing <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/islingtons-planning-backlash-at-developer-super-profits/7005936.article">reported</a> that Islington Council plans to <em>&ldquo;clamp down on ‘artificially pessimistic’ viability studies used by developers to minimise affordable housing obligations.&rdquo;</em> Islington Council said it comes after it had <em>&ldquo;received a ‘significant number’ of viability studies that do not provide underlying methodology and modelling. These studies are ‘unsupported by robust evidence’ and create ‘an artificially pessimistic outcome’.&rdquo;</em></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See page 11 of the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6014_1.pdf">viability assessment</a> submitted by the developer and which is currently published (we presume mistakably) on the council&rsquo;s planning portal.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See paragraph 46 of the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/159669_1.pdf">Officer&rsquo;s report.</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://35percent.org/images/affordablehousingspg.pdf">planning policy</a> requires all developments in the North of the borough without on-site affordable housing to pay a minimum of £100,000 per habitable room in lieu of each affordable housing unit not provided (i.e. 35% of the total number of habitable rooms which in this case is <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/6006_1.pdf">720 habitable rooms</a> = 252 x £100k = £25.2m). Indeed, developments on the riverside should provide more and are determined on a &lsquo;case-by-case&rsquo; basis. <a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>See LBS_WS_SB paragraph 92.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>See paragraph 7.3.4 of Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/6069/draft_affordable_housing_spd_2011">Affordable Housing SPD</a><a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>See paragraph 3.6.4 of RICS Guidance <a href="http://www.pas.gov.uk/c/document_library/get_file?uuid=2c5c4f63-5010-4839-83f9-4955cf09e0a9&amp;groupId=332612">Financial Viability in Planning 2012</a><a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let's Talk About... Peter's Promises]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-04T15:21:48+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/10/04/lets-talk-about-peters-promises</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SNHeygateOverage.pdf"><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/SN1100homes.png" width="400" align="right"></a>Southwark Council leader Peter John has pledged that the 11,000 new council homes to be built over the next 30 years will not entail the demolition of the same number of existing council homes. In an <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10997/an_open_letter_from_cllr_peter_john_leader_of_southwark_council">open letter</a> to all residents Cllr John says;</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;To be absolutely clear, the 11,000 new homes that we promise to deliver will be new homes additional to our existing stock. These will be council homes on council rents for those that need them. It has been said that what we are intending to do is demolish 11,000 existing council homes and replace them to reach our target of 11,000. This is just not true. These are new homes and do not include the existing stock of council housing.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200463/community_conversations/2923/lets_talk_about_new_council_homes_for_southwark"><img src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/communityconversation.png" width="300" height="200" align="left"></a>This emphatic promise has been prompted by residents’ concern about some of the questions Southwark are asking in their <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200463/community_conversations/2923/lets_talk_about_new_council_homes_for_southwark">resident survey</a> entitled <strong>‘Let’s talk about&hellip;new council homes for Southwark’</strong>. The survey seeks resident approval of a Charter of Principals for how the Council <em>‘will work with residents on our programme of investment and renewal’</em>. The <a href="http://www.sgto.org.uk/">Southwark Group of Tenants Association</a>&rsquo;s newsletter (issue 15) says that the survey <em>‘seems to confuse the building of 11,000 homes with the ‘renewal’ or ‘redevelopment’ of estates’</em>. Southwark Defend Council Housing puts it stronger - <em>‘Southwark Council threatens massive redevelopment of its housing estates in Camberwell &amp; Peckham’</em>, and links the questions to Southwark’s new CIL <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/07/23/mystery-objector-1301/"><em>‘Estate Renewal Zone&#8217;</em></a>.</p>

<h3>..the price tag</h3>

<p><img src="http://35percent.org/images/CILChargingZones.png" width="200" align ="right">All agree that building 11,000 council homes is a good promise and is off to a good start<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, but the promise now looks as if it has a price attached, a price which the resident survey is very artfully concealing. The survey talks of ‘principles’ and ‘pledges’ but makes no mention of the asset appraisal study of council stock that will determine which estates are chosen for redevelopment, nor the part the survey itself will play in making those choices. The asset appraisal study is due to be completed by December and is described in a recent council <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">cabinet report - ‘Next steps on Developing Long Term Plans for the Delivery of New Council Homes’</a>. The report says that the council must <em>‘identify as much potential land as possible for development opportunity’</em><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. This requires <em>‘a detailed and comprehensive appraisal be undertaken of the performance of the Housing Revenue Account (HRA) assets’</em><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> (ie council homes), leading to <em>‘an assessment of their worth to the housing business’</em><sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>.</p>

<h3>..the <strong>Asset Performance Evaluation Tool</strong></h3>

<p>Establishing the financial ‘worth’ of each council home does not end the process. Southwark will also look at ‘non-financial’ factors – income, employment, health, education and social exclusion – to see which stock <em>‘prevents the council effectively meeting its social housing objectives’</em><sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>. An <em>&lsquo;Asset Performance Evaluation Tool&rsquo;</em>, which includes <em>‘a measure of social return based on feedback from engagement with residents’</em><sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>, will ‘enable’ the council to reach its decisions.</p>

<p>Finally Southwark will make <em>‘a correlation of these results with open market values and development potential across the stock will identify candidate groups of assets where more detailed options appraisal could result in either opportunities for additional homes or improvements in values to the overall HRA business plan, increasing the surpluses that may be available to subsidise new developments.’</em><sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" rel="footnote">7</a></sup></p>

<p>Putting all this into plain English, Southwark will put a financial value on each of its estates, take a look at the lifestyles of its tenants and residents and estimate how much the land is worth to developers. The ‘options’ will then open up, including sell-offs (aka ‘improvements in value to the overall HRA business plan’). Putting it even more simply, it looks like Southwark will;</p>

<ul>
<li>see how much each council estate is worth&hellip;</li>
<li>see which ones it doesn’t like&hellip;.</li>
<li>see which ones it wants to ‘redevelop’&hellip;.</li>
</ul>


<p>This all paints a rather alarming picture, particularly in light of the Heygate experience where an <a href="http://betterelephant.org/blog/2012/12/23/1998-southwark-housing-stock-survey/">options appraisal study</a> which recommended retaining half the estate&rsquo;s buildings was ignored. The 35% campaign has requested a copy of the <strong>&lsquo;Asset Performance Evaluation Tool&rsquo;</strong> given the key part it looks like playing in the future of every Southwark council estate resident.</p>

<h2>Aylesbury - Stop Press</h2>

<p>The long-anticipated outline planning application and phase 1b/1c demolition applications have been submitted to Southwark Council. Residents in the first phase have received <a href="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/scan0027.pdf">this letter</a> from agents acting on behalf of Notting Hill Housing Trust and Barratt. However, despite having been submitted on 25th September, there are no planning documents online yet. All we know at the moment is that the outline application is for 2,745 new &lsquo;private and affordable units&rsquo; including 1,070 parking spaces plus retail, office &amp; community space. The detailed application proposals include 815 new homes, new roads and some <em>&lsquo;public and private open space&rsquo;</em>.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Phases 1 &amp; 2 of the programme will deliver 447 social rented homes out of 669 total units by early 2016. <a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>See para. 41 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>See para. 50 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>See para. 50 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>See para. 51 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>See para. 55 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:7">
<p>See para. 53 of <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s47488/Report%20Long%20term%20plans%20for%20the%20delivery%20of%20new%20council%20homes.pdf">Cabinet report</a><a href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elephant Traders - Not in the Pink]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/09/27/penrose-street-sorting-office/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-27T09:31:46+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/09/27/penrose-street-sorting-office</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://tradingplaces-elephant.tumblr.com/"><img class="right" src="http://33.media.tumblr.com/eb768bd9c749502c3d8926ced246593f/tumblr_nbcjwdMLuv1tklzg2o1_1280.jpg" width="200" height="300"></a>We <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/07/12/the-more-rent-seeking-elephants-at-elephant-the-better/">blogged</a> on 12th July about <a href="http://www.social-life.co/blog/post/Trading_Places_Elephant_and_Castle_regen/"><em>Social Life</em></a>, a social enterprise based on the Pullens estate. They have now completed their research on the Elephant &amp; Castle shopping centre redevelopment and how it is affecting the traders there. A concise and impressive report is now available <a href="http://tradingplaces-elephant.tumblr.com/">here</a>. Its conclusions will not surprise people familiar with the shopping centre. It says: <em>&ldquo;Overall, traders are anxious and concerned about the redvelopment. Many of the traders have mixed feelings about the plans.&rdquo;</em>;<em>&ldquo;The shopping centre is an important social space for traders, local people and regular customers and it plays a hugely important role in the social life of the local community.&rdquo;</em>;<em>&ldquo;The shopping centre supports dense networks of social relationships in the local area, across London and globally.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>We hope developers Delancey have read this report and are giving it full weight in their forthcoming planning application for the shopping centre&rsquo;s redevelopment. However, we hear from several sources that they are not treating the current occupants very well: rents are being raised and new rental agreements are in the form of licences rather than leases, which points towards them getting rid of shopkeepers rather than keeping them. An <a href="http://www.theprisma.co.uk/2014/09/21/how-changes-in-elephant-castle-will-affect-the-latino-community/">interview</a> with respected academic and Director of <a href="http://latinelephant.wordpress.com/">Latin Elephant</a> Patria Roman paints a similar picture. Nevertheless, one shopping centre leaseholder and popular venue for Latin American events appears to be fighting back - the <a href="https://www.change.org/p/southwark-council-save-the-coronet">&lsquo;Save the Coronet&rsquo; petition</a> now stands at 3,856 signatures.</p>

<h2>Sorting Office sorted?</h2>


<p><img class="left" src="http://walworthsociety.co.uk/images/Copy%20of%20image%20001%20-%20resized.jpg" width="300" height="150">Two contentious planning applications are pending just down the road from the Elephant in Walworth. One of these would see the effective demolition of a local heritage asset - the former sorting office on Penrose street, the other could jeopardise the future of much loved and valued local mental health charity <em>Cooltan Arts</em>.</p>

<p>The Sorting Office was built in 1897 and the Walworth Society has long been <a href="http://walworthsociety.co.uk/index.php/blog/116-31-penrose-street-walworths-victorian-sorting-office">campaigning</a> to have it retained as part of the extensive redevelopment of the area. A previous planning application was refused after a large number of objections to its demolition. Its owner is now back with <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeDocs&amp;TheSystemkey=9554889">another application</a> which looks like a prime example of &lsquo;facadism&rsquo;: an increasingly common practice which has been <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/architecture-design-blog/2014/aug/25/front-facade-bad-developments-ruining-historic-buildings">described</a> in the development industry as a <em>&ldquo;wilful two fingers up&rdquo;</em> to local planners.</p>

<p>The application is for 6 x 3 storey and 2 x 2 storey town houses, 8 being just below Southwark&rsquo;s threshold for an affordable housing contribution. They will be squeezed behind the retained facade and side wall, but require the demolition of the rest of the sorting office and surrounding outbuildings.</p>

<h2>Cooltan Arts - threat</h2>


<p><img class="right" src="http://www.cooltanarts.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/DSCF4054-lr.jpg" width="300" height="200">Cooltan Arts, long term residents of the Walworth road were relocated last year on the <a href="http://www.cooltanarts.org.uk/2013/10/cooltan-arts-community-space-for-237-walworth-road/">promise</a> that they would be able to return to redveloped premises on their former site off the Walworth road. But a revised planning application for the site no longer contains this promise to reprovide space for Cooltan (nor does it contain the amount of affordable housing required by policy). Objections to the application <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/AcolNetCGI.exe?ACTION=UNWRAP&amp;RIPNAME=Root.PgeResultDetail&amp;TheSystemkey=9553921">ref:(14/AP/0830)</a> can still be sent to <a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#x74;&#111;&#x3a;&#x70;&#x6c;&#x61;&#110;&#x6e;&#105;&#x6e;&#103;&#46;&#97;&#112;&#x70;&#x6c;&#x69;&#99;&#97;&#116;&#105;&#111;&#x6e;&#115;&#64;&#x73;&#x6f;&#117;&#116;&#104;&#x77;&#x61;&#114;&#107;&#46;&#x67;&#x6f;&#118;&#x2e;&#117;&#107;&#x2e;">&#112;&#108;&#x61;&#x6e;&#x6e;&#105;&#110;&#x67;&#46;&#97;&#x70;&#x70;&#108;&#105;&#x63;&#97;&#116;&#x69;&#111;&#x6e;&#115;&#64;&#115;&#111;&#x75;&#x74;&#104;&#119;&#x61;&#114;&#x6b;&#x2e;&#103;&#x6f;&#x76;&#x2e;&#x75;&#x6b;&#x2e;</a></p>

<h2>Developers award Southwark top marks</h2>


<p>Southwark Council has been <a href="http://www.mipimuk-awards.co.uk/mipimukawards2014/shortlist">shortlisted</a> for two awards at the latest property developers&#8217; jamboree <strong>&lsquo;MIPIM UK&rsquo;</strong>, due to be held at Kensington Olympia on 15th-17th October. Southwark is in the running to be both <em>&ldquo;UK best planning authority of the year&rdquo;</em> and <em>&ldquo;Public-Private Partnership of the Year&rdquo;</em> for the Aylesbury estate. The MIPIM awards <a href="http://www.mipimuk-awards.co.uk/mipimukawards2014/shortlist">web page</a> claims that for developers, Southwark is both <em>&ldquo;welcoming and demanding&rdquo;</em>. We agree that it is certainly welcoming but as we have shown, it is not so demanding - especially when it comes to enforcing its own minimum policies on affordable housing contributions.</p>

<p>MIPIM also states in the citation for the Aylesbury partnership award that 75% of its affordable housing will be social rented. We doubt very much that all the new social rented homes will be at social rents and suspect that the forthcoming Aylesbury outline planning application will replace at least some of it with the new so-called &lsquo;affordable rents&#8217;of up to 80% market rent.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/09/peter-j-mipim.jpg?w=500&h=409" width="375" height="375">MIPIM itself is usually held in sunny <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/6687">Cannes</a>. In 2013 the Council leader was <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/SNCannesMipim.pdf">accused</a> of <em>&lsquo;going on a jolly&rsquo;</em> to the event paid for by developer Lend Lease and last year he <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7449">withdrew</a> after protests and demonstrations. This year it is proving equally controversial: several Councils have pulled out after media pressure and an <a href="http://southwarknotes.wordpress.com/2014/09/21/open-letter-to-southwark-council-to-not-attend-mipim/">open letter</a> signed by several local campaign groups asks Southwark to join them. So far Council leader Peter John is unimpressed.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://radicalhousingnetwork.org/">Radical Housing Network</a> is organising protests during the exhibiton on 15th - 17th October.</p>

<h2>Heygate viability assessment latest</h2>


<p>After a long appeal against the Information Commisioner&rsquo;s decision, the Information Tribunal ordered Southwark Council and Lend Lease to disclose the Heygate viability assessment back in May. The Tribunal extended the time for forwarding the assessment to the Information Commissioner back in June, but the assessment has still not been revealed. After inquiries to the Tribunal by Mr Glasspool who requested the information, a case management hearing has now been scheduled for 15th October.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting the Record Straight]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/09/20/setting-the-record-straight/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-20T13:15:14+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/09/20/setting-the-record-straight</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Southwark Council has had its feathers ruffled by both the Guardian and the BBC lately. A <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2014/sep/17/truth-property-developers-builders-exploit-planning-cities">Guardian article</a> by Oliver Wainright uses the redevelopment of the Heygate estate as an example of how developers are <em>&lsquo;exploiting planning authorities and ruining our cities&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Southwark Council has posted a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1785/setting_the_record_straight_the_true_value_of_the_elephant_and_castle_regeneration">press statement</a> <strong>&lsquo;setting the record straight&rsquo;</strong>, in which it claims it will receive <em>&ldquo;phased payments as the scheme progresses&rdquo;</em> and this will amount to <em>&ldquo;hundreds of millions&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf"><img class="center" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/HeygateLandReceipts.png"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf"><img class="right" src="http://crappistmartin.github.io/images/rapage70.png" width="400" height="620"></a>It is true that there will be phased payments amounting to £50m (£46m for the main site + £4m for the Rodney road site) - this figure is now well known from the leaked <a href="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf">Regeneration Agreement</a>, but getting the <em>&ldquo;hundreds of millions&rdquo;</em> of pounds depends upon the so-called &lsquo;overage&rsquo; or &lsquo;super-profit&rsquo; and how much this will be, if anything, won&rsquo;t be known until the project is completed in 2025.</p>

<p>The overage will be what is left over after building costs, a 2.6% management fee and 20% priority developer return is deducted from the total sales revenue and it will be calculated according to Lend Lease&rsquo;s financial model, as detailed in a 3000 page spreadsheet known as Appendix 22 of the Heygate viability assessment. This complicated accounting process is entirely under Lend Lease&rsquo;s control and while the Council has the right to inspect the financial model, this may not guarantee the expected overage windfall as the Barangaroo Delivery Authority in Sydney Australia <a href="http://www.smh.com.au/nsw/barangaroo-public-works-in-doubt-after-government-loses-court-battle-with-lend-lease-20140821-106lke.html">is finding out</a> to its cost.</p>

<p>Any reckoning of the gain due to Southwark must also take into account the £65m<a href="#footnote-1">[1]</a> it has spent on Heygate decant costs plus an unquantified amount of public money devoted to regeneration since the wider E&amp;C scheme was conceived, starting with the £25m Single Regeneration Budget (SRB) funding received back in 1999.</p>

<p>On top of the Guardian’s Heygate story the BBC has taken up the plight of Aylesbury leaseholders being &lsquo;forced out of the city&rsquo;, with an <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-london-29098960">online article</a> and televised reports on both its London News and <a href="http://youtu.be/RtvghCKNJjQ">Inside Out programme</a> on 8th Sep. Inside Out did not think much of the paltry amount of compensation leaseholders on the Aylesbury estate were being offered, particularly in comparison to the £340k cost of one-bed properties in the area and described the situation as <em>&lsquo;the Right to Buy dream turned sour&rsquo;</em>.</p>

<center>
<iframe width="350" height="197" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/RtvghCKNJjQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</center>


<p>Southwark again &lsquo;sets the record straight&rsquo; and <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1767/southwark_councils_full_response_to_bbc_inside_out_programme">insists</a> that offers such as <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/05/16/southwark-gives-green-light-to-slum-landlords/">£85k for a 1-bed flat</a> are based on <em>&ldquo;actual market evidence of properties being sold on the Aylesbury estate&rdquo;</em>. This method of basing valuations on the sales prices of other properties depressed by the prospect of demolition has been <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/05/30/aylesbury-leaseholder-fights-incestuous-valuation/">criticised</a> by the Lands Tribunal. Southwark Council&rsquo;s valuers are also pretty imaginative in the way they gather &lsquo;market evidence&rsquo;, using a <a href="http://35percent.org/blog/2014/05/16/southwark-gives-green-light-to-slum-landlords/">1-bed property which had been illegally converted</a> to 4 beds flat as the basis of the compensation for one unfortunate leaseholder.  The derisory compensation offered to Aylesbury leaseholders is in stark contrast to the abundant profit that the builder of the Aylesbury redevelopment Barratt has just <a href="http://www.thisismoney.co.uk/money/markets/article-2750592/Booming-UK-housing-market-fuels-doubling-annual-profits-Barratt.html">announced</a>.</p>

<p>The Guardian and BBC stories reflect a wide-spread public view that developers and housebuilders are making big profits at local people’s expense and taking Southwark for a ride (an <a href="https://www.change.org/p/heygate-estate-scandal-demand-an-investigation">online petition</a> demanding an investigation into the Heygate development has gained over 700 signatures in 3 days) and a couple of press releases from Southwark won’t change this view.</p>

<p><font size="2"><p id="footnote-1">[1] See paragraphs 5.34 &amp; 5.35 of the Project Director&rsquo;s Jan 2013 <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/8171/proofs_of_evidence_%E2%80%93_jon_abbot_%E2%80%93_final_proof">CPO public inquiry evidence.</a> </p></font></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notting Hill Housing Trust - Quids in With Boris]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/08/19/notting-hill-housing-trust-quids-in-with-boris/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-19T17:53:38+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/08/19/notting-hill-housing-trust-quids-in-with-boris</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Notting Hill Housing Trust is an important provider of housing in Southwark, both &lsquo;affordable&rsquo; and <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/00,news,26531,440,00.htm">private</a>. It has plans to build more than 4000 homes in Southwark; 3500 of these will be on the Aylesbury estate, which it is redeveloping <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/about-us/building-new-homes/our-developments/aylesbury-estate-southwark">in partnership</a> with Britain&rsquo;s largest - and the mayor&rsquo;s favourite - housebuilder Barratt Homes. According to the NHHT <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/asset/view/6912.pdf">website</a>, a hybrid application comprising outline planning for the whole Aylesbury and detailed planning for the first phase is due to be submitted by the NHHT/Barratt consortium next month.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/development/greater-london-authority-allocates-404m-for-affordable-homes/7004790.article"><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/nottinghillfunding.png" width="400" height="300"></a>Notting Hill has secured more money than any other housing association from the Mayor&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.london.gov.uk/priorities/housing-land/increasing-housing-supply/affordable-homes-programme">affordable housing fund</a> (£59m - nearly three times the amount of the next highest provider). However, it is <a href="http://www.cih.org/news-article/display/vpathDCR/templatedata/cih/news-article/data/Losing_social_homes_means_we_are_storing_up_trouble">well known</a> that a condition of getting money from this funding stream is that only affordable rented homes can be built - not social rented. This was <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk//7005104.article">cited</a> by London Labour housing spokesperson Tom Copley as the reason why so few housing associations had applied for the funding, of which £380m still remains unallocated.</p>

<p>Notting Hill Housing Trust enthusiastically <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/06/16/notting-hill-housing-no-social-housing">endorses</a> the Mayor&rsquo;s affordable rent policies, which may explain why Boris Johnson is so happy to give it so much money.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://35percent.org/images/SouthwarkMarketRents.png">Aylesbury estate tenants will have the right to a tenancy in the new Notting Hill development and those already &lsquo;decanted&rsquo; to other parts of the borough will have the right to return, but if the affordable rents are 80% of market rent this won&rsquo;t mean very much. Southwark Council&rsquo;s recently published &lsquo;Affordable Rent Product Study&rsquo; gives £289pw as the market rent of a 1-bed flat in SE17 – 80% of this would be £231pw.  A council rent for a 1-bed flat in SE17 is currently around £100pw.</p>

<p>Southwark Council has repeatedly said in public that there would be 50% affordable housing on the new Aylesbury, of which 75% would be social rented and this was written into its <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200211/area_action_plans/1327/aylesbury_area_action_plan">planning policy for the scheme</a>. Notting Hill Housing Trust now says that social rent is the same as affordable rent and probably thinks that people are too stupid to tell the difference.</p>

<p>We think that any Aylesbury tenant moving into one of the replacement homes should not be expected to pay much more than their current council rent. If Southwark doesn&rsquo;t want to see another Heygate-style diaspora of long-standing communities then it should hold good on its promises, stick to its policies and ensure that policy definitions are not allowed to be blurred.</p>

<h2>Notting Hill Housing Trust - Manor Place Depot</h2>


<p><img class="left" src="http://35percent.org/images/manorplace.jpg" width="300" height="200">We <a href="http://affordable.heroku.com/blog/2014/06/16/notting-hill-housing-no-social-housing/">blogged</a> in June about the prospect of no social housing in Notting Hill Housing&rsquo;s Manor Place Depot development. Since then NHHT appears to have had a change of heart.</p>

<p>One of our members visited NHHT&rsquo;s second exhibition for its Manor Place Depot development and reported back as follows:</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;The exhibition gave no figures for the housing , simply saying some of the housing would be affordable rent, of which social rent was as a subset.  However discussions with NHHT staff yielded the following information:</em></p>

<p><em>The 35% target for affordable housing would be met, with 95 units out of the 270 proposed.  Of these 95 units, 50% will be affordable rent and 50% shared ownership.  NHHT defines affordable rent as including social rent, and there will be some social rent though they don&rsquo;t know how much until the viability assessment.  NHHT policy, they say, is for all the family units to be at social rent.</em></p>

<p><em>Since the first exhibition, NHHT has received GLA funds for all of its sites.  This contributes £30,000 - £40,000 of the cost per unit, they say.  NHHG were unwilling to provide information as to what exact tenure mix this public funding will subsidise, and how it differs per site.</em></p>

<p><em>On affordable market rent, NHHT say they don&rsquo;t go anywhere near 80% market rent and have a cap in London of £230 (i.e. this is the maximum affordable market rent they will charge, they say).</em></p>

<p><em>They said that there will be a further exhibition in September/October ahead of the planning application in November/December.&ldquo;</em></p>

<h4>We say:</h4>


<p>Social rented housing and affordable rented housing are not one and the same thing, Notting Hill Housing Trust needs to stop muddying the waters. If it wants to start consulting meaningfully with local people it must tell them exactly how much social rented housing there will be and how much affordable rented housing there will be and exactly how much rent they will be charging for each.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mind the (Elephantine) Gap]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/08/12/mind-the-gap/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-12T18:09:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/08/12/mind-the-gap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A £64m funding gap for the infrastructure improvements of the Elephant &amp; Castle regeneration has been identified by Southwark Council. The figure is given in its <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10740/addendum_to_cdeip1">submission</a> to the Government inspector examining Southwark&rsquo;s plans for raising funds from developers through the new Community Infrastructure Levy.</p>

<p><img src="http://affordable.herokuapp.com/images/fundinggap.png"></p>

<p>The hoped-for improvements include a new northern line ticket hall, better access to the mainline station, a remodelled northern roundabout, new leisure centre, GP surgeries and refurbished Town Hall with library and museum.</p>

<p>Evidently the money raised from developments at the Elephant so far has not been enough to provide all the benefits that everybody was expecting from the regeneration and so far committed public funding is not enough to fill the gap. This gap comprises a £40m shortfall for the northern line tube station upgrade, £12m needed for the mainline train station upgrade and about £9m needed for the northern roundabout improvements. The reason for the shortfalls is that developers are not paying enough. The CIL predecessor at the Elephant was the Elephant &amp; Castle Strategic Transport Tariff, which required developers to pay £175 per m2 of any new residential floorspace towards public transport infrastructure. The problem is that developers regularly submitted viability assessments showing that they couldn&rsquo;t afford to pay the full tariff. For example, Lend Lease was able to re-negotiate the tariff for its Heygate redevelopment down to a level of £104 per m2, providing a total transport contribution of £13m when it should have paid £22m:</p>

<p><a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/254761_1.pdf"><img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/s106headsofterms.png"></a></p>

<p>In making up the shortfall, Southwark hopes to gain £18.5m in CIL contributions from future developments at the Elephant over the next 15 years, but this is obviously not enough and it could mean raiding CIL yields from elsewhere in the borough or CIL destined for health facilities, open space or public realm benefits.</p>

<p><a href="https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/rbi-blogs/wp-content/blogs.dir/303/files/2014/06/the-blades-MoS.jpg"><img class="right" src="https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/rbi-blogs/wp-content/blogs.dir/303/files/2014/06/the-blades-MoS.jpg" width="300" height="200"></a>The model of private development cross-subsidising public benefits is plainly not working. While public assets (eg. the disposal of public land or spending from public funds) is fuelling the regeneration, developers aren&rsquo;t paying enough towards the improvements. As we have <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/04/15/the-elephants-new-ivory-towers">shown</a> they systematically use viability assessments to wriggle out of planning contributions and all we are ending up with is social-housing free towers sprouting up across the Elephant (the latest proposed being the Ministry of Sound&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.estatesgazette.com/blogs/london-residential-research/2014/06/planning-battle-ministry-move/">&lsquo;the blades&rsquo;</a>).</p>

<h2>360 Tower PRS deal collapses</h2>


<p><img class="left" src="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/imageuploads/1299150006_80.177.117.97.jpg" width="300" height="200">We <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/03/31/middlemen-on-the-make">blogged</a> earlier in the year about Elephant tower of shame the &lsquo;London 360 Tower&rsquo;. The latest news is that the groundbreaking plans for it to be one of the first large PRS - private rented sector developments in London have collapsed according to an <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/03/31/middlemen-on-the-make">article</a> in Property Week magazine. There is no information as to why this has happened - perhaps developers want a quicker return on their investment than PRS will provide? Delancey &amp; APG are also proposing a PRS development for the new shopping centre - will it go the same way? Maybe former deputy Council leader <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2013/12/07/kim-humphreys-exit-stage-left">turned development consultant</a> Kim Humphries knows?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Southwark's Mysterious Estate Renewal Zone]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/07/23/mystery-objector-1301/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-23T09:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/07/23/mystery-objector-1301</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Our <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/07/19/community-infrastructure-levy/">search</a> to identify mystery Objector 1301 - who is lobbying for subsidies to knock down Southwark&rsquo;s council estates at next week&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/856/planning_policy/2696/community_infrastructure_levy">CIL public inquiry</a> - has brought some clarity but also some more mystery with it.</p>

<p>Having been pointed towards Southwark Council&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10738/cdcil5_appendix_i_of_regulation_19_consultation_statement">table of responses</a> to CIL objector representations, we noted that the Council&rsquo;s response to <strong>Objector 1301</strong>&rsquo;s objection makes it fairly clear who the objector is, but it also raises some worrying questions about the Aylesbury redevelopment and the Council&rsquo;s plan for the future of some of its housing estates in general.</p>

<p>In its response to <strong>Objector 1301</strong>, the Council makes the worrying admission that <strong> <em>&ldquo;The appraisal showed the [Aylesbury] site to be unviable with the requisite of providing 50% affordable housing.&rdquo;</em> </strong><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10738/cdcil5_appendix_i_of_regulation_19_consultation_statement">(pg 106)</a> and it then goes on to confirm that under the terms of the development agreement Notting Hill will be providing<strong> <em>&ldquo;affordable rented units&rdquo;.</em> </strong><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10738/cdcil5_appendix_i_of_regulation_19_consultation_statement">(pg 107)</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/zone3.png"><img class="right" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/zone3.png" width="400" height="300"></a>But more worrying is the Council&rsquo;s response on page 109, where it states that it has <strong> <em>&ldquo;recommended a lower CIL rate in the lower value area of the Borough, within which the majority of housing estates identified for Estate renewal are located.&rdquo;</em> </strong><a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10738/cdcil5_appendix_i_of_regulation_19_consultation_statement">(pg 109)</a>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
<a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/CILChargingZones.png"><img class="left" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/CILChargingZones.png" width="400" height="800"></a>This estate renewal zone is shown as zone 3 in the map above. You can see from the map on the left that the Council&rsquo;s planners have split the borough into 3 zones for the puroposes of its CIL charging schedule. Zone 1 (bankside) will charge developers £400 per sqm for new residential buildings, zone 2 (the rest of the borough) will charge £200 per sqm, and developers in zone 3 - the <strong> <em>&lsquo;low value area&rsquo;</em> </strong>where <strong> <em>&lsquo;the majority of housing estate identified for renewal are located&rsquo;</em> </strong>- will be charged just £50 per sqm.</p>

<p></br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
<a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/MapSouthwarkEstates.png"><img class="right" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/MapSouthwarkEstates.png" width="300" height="300"></a>Southwark&rsquo;s new estate renewal zone reaches right up to East Street, extends down to include most of Peckham and stretches from Rotherhithe in the East across to include most of the Brandon estate in the west. The map on the right illustrates that a significant proportion of the Council&rsquo;s housing stock is within the boundary of zone 3 and much of this comprises estates that haven&rsquo;t yet been brought up to Decent Homes standard.</p>

<p>No reference can be found in any other policy documents relating to this estate renewal zone. So is this a precursory indication of what could be found in the forthcoming replacement of the borough&rsquo;s Core Strategy? (which is as usual currently being drafted behind closed doors), or is it more an insight into Southwark&rsquo;s contradictory <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1617/southwark_council_challenges_mayor_over_affordable_rent">outwardly oppositional</a> but inwardly complicit stance towards controversial <a href="http://www.standard.co.uk/news/politics/eric-pickles-tear-down-estates-to-boost-poor-innercity-homes-9277330.html">government</a> and mayoral housing policy? In any case we would be interested to know if any council tenants or leaseholders in zone 3 have been notified that their estates have been <strong> <em>&ldquo;identified for estate renewal&rdquo;</em> </strong>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PRS - (Private Rip-off Sector)]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/07/19/community-infrastructure-levy/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-19T13:20:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/07/19/community-infrastructure-levy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Delancey has been very shy about telling us what rents it will be charging for its new Private Rented Sector (PRS) homes in its <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7258">shopping centre</a> and <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7208">Tribeca Square</a> developments (which could total around 2000 units). We can now tell you: at least £375 per week for a 1-bed and £500 per week for a 2-bed flat; hardly rents that are <em>&ldquo;relevant to Londoners earning London wages&rdquo;</em> as Delancey has hitherto <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7378">maintained</a>. We know this because it is written in the evidence<a href="#footnote-1">[1]</a> submitted on behalf of Delancey by its representative Deloitte to next week&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/856/planning_policy/2696/community_infrastructure_levy">public inquiry</a> examining Southwark&rsquo;s new Community Infrastructure Levy (CIL) charging schedules:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/DelanceyCILSubmissionPRSRentLevels.png"></p>

<p>CIL is the amount a developer must pay towards public infrastructure and largely replaces the current s106 contributions. Developers don&rsquo;t like CIL because - unlike s106 - it is non-negotiable and they are now busy pleading poverty to try and get the CIL levy reduced. Delancey, joined by British Land, Berkeley homes, Sellar, Lend Lease etc. are claiming that the CIL tariffs proposed are a big threat to the viability of future projects and the delivery of affordable housing (not that the absence of affordable housing has worried them in the past!).</p>

<p>Delancey is also making an argument for reducing CIL in the particular case of Private Rented Sector developments, which is no surprise given the two sizeable PRS developments it has in its pipeline. Despite the eye-watering rents, it claims that it can&rsquo;t make as much money out of PRS as it would do if it were building private housing for sale. Added to this it has to wait longer to extract its customary 20% profit. Thankfully on this occasion Southwark Council appears to be standing its ground and rejects Delancey&rsquo;s argument<a href="#footnote-2">[2]</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/LBSResponseToCILSubmissions.png"></p>

<h3>Wanted: Objector 1301</h3>


<p><img class="left" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/objector1301.jpg" width="300" height="200">As well as Delancey, Deloitte is representing several other developers at the inquiry, but none are as mysterious as <strong>Objector 1301</strong> whose identity is &lsquo;confidential&rsquo;<a href="#footnote-3">[3]</a>. We are not surprised that objector 1301 wants to keep himself in the shadows, because his great idea is that anybody knocking down and redeveloping a council estate should not pay any CIL at all! <strong>Objector 1301</strong>&rsquo;s argument is that the cost of having to give ex-tenants and leaseholders fair compensation for losing their homes (although it is seldom fair) is too high to maintain the customary 20% profit, while also paying for local public infrastructure. <strong>Objector 1301</strong>&rsquo;s solution to the problem is simple and elegant - just insert a footnote saying that none of the above applies to council estate regenerations<a href="#footnote-4">[4]</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/objector1301.png"></p>

<p>Who can this mystery <strong>Objector 1301</strong> be? Property developers have no qualms about being unpopular in their pursuit of profit, it is the nature of the beast. But a Housing Association may well feel the need to maintain its anonymity. Their free-market orientation is becoming more <a href="http://www.socialhousing.co.uk/free-preview-social-housings-2014-sales-and-development-activity-special-report/7004650.article">apparent</a> day by day, but Housing Associations must at least keep up the pretense of being affordable housing providers. If <strong>Objector 1301</strong> is a housing association could it possibly be one with extensive interests in Southwark? maybe one with the initials NHHT? We don&rsquo;t know for sure, but the 35% campaign is offering a small reward for any information that leads to the identification of this mystery objector.</p>

<p><font size="2"><p id="footnote-1">[1] See page 187 of <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10287/cdcil9_regulation_17_representations_to_revised_draft_cil_charging_schedule">submitted written representations to CIL Charging Schedule</a></p></font></p>

<p><font size="2"><p id="footnote-2">[2] See para 38 of <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10211/cdcil10_revised_draft_cil_charging_schedule_submission_report_april_2014">April 2014 CIL Charging Schedule Submission Report</a></p></font></p>

<p><font size="2"><p id="footnote-3">[3] See page 144 of <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10287/cdcil9_regulation_17_representations_to_revised_draft_cil_charging_schedule">submitted written representations to CIL Charging Schedule</a></p></font></p>

<p><font size="2"><p id="footnote-4">[4] See page 146 of <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/download/downloads/id/10287/cdcil9_regulation_17_representations_to_revised_draft_cil_charging_schedule">submitted written representations to CIL Charging Schedule</a></p></font></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Where There's Bronze There's Brass]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/07/12/the-more-rent-seeking-elephants-at-elephant-the-better/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-12T11:03:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/07/12/the-more-rent-seeking-elephants-at-elephant-the-better</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/samkeilelephant.jpg"><img class="left" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/samkeilelephant.jpg" width="300" height="200"></a>Just when we thought the Heygate pyramid had set the limits on misconceived artistic collaborations at the Elephant, we got wind of the latest &lsquo;triumphant elephant&rsquo; sculpture proposal.
According to <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/samkeil_bio_2010.pdf">documents</a> posted on artist Sam Keil&rsquo;s website <em>&ldquo;the team responsible for the redevelopment of the Elephant and Castle district in South London have commissioned Sam to sculpt a major piece for a new public square&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p>The sculpture proposed on the site of the former Heygate estate football pitch is to comprise a bronze elephant <a href="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/keil_elephant.pdf"><em>&ldquo;standing on its hind legs on top of a tall castle tower, in the act of leaping into the air with its water-spraying trunk raised high in triumph.&rdquo;</em></a> The project also includes <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/samkeil_bio_2010.pdf"><em>&ldquo;a series of small elephants which will be distributed as bronze key rings to the owners of the many new apartments associated with the redevelopment.&rdquo;</em></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.vallico.net/sam/img/relief/2.jpg"><img class="right" src="http://www.vallico.net/sam/img/relief/2.jpg" width="300" height="200"></a>Sam has <a href="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/keil_elephant.pdf">published the full proposal</a> of the project on her website along with an example of her previous work at a St. John&rsquo;s Wood development, where - under the heading <em>&ldquo;The Effect of a Sam Keil Bronze on Property&rdquo;</em> - she claims that her sculptures enable developers to <em>&ldquo;charge whatever rent you like&rdquo;</em> . A letter from Southwark is also appended to her proposal in which Council bosses claim to be <em>&ldquo;very enthusiastic&rdquo;</em> about the idea, because it would be <em>&ldquo;well received locally&rdquo;</em> and that <em>&ldquo;the more elephants at the elephant the better!&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.vallico.net/sam/img/prince_philip.jpg" width="300" height="200">International artist Keil, seen here rubbing shoulders with Prince Philip, is represented by a <a href="http://www.whpatterson.com/">fine-art gallery</a> in Mayfair. Although Sam&rsquo;s husband claims that she got the commission <a href="http://www.barganews.com/blogs/towler/?p=37"><em>&ldquo;essentially because she knows one guy with connections&rdquo;</em></a> and that <a href="http://www.barganews.com/blogs/towler/?p=37"><em>&ldquo;not only can she sculpt, but she’s got a nice bottom&rdquo;</em></a>. Sam says that in her spare time she enjoys riding horses <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/samkeil_bio_2010.pdf"><em>&ldquo;bareback in the Arizona Badlands and also in the Negev desert in Israel&rdquo;</em></a>.</p>

<p>Sam <a href="http://www.vallico.net/sam/biography.html">works</a> from her studios in Cambridge and Tuscany and has delivered other high-profile sculptures during her career. In 2011 she <a href="http://www.vallico.net/sam/docs/ft.pdf">presented</a> a bronze eagle to former BP Chief Exec Lord Browne at the Royal Academy of Engineering. Her eagle is <a href="http://www.vallico.net/sam/docs/mike_towler_royal_academy.txt">claimed</a> to signify a <em>&ldquo;symbol of power&rdquo;</em> in manifesting the desire to make the <em>&ldquo;UK the King of Nations again&rdquo;</em>.</p>

<p>Sam claims her bronze elephant <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/samkeil_bio_2010.pdf"><em>&ldquo;`Phoenix&#8217; with water soaring from his trunk will be a new twenty-first century update of the well-known elephant motif for the area&rdquo;</em></a>. We think it will be a tasteless and poorly thought-out marketing gimmick with little public value and a monument to how out-of-touch Southwark regen bosses are with local opinion.</p>

<h2>Kim Consulting (Limited)</h2>


<p><a href="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/photo-5-1.jpg"><img class="right" src="https://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/photo-5-1.jpg" width="300" height="200"></a>Delancey&rsquo;s long-promised consultation on the future of the shopping centre has finally begun. Ex-deputy Council Leader <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2013/12/07/kim-humphreys-exit-stage-left">turned development consultant</a> Kim Humphries, could be seen buttonholing unsuspecting shoppers last Friday to get their views on the redevelopment. One of the key questions being put is: <em>&ldquo;Do you think that the whole of the shopping centre site should be redeveloped rather than refurbished?“</em> This can only be rhetorical, because as our friends at <a href="http://southwarknotes.wordpress.com">Southwark Notes</a> point out - the decision to demolish the shopping centre has already been <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7378">taken</a> by Delancey. Southwark Council has also <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1368/council_will_insist_on_demolition_of_shopping_centre_at_elephant">decided</a> to &lsquo;insist&rsquo; on demolition of the centre.</p>

<p>At a recent Walworth Society meeting, Delancey said that it hopes to complete the consultation and submit a planning application by May 2014. They listed 94 community groups of different kinds that they said they will consult. One group omitted from the list were the shopkeepers. When challenged, Delancey insisted that shopkeepers&#8217; views would be taken fully into account, but that another team of Delancey operatives would be talking to the shopkeepers at the same time as re-negotiating their leases. We are sure this twin-track approach will not inhibit shopkeepers expressing their views. We hear that leases currently offered for renewal are limited to 5 years with a &lsquo;break clause&rsquo; in November 2016, which suggests that this might be the time that those who don&rsquo;t fit the profile of the new town centre will be leaving us.</p>

<p>Delancey is a private developer and a big one. It is registered in the British Virgin Islands and how Delancey turns this to good advantage has already been exposed in <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/PrivateEyeNo1311.pdf">Private Eye</a> and a Channel 4 Dispatches programme. It is <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/newsbysector/constructionandproperty/8606978/Minerva-deal-sees-Jamie-Ritblat-follow-in-fathers-property-footsteps.html">run</a> by Jamie Ritblat and funded by George Soros. Jamie is following in his dad&rsquo;s footsteps - former British Land chief executive Sir John Ritblat - and is a donor to the Tory party. He courted <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2041229/Tory-donor-Jamie-Ritblat-snaps-Olympic-Village-knock-price--costing-275m.html">controversy</a> in 2011 when he snapped up the Olympic Village at a knock down price of £557million – £275million less than the taxpayer paid <a href="http://www.thelondonmagazine.co.uk/property-experts/expert-opinions/the-olympic-village.html">bailing out</a> the previous owner - Lend Lease. Standing behind Jamie is the richest man in the world, George Soros. Mr Soros is notorious for nearly bankrupting the Bank of England and tipping the rest of us into poverty. Mr Soros claims to be <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/business/2012/sep/13/black-wednesday-20-years-pound-erm">proud</a> of the fact the he made £1bn selling sterling that he didn&rsquo;t own. We obviously need have no fear about the future of the shopping centre development not being in good hands.</p>

<h3>Shopping Centre who&#8217;s who?</h3>


<p>The shopping centre was originally to be redeveloped by Lend Lease under the <a href="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2013/02/ra.pdf">Regeneration Agreement</a> signed in 2010 with Southwark Council. St Modwens (KPI) was the owner of the shopping centre at that time. A year later it signed an agreement with Southwark Council and another, tripartite agreement with both Southwark and Lend Lease for the redevelopment of the centre<a href="#footnote-1">[1]</a>. These agreements have been kept confidential<a href="#footnote-2">[2]</a>. St Modwen then sold the site to Delancey &amp; funding partner APG in 2013. The question then, is what is the current contractual relationship between Southwark, Lend Lease and Delancey for the redevelopment of the shopping centre? It appears to be another instance where Southwark Council has several hats: development partner; public authority with CPO powers; author of enforcer of planning policy, and as former Heygate residents know it does not always resolve these competing roles in the best interests of local people.</p>

<h2>Save the Coronet</h2>


<p><img class="left" src="http://crackmagazine.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/Screen-shot-2013-12-03-at-14.55.50-660x403.png" width="300" height="200">The Coronet is taking no chances with its future, it has launched the <a href="http://coronettheatre.co.uk/home/save-the-coronet/">&lsquo;Save the Coronet&rsquo;</a> campaign and has gained impressive support from a long list of <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/SNSaveTheCoronet.pdf">distinguished artists</a> who have performed there. A sizeable part of the shopping centre site is occupied by the Coronet - a music and event venue, it has also been a cinema and music hall <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7701">dating back to 1872</a> and is a popular local institution.</p>

<h2>Trading Places</h2>


<p>Welcome to &lsquo;Social Life&rsquo; -a social enterprise based on the Pullens estate. Funded by the Young Foundation, their mission is <em>&ldquo;to reconnect placemaking with people&rsquo;s everyday experience and the way that communities work.&rdquo;</em> They have turned their attention to the Elephant &amp; Castle and the impact of the regeneration on local people. The say this: <em>&ldquo;we are carrying out an independent research project to understand how traders in the Elephant &amp; Castle Shopping Centre are being affected by the proposed regeneration. We want to understand how the proposed changes are affecting people now and how they will impact on traders and customers and their businesses, livelihoods, friendships and local relationships in the future. We want to understand more about the Shopping Centre’s social value.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>The results of the research which will be made available in a number of ways: a short report, which will be available on Social Life’s website; a local exhibition of stories and photographs; and a festival about social change being organised by the Social Innovation Exchange. The research findings will be available in September 2014. Further details can be found on <a href="http://www.social-life.co/blog/post/Trading_Places_Elephant_and_Castle_regen/">their website</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/snag-walk-july-2014-new.jpg"><img class="left" src="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/snag-walk-july-2014-new.jpg?w=500&h=669" width="300" height="150"></a>Last but not least, our friends at Southwark Notes are organising a <a href="http://southwarknotes.wordpress.com/2014/07/06/regeneration-rip-the-elephant-sat-19th-july-walk-sound-films/">day of excitement and interest</a> on Sat 19th July. The day begins with an anti-gentrification walk followed by &lsquo;Soundscape&rsquo; - <em>&ldquo;an immersive multimedia sound piece investigating community and gentrification&rdquo;</em> ending with the screening of 3 films including the much-awaited <a href="http://concreteheartland.info">&lsquo;Concrete Heartland&rsquo;</a> - a film <em>&ldquo;exposing the social cleansing of the Heygate Estate in Elephant and Castle.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p><font size="1"><p id="footnote-1">[1] See para 2 of this <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/mgConvert2Pdf.aspx?ID=5663&amp;T=9">22 Nov 2011 Cabinet paper.</a></p></font>
<font size="1"><p id="footnote-2">[2] See para 4 of this <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/mgConvert2Pdf.aspx?ID=5663&amp;T=9">22 Nov 2011 Cabinet paper.</a>   </p></font></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury Estate - 42 More Residents Face Compulsory Purchase]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/06/30/aylesbury-estate-compulsory-purchase-order/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-30T16:17:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/06/30/aylesbury-estate-compulsory-purchase-order</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/gallery/2014/apr/15/china-nail-houses-in-pictures-property-development"><img class="left" src="http://static.guim.co.uk/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2014/4/13/1397410555601/baac3533-f9fe-4c47-994d-eeadf76d8ee1-620x461.jpeg" width="300" height="200"></a> In China homeowners who stand in the way of new developments can refuse compensation if they are prepared to stay put in <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/gallery/2014/apr/15/china-nail-houses-in-pictures-property-development">&lsquo;nail houses&rsquo;</a>. In Britain homeowners don&rsquo;t have that option - sooner or later they would have to accept whatever is offered, as the leaseholders on Southwark&rsquo;s Aylesbury estate are finding out.</p>

<p>Last week Southwark Council served a Compulsory Purchase Order on 22 leaseholders, 12 secure tenants and 8 non-secure tenants whose homes are to be demolished in the next phase of the Aylesbury redevelopment. We reported briefly last year on the <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/SNWolverton.pdf">elderly</a> residents <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/ObjectionCPOAugust2012.pdf">objecting</a> to the <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/WolvertonCPO.pdf">Compulsory Purchase</a> of their homes during the previous phase of the scheme and how they were subsequently <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/30/aylesbury-leaseholder-fights-incestuous-valuation/">forced into litigation</a> in order to obtain fair compensation for their homes.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/pictures/643xAny/2/6/5/18265_Regen_Aylesbury_032.jpg" width="300" height="200">The Council&rsquo;s justification for the CPO - its <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/AylesburyPhase3CPO.pdf">Statement of Reasons</a> for making the order is full of the usual arguments: &ldquo;the Aylesbury estate is amongst the most deprived areas in England&rdquo;; &ldquo;the built fabric is dated&rdquo;; &ldquo;it goes against good design principles&rdquo;; &ldquo;elements of its layout such as the raised walkways contribute to crime&rdquo;.
Many of these arguments can be contested, for example the 2005 Council-commissioned structural survey declared the buildings sound and Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200179/aylesbury_estate/2686/aylesbury_development_partnership/2">own admission</a> that the estate&rsquo;s crime rate is 45% below the borough average. Even if the Council&rsquo;s arguments are accepted it doesn&rsquo;t justify the Council&rsquo;s use of Compulsory Purchase powers against these residents.</p>

<p>One difference between this CPO and that of the Heygate is that it has been served not just on leaseholders but also on council tenants. The Heygate&rsquo;s 1,000 tenants were instead removed from the estate under the Landlord &amp; Tenant Act with the help of 198 Notices to Quit and 4 eventual evictions. Whatever the procedure used, the Council is obliged to make secure tenants an offer of alternative accommodation. Non-secure tenants aren&rsquo;t so lucky: under the Aylesbury CPO there is no guarantee of any offer at all.</p>

<p>Leaseholders will have to rely on their compensation to buy a new home in the area. We know from the two cases that recently went to the Lands Tribunal that this is woefully inadequate with offers of just £85k for a 1-bed and £165k for a 4-bed flat. While current leaseholders are being offered a pittance, 2-bed new-build flats in the <a href="http://www.burgessterrace.co.uk/">completed phase 1</a> Aylesbury development are being <a href="http://www.dropbox.com/s/v02kjcryf8ni15r/LandRegistryTitleTGL392009.pdf">sold for £490,000</a>.</p>

<p>It is difficult to understand this when Southwark should be getting plenty of money from the sale of 28.5 hectares of prime central London real estate. It got £20m for the sale of its nearby Manor Place development site to Notting Hill Housing (£11.8m per Hectare); on this comparison the Aylesbury site could be worth a staggering £330m.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.albany-place.co.uk/"><img class="left" src="http://www.ruskinwalk.co.uk/images/common/ruskin-walk-brochure.jpg"></a>Aylesbury leaseholders are being offered shared ownership options on the nearby Elmington estate regeneration, but this is on very unfavourable terms as shown by <a href="http://moderngov.southwarksites.com/documents/s45196/Representation%20from%20Aylesbury%20Leaseholders%20Action%20Group.pdf">submissions</a> from leaseholders to the Council&rsquo;s recent Overview and Scrutiny Committee meeting.</p>

<p>Aylesbury Leaseholders have formed themselves into an action group and have released <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/vjtwnow85uwfta0/AylesburyCPOPressStatement4July2014v3.pdf">this press statement</a> in their fight to get a fair deal. They have objected to the CPO and there is likely to be a public inquiry.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notting Hill No Social Housing Trust]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/06/16/notting-hill-housing-no-social-housing/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-16T19:17:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/06/16/notting-hill-housing-no-social-housing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://www.britishlistedbuildings.co.uk/images/buildings/en/471/471093-18941-800.jpg" width="300" height="200">One of the most characterful development sites within the the Elephant and Castle Opportunity Area is the <a href="http://www.southwarknews.co.uk/elephant-and-castle-home/elephant-and-castle-history/00,news,10016,5757,00.htm">Manor Place Baths</a>.  The baths provided laundry and bathing facilities to Walworth people for 80 years, until demolition of the surrounding streets and the removal of the local population to the Heygate and Ayelsbury estates sounded its death knell in the 80’s; it was replaced as a swimming pool by the Elephant &amp; Castle leisure centre, the baths were filled in by Southwark Council in 1998 and the buildings were then used by the Council&rsquo;s Environmental Services department until their relocation in 2012.</p>

<p>Notting Hill Housing Trust (NHHT) purchased the 1.7 hectare site from the Council in Nov 2013 for the reasonable sum of £20m - reasonable compared to the <a href="http://www.standard.co.uk/news/london/elephant-and-castle-estate-revamp-ripped-off-taxpayers-8482794.html">£50m figure</a> it sold the 9.9 Hectare Heygate site for. NHHT is now putting out feelers to local community groups in anticipation of a planning application before the end of the year.   The omens do not look good.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/manorplace.jpg"><img class="right" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/manorplace.jpg" width="370" height="240"></a> First, rather than deal directly with the local community NHTT have engaged M&amp;N Place to do the work for them.  M&amp;N Place is eminently qualified – it has an <a href="http://www.mnplace.co.uk/contact-us/">office in Abu Dhabi</a>, provides <a href="http://www.mnplace.co.uk/case-studies/pre-planning/">&lsquo;political intelligence&rsquo;</a> about local authorities and is well versed in bending local opinion to the developers will on behalf of London boroughs. M&amp;N Place is also eminently <a href="http://www.mnplace.co.uk/case-studies/pre-planning/kidbrooke-greenwich/">experienced</a> - having successfully bent opinion for Berkeley homes&#8217; <a href="http://halag.files.wordpress.com/2010/11/ferrier.pdf">deplorable redevelopment</a> of the Ferrier estate in Greenwich.</p>

<p>Undeterred, a concerned local resident attended the first <a href="http://manorplacedepot.co.uk/manor-place-banners.pdf">public exhibition</a> for the development. There was no information about affordable housing on display, but after probing NHHT staff it turns out there will be no social housing - we will be getting the dreaded affordable rent instead. They agreed this would be beyond the means of people on low or average incomes. <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/manorplacedepotconsultation.pdf">Here</a> is a link to his full report.</p>

<p>NHHT are shy about saying what exactly the rents will be, but below is a screenshot taken <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/customers/permanent-rented-housing/information-for-permanent-rented-housing-tenants/affordable-rent-update">from its website</a> which gives us some idea what to expect:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/nhhtrents.png"></p>

<h3>Housing contradictions</h3>


<p>Some housing associations have <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/affordable-rent-not-worth-the-risk-say-associations/6513502.article">complained</a> about the introduction of affordable rent, but NHHT is a true believer: as reported in Labour&rsquo;s <a href="http://redbrickblog.wordpress.com/2014/06/04/what-are-housing-associations-for-part-4/">redbrick blog</a> &lsquo;NHHT chief Kate Davies chaired the ‘Housing and Dependency Working Group’ of Iain Duncan Smith’s think tank the Centre for Social Justice. The name of the group almost says it all, but her conclusion is: ‘social housing is not a desirable destination; private ownership is preferable to state provided solutions’.</p>

<p>NHHT&rsquo;s hostility to social housing is evident in its <a href="http://www.nottinghillhousing.org.uk/customers/permanent-rented-housing/information-for-permanent-rented-housing-tenants/affordable-rent-update">conversion policy</a> - social rented homes will be converted to affordable rent as soon as there is a change of tenant.</p>

<p>NHHT will be providing 1,200 of Southwark&rsquo;s new homes over the next three years in Camberwell, Peckham, Bermondsey &amp; Blackfriars plus the 3,500 new homes on the Aylesbury estate. In a <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/05/manx-connections-the-off-shore-home-of-the-elephants-developers">previous blog</a> we raised concerns about exactly what kind of affordable housing the Aylesbury estate would get. As the picture becomes clearer that concern deepens. Up to now Southwark has fought the very idea of introducing affordable rent to the borough, joining with seven other boroughs in <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1387/councils_to_take_mayor_of_london_to_court_over_affordable_rents">taking Boris Johnson to court</a>. Former head of regeneration Cllr Fiona Colley <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/fionacolleyresponsetolondonplan.pdf">summed up</a> the matter simply: <em>&lsquo;affordable rent will be very difficult for people in housing need to afford&rsquo;</em>. So why is NHHT - the champion of affordable rent - providing so many of Southwark&rsquo;s new homes?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aylesbury Leaseholder Fights 'Incestuous' Valuations]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/30/aylesbury-leaseholder-fights-incestuous-valuation/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-30T08:08:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/30/aylesbury-leaseholder-fights-incestuous-valuation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://cached.imagescaler.hbpl.co.uk/resize/scaleWidth/456/?sURL=http://offlinehbpl.hbpl.co.uk/News/NST/charity-Tribunal-20140514044354391.jpg" width="250" height="140">As reported in our previous blog post, this week saw a second Aylesbury leaseholder fighting the council&rsquo;s controversial compensation valuations at the Upper Lands Tribunal. In buying back homes on the estate the Council has consistently maintained that all leaseholders are given &lsquo;market value&rsquo; in compensation for the loss of their homes. Last week <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/16/southwark-gives-green-light-to-slum-landlords/">we learned</a> how it arrives at its market value calculation by using illegaly-converted flats as comparable market evidence. This week we learned more about its valuation procedures.</p>

<p>The claimant was a Mrs Olubunmi John, formerly of 28 Wolverton on the Aylesbury estate and now living in the Kent borders. She was represented by <a href="http://www.averyassociatessurveyors.com/">Avery Associates</a> chartered surveyors and a barrister from <a href="http://www.tanfieldchambers.co.uk/Barristers/Stan_Gallagher">Tanfield Chambers</a>. Mrs John&rsquo;s surveyor had originally carried out a survey and valued her 3-storey, 4-bed maisonette at £288,750. In adjusting for market conditions he increased this to £297,500 on the date she and her family had to leave. The council&rsquo;s valuation of Mrs John&rsquo;s home on the day it took possession was just £165,000.</p>

<p>The hearing began with Mrs John&rsquo;s representatives producing a council-commissioned report confirming that the buildings were structurally sound. This quickly defeated earlier unevidenced intimations by the council that the Aylesbury estate&rsquo;s buildings had structural issues.</p>

<p>The barrister then questioned the impartiality of the Southwark council officer who decided on the compensation offer. He pointed out that other boroughs use an independent valuer - somebody from outside the council to decide how much the property is worth. The compensation is then based upon this objective valuation. Southwark Council keep it all &lsquo;in house&rsquo;: they decide their own valuation and then offer that amount as compensation. Most other London Boroughs - <a href="http://sutton.moderngov.co.uk/Data/Strategy%20Committee/20040608/Agenda/$Item%2016.doc.pdf">Sutton</a>,  <a href="http://bit.ly/1pqMVho">Kensington &amp; Chelsea</a>, <a href="http://www.newham.gov.uk/Documents/Environment%20and%20planning/Carpenters%20Estate%20Residents%20Charter.pdf">Newham</a>,
<a href="http://debeauvoircouncillors.blogspot.co.uk/2013/06/colville-estate-regeneration-what-is.html">Hackney</a> and Lewisham to name just a few - all rely on valuations from independent external valuers as the basis for their negotiations.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8345/8183341508_e809f1b36f_z.jpg" width="300" height="200">Mrs John&rsquo;s barrister also criticised Southwark Council for using other properties on the Aylesbury also earmarked for demolition as its basis for compensation. He referred to Greenwich Council doing just this on the <a href="http://halag.files.wordpress.com/2010/11/ferrier.pdf">Ferrier estate</a> regeneration in Kidbrooke. The Tribunal there rejected the practice as &lsquo;incestuous&rsquo; when it heard an appeal from a Ferrier leaseholder in 2007 and ordered the use of properties off the estate to be used as comparables when calculating compensation.</p>

<p>The barrister went on to claim that the Council was undervaluing properties on the Aylesbury and that this was demonstrated by the high returns that buy-to-let investors were making on the estate. He showed evidence that the properties were averaging a 13% yield - more than double the current average return on investment for properties in London which stands at around 6%. Using the London average figure and average rents on the Aylesbury to calculate the market value of Mrs John&rsquo;s home gives a figure of around £300,000 - nearly double the council&rsquo;s offer. But even this amount is unlikely to buy her a new home in the swanky new <a href="http://www.albany-place.co.uk">Harvard Gardens</a> - the development replacing her Aylesbury home.</p>

<p>The Lands Tribunal should be there to protect people like Mrs John and her neighbours, including the 130 or so <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/SNWolverton.pdf">elderly leaseholders</a> left on the estate, but the risk of taking on Southwark Council and losing is too high and Southwark Council is taking full of advantage of the fact. One of the first things the new labour administration must do is start offering the estate&rsquo;s leaseholders decent and fair compensation for the loss of their homes.</p>

<h2>Meet the &#8216;pop-up&#8217; neighbours</h2>


<p><a href="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/elephant-rd-park-2008.jpg"><img class="right" src="http://southwarknotes.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/elephant-rd-park-2008.jpg" width="300" height="200"></a>On Thursday this week the new <a href="http://www.theartworks-uk.com/">Heygate pop-up boxpark</a> was showcasing its container units to prospective tenants. The event was marketed on the <a href="http://shoreditch.hypeapp.co/shared-events/14034/">&lsquo;Shoreditch Hype&rsquo;</a> website inviting <em>&lsquo;designer-maker&rsquo;</em> or creative businesses to <em>&lsquo;head south for Pop-ups&rsquo;</em> bringing the East London vibe to the Elephant. Prospective tenants were <a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/824753570885436/">invited</a> to come and <em>&lsquo;meet the neighbours&rsquo;</em> at the nearly completed container boxpark located the former Elephant Park - formerly designated public open space until its <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2012/07/04/londons-largest-new-private-park-in-70-years">controversial enclosure</a> in 2012.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BouMpuWIAAApjKT.png" width="300" height="200">Among the <a href="http://blog.wearepopup.com/p/viewing-at-the-artworks/">&lsquo;neighbours&rsquo;</a> already booked to move into the boxpark - when it is completed at the end of June - are two pop-up fashion boutiques, a massage and yoga <a href="http://signup.body-align.co.uk/">&lsquo;vitality hub&rsquo;</a>, a Mauritian tearoom where <em>&lsquo;Artists and designers will showcase their products within Qubes that form the walls&rsquo;</em> and a <a href="http://www.southeastcakery.com/">pop-up &lsquo;Brownie Bar&rsquo;</a>. There will be another open day for prospective designer makers and creative businesses on Weds 4th June.</p>

<h2>Upcoming Events</h2>


<h3>The People&#8217;s Bureau</h3>


<p><a href="http://peoplesrepublicofsouthwark.co.uk/images/stories/news/28maypeoplesbureau.jpg"><img class="left" src="http://peoplesrepublicofsouthwark.co.uk/images/stories/news/28maypeoplesbureau.jpg" width="200" height="300"></a>
In conjunction with the Latin American Women’s Rights Service, local artists Rebecca Davies and Eva Sajovic will be opening <strong>the People&rsquo;s Bureau</strong> for a few days on Friday 30th May, Saturday 31st May and Monday 2nd June.</p>

<p>The People&rsquo;s Bureau is a space and a network to exchange skills and needs. The pilot will run for three days from 11:00 - 17:00 at Unit 306 in the Elephant and Castle Shopping Centre.</p>

<p>The aim of the People&rsquo;s Bureau is to create a pool of collective local knowledge through exchange, a supporting network of different skills and to draw attention to the diversity and existence of different economies in the Elephant and Castle.</p>

<p>For more information about the project, please go to their <a href="http://peoplesbureau.tumblr.com/">website.</a></p>

<h3>Doing the Walworth Walk</h3>


<p><a href="http://www.peoplesrepublicofsouthwark.co.uk/images/stories/news/30may201405.PNG"><img class="left" src="http://www.peoplesrepublicofsouthwark.co.uk/images/stories/news/30may201405.PNG" width="300" height="200"></a>Walworth Society and Friends of Burgess Park have joined forces to host a series of free events on Saturday 7th June, under the <em>&lsquo;Walworth Heritage Day&rsquo;</em> umbrella.
The day will kick off with two guided walks around Walworth. The walks (first at 09:30, second one at 10:00) start at La Bodeguita (South American restaurant at the north end of Walworth Road) will criss-cross Walworth Road until they finish at St Peter&rsquo;s Church in Liverpool Grove, approximately two hours later.</p>

<p>From 11:00 - 15:00, St Peter&rsquo;s Church will host the exhibition of the Walworth heritage and an event by Creation Trust:</p>

<p><strong>This is Walworth</strong>, by the Walworth Society, is an exhibition of panoramas of all the shops and historic buildings that make up the Walworth Road and see how it has changed over the past 100 years.</p>

<p><strong>&lsquo;Put it on the map&rsquo;</strong>, by the council-led <a href="http://www.creationtrust.org/">Creation Trust</a> - you will be invited to tell your stories of the area at the Listening Post, see old images of Walworth from Southwark&rsquo;s Local History Library and Archive collection and suggest names of the new streets, blocks and open spaces at <a href="http://www.rightmove.co.uk/developer/branch/Lend-Lease/Elephant-Park-108524.html">Elephant Park</a> (or, as many local people with memory still prefer to call it, the former Heygate estate).</p>

<p>Free refreshments will be provided by the Electric Elephant Cafe at Inspire.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Another Aylesbury Leaseholder Goes to Lands Tribunal]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/24/aylesbury-leaseholders-at-upper-lands-tribunal/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-24T14:12:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/24/aylesbury-leaseholders-at-upper-lands-tribunal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As mentioned in our previous <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/16/southwark-gives-green-light-to-slum-landlords/">blog post</a>, this week will see a second Aylesbury estate leaseholder taking the council to the <a href="http://www.justice.gov.uk/tribunals/lands">Lands Tribunal</a> over low valuations following its <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/ObjectionCPOAugust2012.pdf">Compulsory Purchase Order</a> of homeowners on the Wolverton block <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/info/200179/aylesbury_estate/1965/project_overview/3">(site 7 of the regen)</a>. 59 family maisonettes, a sports pitch and around <a href="http://www.peoplesrepublicofsouthwark.co.uk/hold-news/news/3200-sedan-way-chainsaw-massacre">30 mature trees</a> have been demolished to make way for <a href="http://www.albany-place.co.uk/">&lsquo;Harvard Gardens&rsquo;</a>.
<img class="center" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/Demolition.jpg"></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.albany-place.co.uk/images/common/harvard-gardens-thumb.jpg">This is the second phase of the Aylesbury regeneration scheme, an L&amp;Q development comprising 147 new homes about which there is <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/05/manx-connections-the-off-shore-home-of-the-elephants-developers/">concern</a> that the social rented element will be the unaffordable &lsquo;affordable rents&rsquo; of up to 80% market. <br/>
</br>
</br></p>

<p>Former resident, Ms Olubunmi John is the second Aylesbury leaseholder taking the council to court over the low compensation she was paid for her home. Ms John lived with her family at no. 28 Wolverton, a 3-storey, 4-bed maisonette until the council took possession of their home under Compulsory Purchase powers in August 2013.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/mrhilmi.jpg"><img class="right" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/mrhilmi.jpg" width="300" height="200"></a>
Ms John and fellow leaseholders <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/SNWolverton.pdf">fought hard</a> for over two years against the council&rsquo;s low valuation offers of compensation for the loss of their homes. Many are elderly and had lived on the block since it was first built in the early 70s. Amongst these was Mr Djevdet Hilmi age 82 (pictured right), who had lived at 36 Wolverton since 1981; he passed away in Jan 2013, just weeks before he was due to appear at a Public Inquiry to contest the Compulsory Purchase Order.</p>

<p>Ms John&rsquo;s property has been independently valued by her RICS qualified surveyor at £288,750; the council&rsquo;s final compensation payment was just £165,000. Much higher compensation is being paid in other regeneration schemes by other boroughs, such as Myatts Fields in Lambeth where Ms John&rsquo;s surevyor has also represented displaced leaseholders.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/fairerfuture.png">The compensation hearing will take place on Tuesday 27th May at the Upper Lands Tribunal in Bedford Square. Substantial legal costs will be incurred by the losing party whoever it is. Why doesn&rsquo;t Southwark Council abide by its own slogan <em>&lsquo;A fairer future for all&rsquo;</em> and pay Ms John a fair price for her home?
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<h2>Appealing the appeal?</h2>


<p>What&rsquo;s up with Southwark Council and Lend Lease? After Southwark <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1672/decision_on_heygate_viability_assessment_tribunal">‘broadly welcoming’</a> the <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/10/foi-appeal-decision/">Tribunal&rsquo;s decision</a> on the Heygate viability assessment, and despite council leader Peter John <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7585">saying</a> that the assessment would show what a good deal 25% affordable housing was, Lend Lease has now asked the Tribunal for more time to respond, as well as more time to decide whether or not to appeal. The Tribunal has responded by giving Southwark and Lend Lease 14 more days until 20th June to come up with the viability assessment and the possibility of appeals still remains open.</p>

<h2>The Elephant forgets</h2>


<p>Retailers, shoppers and users of the Elephant &amp; Castle shopping centre are becoming increasingly apprehensive about its future. New owners Delancey APG have promised consultations on the redevelopment of the site now the local elections are over, so it&rsquo;s useful to look back on the rather dismal history of the shopping centre&rsquo;s previous consultations and a good place to start is this video featuring Dr. Ben Campkin, director of UCL&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/urbanlab">urban lab</a> and author of <a href="http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=SBMPEA6cJREC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=ben%20campkin%20remaking%20london&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q=ben%20campkin%20remaking%20london&amp;f=false">&lsquo;Remaking London&rsquo;</a>.</p>

<center>
<iframe width="350" height="197" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/6-1T1pWiWcQ?list=PLSn28aOCzdBfi8MqPq7DpdeKXuvaePJol" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</center>


<p>Dr Campkin refers to the difficulty of finding the 2005 Ouseley report about allegations of institutional racism in the shopping centre&rsquo;s redevelopment process. We took up the challenge, but it does seem to have dissapeared into Southwark Council&rsquo;s memory hole - despite the fact that there was a <a href="http://moderngov.southwark.gov.uk/ieListMeetings.aspx?CId=194&amp;Year=2005">whole committee</a> set up to respond to it.</p>

<h2>Regeneration goes viral</h2>


<p><img class="right" src="http://i.guim.co.uk/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2014/5/16/1400257660411/Woodberry-Down-new-builds-012.jpg?width=620&height=-&quality=95" width="300" height="200">It is not just us at the Elephant &amp; Castle who are suffering from regeneration. The <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/news/datablog/interactive/2014/may/18/public-private-partnership-housing-projects-london-mapped">Guardian map</a> below shows how it is spreading like a rash across the capital. The map was part of a <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2014/may/18/-sp-truth-about-gentrification-how-woodberry-down-became-woodberry-park">major story</a> about the regeneration of Hackney&rsquo;s Woodbury down - a council estate of over 1500 homes. The familiar themes are all there: managed dilapidation, council-sponsored gentrification, financial viability defined by fat developer profits, a net loss of social rented housing and poor compensation for leaseholders, but great opportunities for overseas investors.</p>

<iframe width="600" height="400" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://www.google.com/fusiontables/embedviz?q=select+col4+from+1uNRQelJXKNtyCVQkmh6VocGymqxVgUVatz6yevOF&amp;viz=MAP&amp;h=false&amp;lat=51.510697&amp;lng=-0.129547&amp;t=1&amp;z=10&amp;l=col4&amp;y=2&amp;tmplt=2&amp;hml=TWO_COL_LAT_LNG"></iframe>


<p>Lessons are being learned though and they are being pulled together in the forthcoming <em>&lsquo;Staying Put: an Anti-gentrification Handbook for Council Estates in London&rsquo;</em>, a collaboration between <a href="http://justspace.org.uk/">Just Space</a>, <a href="http://southwarknotes.wordpress.com">Southwark Notes Archives Group</a>, Prof. Loretta Lees and The <a href="http://www.londontenants.org/">London Tenants Federation</a>.</p>

<p>The handbook is designed to help local communities faced with the gentrification of their council estate.  It explains what gentrification is, how communities can resist it and the alternatives to demolition and displacement. It contains ideas, stories and resources gathered from the experiences of tenants, leaseholders and the wider community organising around council estates in London. The handbook will be launched on 12th June - more details to come.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Southwark's Rogue Landlords - Enforcement or Endorsement?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/16/southwark-gives-green-light-to-slum-landlords/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-16T10:53:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/16/southwark-gives-green-light-to-slum-landlords</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have written briefly before about the <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/SNWolverton.pdf">Aylesbury estate leaseholders</a> subjected to <a href="http://heygate.github.io/img/ObjectionCPOAugust2012.pdf">CPO proceedings</a> and how the council&rsquo;s low valuations of their homes shares similarities with the story of the Heygate&rsquo;s leaseholders.</p>

<p>Former Aylesbury leaseholder Mr Olufemi Joshua, went to the <a href="http://www.justice.gov.uk/tribunals/lands">Upper Lands Tribunal</a> last week. He was taking Southwark Council to court over the low compensation paid for the loss of his 1-bed flat and he heard some extraordinary admissions from a senior council official.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/comparison.jpg" width="300" height="300">Mr Joshua&rsquo;s barrister first revealed that the flat Southwark had used to estimate Mr Joshua&rsquo;s compensation - by way of comparison - had been illegally converted from a 1-bed into a 4-bed flat. Southwark&rsquo;s officer responded that this quite often happened and that rogue landlords could reasonably expect not to be discovered. He explained that he had used the illegally-converted flat&rsquo;s rental income as the basis for calculating Mr Joshua&rsquo;s compensation. Mr Joshua&rsquo;s 1-bed (but legal) property could not raise as much rent as the 4-bed (illegal) property, so therefore Mr J was entitled to less compensation. The council officer had used the illegally-converted flat unwittingly in assessing Mr J&rsquo;s compensation, but nonetheless defended the valuation. He also referred to another illegally-converted 1-bed property (98 Taplow) and his opinion was that investor landlords commonly take such risks.</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;The income potential [of the leaseholder&#8217;s flat] and the way it was laid out at the valuation date doesn&#8217;t give the same potential as 109 Wendover - that property having been reconfigured or converted to form additional rooms.&#8221;</p><footer><strong>Council official explaining how an Aylesbury leaseholder could have got more compensation by illegally converting his flat</strong> <cite>Lands Tribunal 14/05/14</cite></footer></blockquote>


<p>Mr Olufemi Joshua, formerly of 252 Bradenham on the Aylesbury - and now displaced to Grays - had first been offered £65k, which was later raised to £85k before the Tribunal. Mr Joshua&rsquo;s surveyor had valued his home significantly higher at £146k.</p>

<p>The illegally-converted flat (no. 109 Wendover) used for the comparison had been sold at a Savills auction in March 2013. This was around the date that Mr J left his home and so was used as a suitable &lsquo;comparable&rsquo; despite having 4 bedrooms. The <a href="http://www.eigroup.co.uk/files/55/18813/f6bc9070-cf2d-4b15-83a0-9809ff36322c.pdf">auction particulars</a> describe the property as a 4 bed flat currently rented out at £300 per week.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.eigroup.co.uk/files/55/18813/f6bc9070-cf2d-4b15-83a0-9809ff36322c.pdf"><img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/auctionparticulars.jpg"></a></p>

<p>Mr Joshua&rsquo;s surveyor presented the floor plan of the illegal flat to the Tribunal, and explained that whilst internal layouts differed, the properties were identical in overall size. He showed how rudimentary plasterboard had been used to divide the rooms, two of which were not much longer than a single mattress.</p>

<p>Mr Joshua&rsquo;s surveyor went on to claim that the council&rsquo;s valuation of the converted property as a 4-bed flat was improper, not least because it hadn&rsquo;t been registered for council tax as a 4-bed. He further pointed out that the conversion falls foul of the Housing Act&rsquo;s regulations on overcrowding and that the kitchen, bathroom and two of the newly-created bedrooms are all well below council and statutory requirements on minimum room sizes. He highlighted that the illegal conversion is also a breach of the council&rsquo;s leasehold agreement, its planning regulations and its HMO &amp; fire safety regulations.</p>

<div style="font-size:80%; text-align:center;"><a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/109Wendover.JPG"><img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/109Wendover.JPG"></a>Illegal conversion at 98 Taplow shows new plasterboard walls butted up against the middle of a window pane.</div>


<p></br>
A Land Registry search shows that the illegally-converted 1-bed flat at 98 Taplow was <a href="http://www.auctionhouse.uk.net/london/search-results.aspx?lotid=33522">bought at auction</a> by a <a href="http://www.ourproperty.co.uk/directory/14869.html">property company</a> with a <a href="http://www.blemainfinance.co.uk/">commercial buy-to-let mortgage</a>, after it was reposessed from its original owner when he was declared bankrupt in 2012. The <a href="http://www.auctionhouse.uk.net/london/search-results.aspx?lotid=33522">auction particulars</a> describe 98 Taplow as a 4-bed flat currently being let at £402 per week.</p>

<p>Around 330 leaseholders will have to leave their homes during the Aylesbury&rsquo;s 20-year redevelopment.
The mere fact that the Aylesbury is being knocked down is depressing values on the estate and Southwark shouldn&rsquo;t be using them as a point of comparison for determining market value for compensation. It should also stop using properties that have been illegally converted to maximise rental income, otherwise this could be seen as endorsement and there could be a rush to B&amp;Q to stock up on plasterboard.</p>

<p>Mr Joshua has taken a big risk with his case. Not only will he lose the legal costs he has incurred in mounting the case, but he will also have to pay those of the council should he lose. We sincerely hope that he wins and that remaining leaseholders are not put through the legal torment that he has had to suffer; they should be offered a fair price for their homes, in what is after all a scheme that was intended to benefit residents - not impoverish and displace them.</p>

<p>An audio extract of the hearing can be found on Soundcloud.com at the following url: <a href="http://soundcloud.com/user46375590/lands-tribunal-hearing-14th-may-2014-case-refacq8213-flat-252-bradenham-london-se17-2bg">http://soundcloud.com/user46375590/lands-tribunal-hearing-14th-may-2014-case-refacq8213-flat-252-bradenham-london-se17-2bg</a></p>

<p>The decision notice for Mr Joshua&rsquo;s case is due to be issued in 3-4 months and a second Aylesbury case is due to be heard on 27th May (ref: 28 Wolverton ACQ/100/13).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Heygate FOI Appeal Decision - Tribunal Delivers Verdict]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/10/foi-appeal-decision/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-10T13:47:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/10/foi-appeal-decision</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://www.burtonmail.co.uk/imagelibrary/Client%20Images/Client00004/00455000/00455204.jpg" width="210" height="150">The 35% campaign welcomes the latest - and hopefully final - decision in the battle to make the Heygate viability assessment public. The Information Tribunal has <a href="http://www.informationtribunal.gov.uk/DBFiles/Decision/i1279/London%20Borough%20of%20Southwark%20EA.2013.0162%20%2809.05.14%29.pdf">directed</a> that the whole viability assessment be made public, apart from developer Lend Lease&rsquo;s bespoke development model in the assessment&rsquo;s final appendix and the calculations concerning retail &amp; office space - all other information has to be disclosed. Lend Lease and Southwark have been given 28 days to supply the information Commmissioner with the information as outlined by the Tribunal&rsquo;s decision notice. All parties may appeal the decision but only on a point of law.</p>

<p>Southwark Council has released a <a href="http://www.southwark.gov.uk/news/article/1672/decision_on_heygate_viability_assessment_tribunal">press statement</a> also welcoming the decision. This is surprising because the FOI request for the assessment was made over two years ago and the Council has since fought tooth and nail to keep the viability asssessment secret. Southwark also misunderstands the Tribunal&rsquo;s decision notice when it claims that the Tribunal feared developers would simply refuse to work with councils. The Tribunal&rsquo;s view on this was clearly stated:</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;We are doubtful of the claimed “knock on effects” of disclosure in this case. We had evidence that Lend Lease had changed the way it gave access to data as a result of the decision – but no evidence of any project having been put in jeopardy by the ICO’s decision taken some six months ago.&#8221;</p><footer><strong>Tribunal Decision Notice</strong> <cite>Paragraph 43</cite></footer></blockquote>


<p><img class="left" src="http://static.guim.co.uk/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2011/3/2/1299076218162/Scales-of-Justice-007.jpg" width="200" height="100">Southwark Council was supported in its appeal by Lend Lease, who paid a significant proportion of the money that the council has spent fighting the appeal against the Information Commissioner&rsquo;s decision.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://hyperbolegames.com/files/2013/10/PublicInformationHelmetStickerHH0039.gif" width="150" height="150">The viability assessment enabled Lend Lease to build less affordable housing than required by planning policy. The public should now be able to see whether Southwark&rsquo;s decision to waive policy requirements was justified. It was claimed at the planning committee meeting that just 9.4% affordable housing was viable. Only 79 social-rented homes will be built on the whole Heygate development - approx 3% of the total.</p>

<p><a href="http://static.guim.co.uk/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2012/6/29/1340999473946/David-Simonds-London-prop-001.jpg"><img class="left" src="http://static.guim.co.uk/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2012/6/29/1340999473946/David-Simonds-London-prop-001.jpg" width="300" height="200"></a>The Heygate decision puts the balance of public interest with local people. Their right to information that enables them to take part in the planning process has been found to outweigh the developer&rsquo;s interest in keeping information confidential.
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;the importance, in this particular project, of local people having access to information to allow them to participate in the planning process outweighs the public interest in maintaining the remaining rights of Lend Lease&#8221;</p><footer><strong>Tribunal Decision Notice</strong> <cite>Paragraph 58</cite></footer></blockquote>


<p>We will be writing more about this as we digest the decision and what it means for housing campaign groups such as those at Greenwich Peninsula and Earls Court, which have also succeeded in obtaining the <a href="http://ico.org.uk/~/media/documents/decisionnotices/2013/fer_0491596.ashx">information commissioner&rsquo;s support</a> for disclosing viability assessments. This is a trend that we will be encouraging other campaign groups to follow.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manx Connections - the Offshore Home of the Elephant’s Developers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/05/manx-connections-the-off-shore-home-of-the-elephants-developers/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-05T07:02:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/05/05/manx-connections-the-off-shore-home-of-the-elephants-developers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_L6aHVhWUwKM/TS4-T_x7t1I/AAAAAAAABHQ/Epmn6q55hcY/s1600/Isle_of_Man1.png" width="100" height="100">
Further research as a follow-up to our <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/04/15/the-elephants-new-ivory-towers/">previous blog post</a> has uncovered some unexpected connections between the Elephant &amp; Castle and the Isle of Man. The Isle is infamous for two unsavoury practices – <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/uk/datablog/2013/apr/03/uk-companies-controlled-offshore">offshore banking</a> and <a href="http://www.corpun.com/manx.htm">corporal punishment</a>.  Corporal punishment ceased in 1981, but offshore banking remains popular, as does incorporating companies offshore to cane the backside of the British tax authorities.  We have several guilty parties at the Elephant and they include the developers of;</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Strata Tower was developed and owned by a SPV(Special Purpose Vehicle) company <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/RegisterTGL251176.pdf">registered</a> on the Isle of Man. Some of the penthouses are also <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/StrataPenthouseLRRegister.pdf">registered</a> to a SPV holding company on the Isle of Man.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7208">Tribeca Square</a> site sold to a <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/TribecaLR.pdf">company</a> based on the Isle of Man.</p></li>
<li><p>Eileen house is developed by a <a href="https://opencorporates.com/companies/im/113350C">company</a> based on the Isle of Man and which also <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/uk/2012/dec/16/london-property-tax-avoidance-offshore">helps its customers</a> avoid stamp duty by setting up SPV&rsquo;s on the Isle to buy the finished flats.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Heygate developer Lend Lease&rsquo;s global corporate structure is too complex for us to see whether it shares its fellow developer&rsquo;s fondness of offshore companies. However, we have found that its development arm - Lend Lease Residential PLC <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/lendleasefinancialreport.pdf">doesn&rsquo;t pay</a> a penny in UK corporation tax.</p>

<p>Last year Lend Lease UK&rsquo;s parent company in Australia <a href="http://phx.corporate-ir.net/External.File?item=UGFyZW50SUQ9MjA0NTA3fENoaWxkSUQ9LTF8VHlwZT0z&amp;t=1">recorded</a> an annual profit of over £300m.</p>

<p>Lend Lease has no inhibitions about profiting from public assets though. As well as the Heygate and <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/01/11/flogging-the-elephant">&lsquo;One the Elephant&rsquo;</a> developments - both on public land - it was Lend Lease&rsquo;s development arm which <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/business/analysis-and-features/millennium-dome-the-white-elephant-that-learnt-to-fly-8157301.html">bought</a> the Millenium dome plus 150 acres of Greenwich Peninsula for the princely sum of just £1. It <a href="http://www.thelondonmagazine.co.uk/property-experts/expert-opinions/the-olympic-village.html">built the Olympic Village</a> with the help of hundreds of millions in public funding, and has used more former public land for a <a href="http://phx.corporate-ir.net/phoenix.zhtml?c=186950&amp;p=RssLanding&amp;cat=news&amp;id=1888917">£1.3bn scheme</a> at Stratford.</p>

<p>We are about to get into a fresh range of ‘consultations’ for several major developments, including that for the shopping centre, and will no doubt hear the usual claims about the benefits they will bring to the community - the developers have to secure vital planning approvals, after all. The first condition of planning approval should be that the developer will not suck all the financial reward, not just out of the Elephant, but out of the country.</p>

<h2>Aylesbury Regeneration - social rent or affordable rent?</h2>

<p>Southwark Council has just signed up Notting Hill Trust as its development partner for the Aylesbury estate regeneration and this week saw an <a href="http://www.standard.co.uk/news/london/south-london-housing-estate-that-tony-blair-forgot-set-to-be-rebuilt-9309864.html">article</a> in the Evening Standard praising the regeneration plans for not following the bad example of the Heygate. While we agree that the plans do look better on paper - half of the 3,500 new properties will be ‘affordable’, of which three-quarters will be for social rent – a small alarm bell has been rung by the language used in the regeneration documents to describe the social housing element.
In the <a href="http://planningonline.southwark.gov.uk/DocsOnline/Documents/279910_1.pdf">legal agreement</a> for the most recent phase of the Aylesbury redevelopment <a href="http://www.insidehousing.co.uk/lq-wins-work-on-next-phase-of-aylesbury-plan/6522708.article">site 7</a>, the definition of &lsquo;social rented&rsquo; worryingly refers to the <a href="http://www.homesandcommunities.co.uk/ourwork/affordable-rent">HCA definition</a> of Boris&rsquo;s &lsquo;affordable rented&rsquo; housing product of up to 80% market rents:<br/>
<img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/wolvertons106SR.png"></p>

<p>Also, there is no reference to the National Rent Regime in site 7&rsquo;s legal agreement. This is the regulatory framework which decides the level of social rents based - among other things - on the average level of income, and it is standard practice for definitions in these legal agreements to include a reference to the National Rent Regime. Below is an example of the wording normally used in a standard legal agreement used for securing social rented housing:<br/>
<img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/heygates106SR.png"></p>

<p>So the worry is – what will the rent be for the new social housing?  A social rent in the Aylesbury’s SE17 area is currently about £115 pw for a 2-bed flat; on the other hand one of  Mr Johnson’s ‘affordable rents would be way beyond this at around £240pw if it were at 80% of market rent.</p>

<h2>FOI appeal update</h2>

<p>Apologies to those who have been following this appeal and were expecting a decision from the Information Tribunal last week. Unfortunately the decision has been delayed once again and is not now expected to be released until the end of May. We will keep you informed as and when we manage to find out more details on this.</p>

<h2>Is there a doctor in the house?</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/doctor.jpg">Regenerations provide homes, jobs, new trees etc but a serious side effect can be self-delusion; symptoms include a tendency to ignore or mangle the facts and wishful thinking.  It can strike anyone after long exposure to the regeneration industry, but those most at risk include councillors, council officers and, unfortunately, architects.
A recent sad case has just come to our attention.  It concerns a Mr P, senior architect and masterplanner of the New Heygate.  The symptoms of his condition are manifested by confusion over numbers, a hazy recollection of past events and an inability to appreciate the effects of his actions on others.
Mr P’s delusions (see here – <a href="http://youtu.be/a-W6wwVj5dA">http://youtu.be/a-W6wwVj5dA</a> and <a href="http://youtu.be/vyQyt0T1Iho">http://youtu.be/vyQyt0T1Iho</a>) include the belief that only 800 people were forced of the Heygate estate to make way for his masterplan (it was nearer 3000); that they all moved into new homes on early housing sites (they didn’t because none had been built), that 83% of them agreed to this ‘through the democratic process’ (they didn’t, because here was never any ballot, still usual in democracies); that they can even now return to the New Heygate (they can’t, because Mr P’s new homes  will be too expensive, whether you’re an ex-tenant or ex-leaseholder).
Unfortunately facts are seldom a cure in such serious cases, but these may prevent Mr P’s condition becoming contagious, and we nonetheless remain hopeful for his speedy recovery.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Elephant's New Ivory Towers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/04/15/the-elephants-new-ivory-towers/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-15T12:37:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/04/15/the-elephants-new-ivory-towers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<center>
<iframe src="http://www.35percent.org/ivorytowers" width="600" height="400"></iframe>
</br><font size="2">Click <a href="http://www.35percent.org/ivorytowers">here</a> to view our interactive map in a separate browser window</font>
</center>


<p></br>
As part of our evidence gathering for the Heygate <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/02/11/heygate-tribunal-hearing-extended/">FOI appeal hearing</a>, we undertook some analysis of the planning applications behind the Elephant&rsquo;s new high-rise developments. After sifting through pages of planning documents we managed to extract some key figures and have come up with the following startling results:</p>

<ul>
<li>The six largest developments comprise a total of 4,282 new homes of which just 79 will be social rented.<a href="#footnote-1">[1]</a></li>
<li>Viability assessments helped developers avoid £265m in off-site affordable housing tariff payments required by policy.</li>
<li>All six developments are situated on former public-owned land.</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/interactivemapfigures.pdf"><img src="http://www.35percent.org/images/interactivemapfigures.png"></a></p>

<p>In order to crunch the numbers properly we had to obtain the total number of habitable rooms in each development. This is how the 35% policy requirement is worked out: 35% of the total number of habitable rooms must be affordable and 50% of these must be social rented as per Southwark&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/spdpg38.pdf">planning policy requirements</a> at the Elephant. It is worth reiterating that these policy requirements are based on an independent council-commissioned <a href="https://www.southwark.gov.uk/downloads/download/1822/southwark_affordable_housing_viability_study">viability study</a> ensuring that this minimum level of affordable housing requirements is indeed viable.</p>

<p>Next we took the number of habitable rooms sorted by type of affordable housing in each development. We subtracted this from the number of each type required by policy and then multiplied it by the Council&rsquo;s off-site affordable housing <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/affordablehousingspg.pdf">tariff</a> for the Elephant &amp; Castle area. This is the amount a developer must pay if they fail to meet the 35% on-site affordable housing minimum requirement. However, policy also says that this in-lieu payment can further be reduced if the developer submits a viability appraisal pleading viability poverty. Our analysis shows that this loophole has meant a loss to the Council of £265m in off-site tariff payments, in what has become habitual practice by developers not just at the Elephant but across the borough.</p>

<p>Our findings also formed the basis for <a href="http://www.35percent.org/images/35percentFALP.pdf">our response</a> to the Mayor&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.london.gov.uk/priorities/planning/london-plan/draft-further-alterations-to-the-london-plan">draft further alterations to the London Plan</a>.</p>

<h2>FOI Tribunal update</h2>

<p>For those who have been following our FOI appeal updates and are wondering what the Informaton Tribunal&rsquo;s decision on the appeal is, the good news is that there are only 10 more days to wait. The decision was originally delayed due to the judge&rsquo;s ill-health but is now due to be announced on 25th April - watch this space!</p>

<p><font size="1"><p id="footnote-1">[1] Note that our list does not include the Newington Triangle or shopping centre developments (totalling approx 1,500 more homes) - for which there are no planning applications yet submitted, but which have been rumoured not to foresee the inclusion of any social rented homes. </p></font></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Middlemen on the Make]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/03/31/middlemen-on-the-make/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-31T07:32:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/03/31/middlemen-on-the-make</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/imageuploads/1299150006_80.177.117.97.jpg" width="300" height="200">It was <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7460">announced</a> earlier this month that the Elephant’s 360 tower is in line for yet more public funding. As mentioned in a <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2013/08/10/towering-disgrace">previous blog post</a>, the land for this private development was purchased with £18m of public money back in 2007 to provide key worker housing by English Partnerships, a public housing agency. This all fell through and the development was eventually awarded last summer to developers <a href="http://www.essentialliving.uk.com/developments/360-london/">Essential Living</a> by Mayor Boris Johnson. The 360 Tower is now on the short-list for funding from the government&rsquo;s £1bn build-to-rent scheme, which is designed to help developers build large-scale housing developments specifically for private rent.</p>

<p>Why Essential Living should need help to build homes it will be letting at handsome profit in a booming property market is not clear, particularly when the Tower will not provide any social rented housing (there will be a meagre 29 units of so-called ‘affordable rent’ instead). There will be 159 units for shared ownership, provided without any government grant, but if the developer is getting subsidy instead for its private rented homes then it’s hardly needed. The public purse will be paying for the free-market housing that pays for the affordable housing, which seems to make the developer a bit redundant from our point of view - why bother with the middle man? There is a chance that some money may be recouped on the initial land cost; one of the GLA’s objectives is ‘a land payment at the earliest opportunity representing best value for the GLA but on a partial deferred basis’ – how much this will be remains to be seen; Elephant land values have varied wildly.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>MIPIM</strong></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://static.guim.co.uk/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2014/3/14/1394794674203/MIPIM-011.jpg" width="300" height="200">After <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/6687">bad press</a> following its developer-funded visit last year, Southwark very wisely pulled out of last week&rsquo;s developer jamboree known as the MIPIM event in Cannes on the French riviera. Housing campaigners from all over Europe protested against the sale of our cities, particularly by our public authorities as related in <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/society/2014/mar/14/anger-cannes-property-fair-councils-%0Adevelopers-mipim">this Guardian article</a>. Those from London were organised by the <a href="http://radicalhousingnetwork.org/">Radical Housing Network</a> and included Campaigners from Southwark.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Strata Tower occupation</strong></p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://southwarktenants.files.wordpress.com/2014/03/we-protest.jpg?w=300&h=225">Closer to home there was more radical action against MIPIM, when <a href="http://southwarktenants.wordpress.com/">Southwark Tenants</a> occupied a flat in the infamous Strata Tower to protest against social cleansing and Strataspheric private rents, and housing activists <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7449">protested</a> outside City Hall.<br/>
</br>
</br>
</br></p>

<hr />

<p><strong>TfL - Northern Roundabout Plans</strong></p>

<p>The long-promised public <a href="https://consultations.tfl.gov.uk/roads/elephant-and-castle">consultation on TFL&rsquo;s plans</a> for Elephant &amp; Castle&rsquo;s northern roundabout started last week. The new plans have unlocked the delayed development of the shopping centre and the new transport layout will have a critical impact on the Elephant&rsquo;s regeneration. There are critical local voices though - the SOS campaign (Save our Subways) is canvassing local views through this website: <a href="http://elephantandcastleroundabout.org/">http://elephantandcastleroundabout.org/</a></p>

<p>TFL will be holding an exhibition where the public will have an opportunity to view detailed maps of the scheme and speak to its designers.</p>

<p>The exhibition will take place at:Typo Cafe, London College of Communication, Elephant &amp; Castle, London SE1 6SB</p>

<p>Saturday 29 March 11:30 – 15:30</p>

<p>The consultation closes 30 April 2014.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mission Possible - Bringing Viability Assessments Out of the Dark]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/02/22/viability-assessment-says-no/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-22T12:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.35percent.org/blog/2014/02/22/viability-assessment-says-no</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://www.35percent.org/images/confidential.jpg" width="300" height="200">Following the successful FOI request by Heygate campaigners, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/davehillblog/2013/nov/21/earls-court-project-community-benefits-capital-and-counties">Earls Court</a> community activists have also succeeded with their FOI request for disclosure of viability documents behind their local regeneration scheme, which - like the Heygate - has a great absence of truly affordable housing. The Information Commissioner cites the Heygate decision in his <a href="http://ico.org.uk/~/media/documents/decisionnotices/2013/fer_0491596.ashx">decision notice</a>.</p>

<p>However, just as at the Elephant, local authority (Kensington &amp; Chelsea) and developer (Capital &amp; Counties Ltd.) have combined together to appeal against the Information Commissioner&rsquo;s decision. The appeal hearing is due to take place at the beginning of June.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://www.propertyreporter.co.uk/images/slider/1103231_Scales.gif">Meanwhile the sixth and final day&rsquo;s hearing against disclosure of the Heygate Masterplan viability assessment took place on Tuesday. The Tribunal heard arguments from barristers representing Lend Lease &amp; Southwark Council on one side, and the Information Commissioner and ex-Heygate resident Adrian Glasspool on the other.</p>

<p>The differences between the two sides were brought into focus. Lend Lease argued amongst other things that the public interest is best served by protecting its own commercial interests. Southwark pointed to the disruption that it claimed disclosure would bring to the regeneration process. The Information Commissioner robustly defended his decision to order disclosure on the grounds of enabling effective participation in the planning process. Mr Glasspool&rsquo;s barrister emphasised the departures from Southwark Council&rsquo;s own planning policies, not just regarding affordable housing but also car parking.</p>

<h4>Data Lockdown</h4>


<p><img class="right" src="http://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2013/05/07/article-2320579-19A78BC8000005DC-582_634x934.jpg" width="200" height="400">Amongst the interesting facts to come out was that no planning officer had actually seen the viability assessment. This job was given to the District Valuer Service (DVS). Also, Lend Lease no longer shares information with Southwark Council in the same way; it has established a restricted-access &lsquo;data room&rsquo; which admits only selected Southwark Council officers on a need-to-know basis.</p>

<p>Lend Lease also emphasised the Human Rights aspect of its argument: as a legal person it has the right to &lsquo;peaceful enjoyment of its possessions&rsquo; and the unjustified interference with this enjoyment that would be entailed by disclosing the viability assessment. The Information Commissioner robustly rejected this argument.</p>

<p>Southwark offered the argument that the public had ample opportunity to influence the planning decision through the extensive consultation process, and through to the final decisions about the s106 agreement. They also argued that there could be no public interest in disclosing a very hefty and complicated document, which many would simply not be able to understand.</p>

<p><strong>Viability Assessment says NO!</strong><br/>
<img class="right" src="http://i.telegraph.co.uk/multimedia/archive/02419/jobs0_3_2419481b.jpg" width="300" height="200">Contrary to Southwark and Lend Lease, Mr Glasspool&rsquo;s barrister made powerful arguments that the public interest lay in allowing the local community full participation in the planning process: the local community had played an extensive part in consultations, but had been thwarted by the use of the viability assessment; its secrecy was an obstacle to understanding how the loss of public benefit promised by the regeneration was justified. She pointed out the dangers of public policy decisions being made when only one side is in full possession of the facts. Lend Lease&rsquo;s answer to any questions about the loss of affordable housing or maintaining a car-free development was simply &ldquo;Viability assessment says no!&rdquo;.<br/>
A decision is expected within around 4 weeks.</p>

<p></br>
<strong>Peabody Triangle - two more faulty towers?</strong><br/>
<img class="left" src="http://static.panoramio.com/photos/large/56023043.jpg" width="200" height="200">Peabody Trust held an exhibition of <a href="http://www.london-se1.co.uk/news/view/7342">plans for its Newington Triangle development</a> last Saturday. The triangle is currently occupied by the Institute of Optometry, parts of Southbank University and the London School of Musical Theatre (pictured). It is nonetheless a development site that has passed to the Peabody Trust from a private developer. Peabody plans to build 550 residential units and a new HQ for themselves. While it is reported that there is going to be 35% affordable housing, more worryingly this might not include any social rented units. We hope this is not the case and Peabody&rsquo;s proposed two towers do not join the Elephant&rsquo;s other <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2013/08/10/towering-disgrace">&lsquo;Towers of Shame&rsquo;</a>), notorious for having no social rented housing. Peabody are the preferred providers of the affordable housing at the recently-approved <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2013/08/10/towering-disgrace">London 360 Tower</a> just around the corner. This has no social-rented housing, just 29 units of so-called &lsquo;affordable rent&rsquo;. <br/>
</br>
<strong>Lend Lease doing well down under</strong> <br/>
<img class="left" src="http://www.oneplanetcommunities.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/Barangaroo-waterfront.jpg" width="300" height="200">Lend Lease has just <a href="http://www.smh.com.au/nsw/court-ruling-over-barangaroo-may-put-public-works-at-risk-20140107-30fhg.html">won a legal battle</a> against a Sydney public authority. The dispute was about how much Lend Lease would pay in so-called &lsquo;overage&rsquo; or value share payments, which is a kind of surplus profit share agreement - similar to the one we have at the Elephant. The decision has left the Sydney authority short of the money it needs to deliver public benefits it expected in return for handing over the prime public land for private development.</p>

<p>The Barangaroo development has other <a href="http://www.35percent.org/blog/2012/12/09/has-southwark-signed-a-bum-deal-at-the-elephant">familiar elements</a> - it includes the provision of a public park, which looks doubtful now the authority has lost its money, although it does plan to appeal.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
